College of Architecture

COLLEGE: College of Architecture

MAJORS: Architecture, Landscape Architecture, Interior Design

ADMISSION

Admission to the College of Architecture

Admission to the University of Nebraska–Lincoln does not constitute admission to the College of Architecture. Students seeking enrollment in the College of Architecture should indicate their desire by marking the proper major code on the University application form.

Freshmen students applying for admission to the Pre-Architecture and Pre-Landscape Architecture Program must submit complete admission application materials by March 15. Please note this is different from the standard university procedures. Freshmen students applying for admission to the Pre-Interior Design Program must submit complete admission application materials by May 1 for fall admission and December 1 for spring admission. Transfer students must present materials by February 15. These admission procedures apply to high school students seeking admission, as well as transfer students, international students, and also those transferring from UNO and UNK to UNL.

High School Standards Pre-Architecture Program

Prospective students interested in the Professional Program in Architecture are eligible to apply for admission into the pre-architecture major if their high school records meet the following standards:

1. Mathematics–4 units of Algebra I, II, geometry, and one-half unit of trigonometry, and one-half unit that builds on a knowledge of algebra or pre-calculus.

2. English–4 units of intensive reading and writing.

3. Social Studies–3 units. At least one unit of American and/or world history and one additional unit of history, American government, and/or geography.

4. Natural Science–3 units. At least two of the three units selected from biology, chemistry, physics, and earth sciences. One of the units must include a laboratory.

5. Foreign Language–2 units.

Deficiencies

Students who are admitted through the Admission by Review process with core course deficiencies will have certain conditions attached to their enrollment at UNL.

High School Standards Pre-Interior Design Program

Prospective students interested in the Interior Design Program are eligible for admission to the pre-interior design major if their high school records meet the following standards:

1. Mathematics-4 units of Algebra I, II, geometry, and one additional unit that builds on a knowledge of algebra.

2. English-4 units of intensive reading and writing.

3. Social Studies-3 units. At least one unit of American and/or world history and one additional unit of history, American government, and/or geography.

4. Natural Science-3 units. At least two of the three units selected from biology, chemistry, physics, and earth sciences. One of the units must include a laboratory.

5. Foreign Language-2 units.

Deficiencies

Each application that does not meet the requirements for Assured Admission will automatically receive individual review. The applicant’s total academic record and performance will be taken into consideration. If admitted, all deficiencies will have to be made up within the first academic year and are governed by University policies for removal of deficiencies.

High School Standards Pre-Landscape Architecture Program

Prospective students interested in the Professional Program in Landscape Architecture are eligible to apply for admission into the pre-architecture major if their high school records meet the following standards:

1. Mathematics–4 units of Algebra I, II, geometry, and one-half unit of trigonometry, and one-half unit that builds on a knowledge of algebra or pre-calculus.

2. English–4 units of intensive reading and writing.

3. Social Studies–3 units. At least one unit of American and/or world history and one additional unit of history, American government, and/or geography.

4. Natural Science–3 units. At least one of these units must include chemistry with a lab. Two other units can be from biology, physics, and/or earth sciences.

5. Foreign Language–2 units.

Admission Deficiencies/Removal of Deficiencies

Each application that does not meet the requirements for Assured Admission will automatically receive individual review. The applicant’s total academic record and performance will be taken into consideration. If admitted, all deficiencies will have to be made up within the first academic year and are governed by University policies for removal of deficiencies.

General Admission Requirements for the College of Architecture

In addition to the high school admission requirements, the College of Architecture has established the following general admission requirements for all undergraduate students.

New freshman students must:

Graduate in the upper quartile of their high school class, or
Have an enhanced ACT composite score of 22, or
Have a combined SAT verbal and math total of at least 1030 enhanced, or
Receive permission from the chair of the department with a waiver from the above requirements.

New international freshman students must:

Meet UNL entrance requirements for new international freshman students, and
Have a MELAB score of at least 80 or a minimum TOEFL score of 550, or computer-based score of 213 or 79-80 Internet-based.

New transfer students must:

Have a minimum 3.0 cumulative GPA for architecture and landscape architecture or 3.0 for interior design and be in good scholastic standing.

NOTE: New transfer students must comply with new freshman student entrance requirements if they have completed less than 12 credit hours of college study.

New international transfer students must:

Meet UNL entrance requirements for international transfer students
Have a MELAB score of at least 80 or a minimum TOEFL score of 550, or computer-based score of 213, or Internet-based score of 79-80
Have a minimum 3.0 cumulative GPA and be in good scholastic standing

Students who transfer into the College of Architecture from other colleges at UNL must:

Have a minimum 3.0 cumulative GPA for architecture and landscape architecture or 3.0 for interior design and be in good scholastic standing. Students transferring from UNO and UNK are included in the new transfer student category.

NOTE: New transfer students must comply with new freshman student entrance requirements if they have completed less than 12 credit hours of college study.

Readmission

Students who apply for readmission to the College of Architecture must have a minimum 3.0 cumulative GPA for architecture and landscape architecture or 3.0 for interior design, be in good scholastic standing and receive permission from the Dean of the College. Students may apply for admittance into the Pre-Architecture, Pre-Landscape Architecture, and Pre-Interior Design Program a maximum of three times.

Former students who withdraw after being admitted to the College, or who have been academically suspended and wish to be readmitted must: a) be readmitted to the College in good scholastic standing, and b) be in good scholastic standing in accordance with the departmental standards and receive permission from the chair of the department. Applicants for readmission will compete for spaces available with all other admission applicants.

ADVISING

Academic Advising

The College of Architecture is committed to providing effective advising services to students as an essential component of their educational experience.

Students in the Architecture, Interior Design, and Landscape Architecture Programs are assigned to a staff adviser. These advisers are located in the Programs Office to afford students easy access to information and to the program directors should this be necessary or desirable. Students are also given access to an advisers Web site developed specifically for the College.

After admission into their respective professional program, students are assigned a faculty adviser. This person serves as an important resource for questions about the professions, their future careers, and their academic plans and progress. Students are encouraged to regularly consult with their adviser and are responsible for initiating advising contacts and preparing for advising sessions. Students must consult with their adviser prior to registering for classes. Failure to do so may result in removal from classes. Ultimately, students are themselves responsible for fulfilling all the requirements of the curriculum in which they are enrolled. The intellectual mentoring relationship between academic adviser and student is protected by confidentiality and strengthened by listening with understanding to student concerns.

The program office houses student records and the staff is helpful in checking on degree requirements and University procedures and policies.

The program office provides information for prospective and entering students who are seeking admission to the College of Architecture.

ACADEMIC PROGRAMS & POLICIES

Academic Load

Students in the bachelor of science in design (BSD) degree program must be enrolled in 12 credit hours of course work to be classified as a full time student. Students in the master of architecture degree program must be enrolled in 9 credit hours of course work to be classified as a full time student. Students participating in one of the department’s study abroad programs enrolled in less than the credit hours specified above may also be classified as full time students with permission of the chair.

BSD students must obtain permission from the chair of the department to enroll in more than 17 credit hours prior to the start of the semester. Students in the MArch program must obtain similar permission to exceed 15 credit hours.

Employment and Course Load Guidelines

The study of architecture is a demanding discipline requiring a significant commitment to succeed. For this reason, the department has adopted a policy recommending students who are employed to not exceed the following registration guidelines:

Work load per week

|

Course load per semester

0 hours

|

up to 18 credit hours

8-16 hours

|

13-16 credit hours

17-20 hours

|

10-12 credit hours

Full time

|

up to 6 cr hours

Professional students holding teaching or research assistantships are required to be enrolled as a student in the professional program and their course load cannot exceed 12 credit hours per semester. Students holding these positions are prohibited from engaging in any other form of remunerative employment without the permission of the program director.

Course Exclusions & Restrictions

Military Science, Naval Science, Aerospace Studies and/or Physical Education

A maximum combination of courses in these areas totaling 6 credit hours can be applied toward the bachelor of science in design degree as elective credit.

Drop/Add

The university’s drop/add policy is outlined in the Schedule of Classes each semester. The professional program subscribes to the same rules and limitations indicated in this publication. In general, classes can only be added during the first week of the semester. You may drop a class from your schedule anytime during the first eleven weeks of the semester. After the eleventh week, withdrawal from the class is possible only for extraordinary circumstances and will be granted only by petition. Grounds for extraordinary withdrawal include: military service, medical illness, death in immediate family, personal trauma, or complete absence from all courses without officially withdrawing.

The specific deadline for dropping a class is listed in the Schedule of Classes. Students can access eNroll or use the NRoll telephone registration system (402-472-7272) to drop or add classes. Please be warned, failure to attend classes does not constitute proper notification of dropping a class. If you are unable to attend classes, you need to see or telephone your instructor as soon as possible. Failure to do so may jeopardize your chances for dropping the class. If you wish to drop all your courses, you need to use the Withdrawal from the University form. See the section below for a description of this process.

The Drop/Add form is available in the Program Office.

Dual Degrees

Joint Degree Programs

Civil Engineering

The departments of civil engineering and architecture offer a joint degree program of study. This program allows the student to obtain the masters degree in architecture and the bachelors degree in civil engineering after seven years of study. A suggested sequence of courses can be obtained from your adviser or the program office. Special advising for this program is provided by Professor Kuska.

Business

Architecture majors accepted to the 5th and 6th years may choose to pursue a three-year course of study that leads to joint degrees of master of architecture and master of business administration. Participation in this joint degree program requires admission into both the MArch and MBA programs. Students should consult with their adviser to develop an appropriate plan.

Community and Regional Planning

Architecture majors accepted to the 5th and 6th years may choose to pursue a course of study that leads to joint degrees of master of architecture and master of community and regional planning. A suggested sequence of courses can be obtained from your adviser, the Architecture Program Office, or the Community and Regional Planning Program Office.

Construction Management

Architecture majors accepted to the 5th and 6th years may pursue a course of study that leads to joint degrees of master of architecture and master of engineering in construction management. This requires acceptance by the Construction Management Program. The required course sequence can be obtained from your adviser.

Enrollment Policy

College of Architecture Enrollment Policy

Enrollment in the pre-architecture, pre-interior design, and pre-landscape architecture majors shall be limited by available teaching resources and space capacities, therefore an enrollment limit is established for each of these programs.

Admission to the Pre-Architecture, Pre-Interior Design, and Pre-Landscape Architecture Programs occurs year-round; however, access to studio courses is not guaranteed for those students admitted beyond the February 15th deadline for transfer students or March 15th deadline for freshmen.

Probation, Appeals and Dismissal

BSD students who are placed on probation will not be allowed to take any new architecture or interior design courses without the permission of the program director. Students will be allowed to retake architecture and interior design courses while on probation. Students may not take the same course more than three times.

Students in the BSD degree program placed on academic probation by the College for two consecutive semesters will be transferred out of the College of Architecture into General Studies and must reapply for admission to the College and the Architecture, Landscape Architecture, or Interior Design Programs. Students must have a cumulative GPA of 3.0 to be readmitted from General Studies into architecture and 2.8 into interior design.

Students in the MArch program placed on probation will be allowed to continue with their classes for one semester. If their next semester grade point average is below a 3.0 they are dismissed from the degree program. Students desiring to be readmitted will have to apply for admission to the professional program.

Students who register for new architecture or interior design courses while on probation will be administratively dropped from those courses unless they have received the permission of the program chair.

Registration Limits

Students are not allowed to register for 300-800 level architecture or interior design courses unless they have been admitted into their respective professional programs. Some specific courses allow registration of non-majors with permission of the faculty member teaching the course but this permission process is not available to majors.

The programs have adopted limits on the number of credit hours a student can register for without the permission of the Chair. Students in good academic standing are allowed to register for a maximum of 17 credit hours. Students wishing to exceed this number must secure permission from the Chair prior to registering for the courses. Under no circumstances can a student register for more than 19 hours in a semester.

Students who are on academic probation are restricted to a maximum number of 12 credit hours. Under no circumstances will they be allowed to exceed this number while on probation. For more specific limitations for students on academic probation see the text on Academic Standing earlier in this section.

Student Recognition

Dean’s List

Each semester, select undergraduate students enrolled in the College of Architecture are recognized for their scholastic accomplishments by being named to the Dean’s List. Criteria for this honor are:

1. Students must earn a semester (not cumulative) GPA that ranks them in the upper ten percent of the College’s enrollment.

2. Students must earn a minimum of 12 graded credit hours during that semester. (Pass/No Pass credit cannot be applied toward the 12 required credit hours.)

Graduation With Distinction and With High Distinction

Students with outstanding scholastic records may earn the special honor of graduation With Distinction or With High Distinction. One student each graduation may be chosen to graduate With Highest Distinction. Requirements for these honors are listed below.

Graduation With Distinction shall be awarded to students earning at least 60 credit hours in residence at UNL who are in the 90th percentile of those graduating in the prior twelve month period or who have a minimum 3.6 cumulative GPA.

Graduation With High Distinction shall be awarded to students in the top half of those who meet the qualifications for graduation with distinction and have a minimum 3.8 cumulative GPA.

Graduation With Highest Distinction may be awarded by selection of the faculty to a student who meets the qualifications for graduation with high distinction and has also demonstrated outstanding professional excellence through creative work.

International Studies Programs

China. The College of Architecture has a formal agreement for an exchange of faculty and students with the Northwest Institute of Architectural Engineering at Xian, People’s Republic of China. This exchange program was initiated in 1989.

Dublin, Ireland. During the fall semester, qualified students in the Department of Architecture can elect to study in Dublin, Ireland. Under an agreement with the Dublin Institute of Technology, students have an opportunity to complete one semester of their requirements toward a degree at UNL.

Hannover, Germany. During the spring semester, qualified students in the fourth or fifth year of the BSD program can elect to study in Hannover, Germany. Under an agreement with Hannover University, students have an opportunity to complete one semester of their requirements toward a degree at UNL.

Clermont-Ferrand, France. During the spring semester, qualified students in the fourth or fifth year of the BSD program can elect to study in Clermont-Ferrand, France. Under an agreement with the university, students have an opportunity to complete one semester of their requirements toward a degree at UNL.

London, England. During each spring semester, qualified students may elect one semester of resident studies in London, England. The program offers students enrolled in the architecture (5th or 6th years), interior design (4th year), or landscape architecture (4th year) programs the opportunity to study urban and architectural design in a cross-cultural and comparative manner. Under the direction of a faculty member in either the architecture, interior design, or landscape architecture programs, the program is annually accommodated by a wealth of historic and modern case materials with cooperative assistance from educators and practicing professionals in the London area. Stephan Rienke (AIA, RIBA) serves as adjunct professor to the College and provides invaluable professional and cultural assistance to visiting UNL faculty and students.

Tianjin, China. During each fall semester, qualified students may elect a semester of resident studies in Tianjin, China. The program offers students enrolled in the architecture (5th or 6th year) or landscape architecture (5th year) the opportunity to study design in an urban environment with cross-cultural influences. Under the direction of a faculty member of either architecture or landscape architecture, the program offers students a rich experience. Working with the urban design and planning office of KX International Design and Planning.

Monteverde, Costa Rica. During the summer 3-week pre-session, the Community and Regional Planning Department offers a 3-credit advanced field studies course in Costa Rica, covering basic field techniques in environmental, social and economic aspects of sustainable community planning in developing regions and sensitive environments.

Senior Check/Degree Audit

Senior and Professional Check and Application for Degree

During the last semester of the third year of study, senior checks are to be initiated by the student and reviewed by the student’s adviser. The senior check forms are maintained by the adviser and filed in the students’ advising folders.

Students must complete senior checks with their advisers and, after the adviser signs off on it, submit them to the Program Office for final processing and approval during early registration for their last semester in the BSD program.

A similar procedure applies to students in the MArch and BLA programs. The professional check will be initiated in the student’s first year in the program. The final check, with their adviser and submittal to the Program Office for processing and approval, should occur during the early registration period for the last semester in the MArch program.

Students in both the BSD and MArch degree programs must also file a graduation notice with the Credentials Office early in the semester in which they intend to graduate. Failure to meet the published deadline will delay graduation one full term.

Substitutions and Waivers

Students wishing to propose a course substitution in their curriculum of study must petition the Professional Program Committee by completing a substitution form. The substitution form should be filled out in consultation with your academic adviser. All proposals must include a detailed explanation for the substitution. The student’s adviser must review and sign the completed form before it can be submitted to the Professional Program Committee. It is very important that these procedures be followed for an expeditious response to the proposal. Substitutions must be approved before enrolling in a substitute course.

Students are advised the Professional Program Committee meets once a month, and will not consider any substitution proposals without a completed form and explanation signed by their adviser. The process to obtain a course substitution is lengthy and can not be accomplished at the “eleventh hour” to compensate for poor academic planning.

Copies of the substitution form are available in the Program Office.

Internships

Architecture Internship

An internship program is available to students who have completed the BSD or its equivalent before or during the 5th and 6th year of the Professional Program in Architecture. Academic credits will be given (up to 6 hours) for this internship experience. Students will be required to apply for acceptance into the program and will be monitored by the program’s internship coordinator.

Interior Design Internship

All students enrolled in the Interior Design Program need to complete an approved internship as part of their professional requirements. Students are not eligible for an internship until they are enrolled in, or have completed, IDES 351 Interior Design Studio 2.

Landscape Architecture Internship

All students enrolled in the Landscape Architecture Program need to complete an internship as a part of their professional requirements. Academic credit will be given (up to 6 hours) for this internship experience. The internship program is available to students who have completed the BSD program.

Planning Internship

The Community and Regional Planning Program recommends that students without previous work experience in planning complete a field internship as part of the MCRP program. The internship involves a training period of actual service in a public or private organization.

The field experience component of the MCRP program provides an excellent means for students to augment and expand their planning skills, to more closely examine their career aspirations, and to evaluate their academic progress. Internships provide students with unique learning experiences that are impossible to replicate in the classroom. Many internships provide financial assistance for students while they are in school and often facilitate their search for employment after graduation. The internship component of the MCRP program also is an important vehicle for fulfilling the public service mission of the Community and Regional Planning Program, the College of Architecture, and the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.

ACE REQUIREMENTS

Achievement-Centered Education (ACE)

The University of Nebraska–Lincoln requires all students receive a broad general education as part of their academic experience. This requirement translates into the obligation of all students to fulfill the requirements of the ACE program. Information about the ACE program may be viewed at ace.unl.edu.

English

It is of vital importance that architects and interior designers be able to express themselves clearly and concisely. As a matter of routine, architects and interior designers are called upon to prepare reports, papers, or specifications in which clarity and precision are essential. For this reason, a student is required to do more than meet the English composition course requirement. In daily oral and written work the student must demonstrate an acceptable skill in the use of effective English. The dean may require students who fail to meet acceptable standards to do additional work in English composition or speech communication. Each instructor is expected to bring to the dean’s attention the students who need additional work.

Students are expected to take ENGL 101 plus ENGL 151. Or they may take ENGL 150 plus ENGL 151. ENGL 186, 187 and 192 may not be used to satisfy the freshman English composition requirement.

Mathematics

Students in the Architecture Program are required to receive credit for MATH 106. Courses taken as deficiencies to qualify for MATH 106 will not apply as credit toward their degree. Students in Landscape Architecture are required to take either MATH 106 or STAT 218 to fulfill their mathematics requirement. Students in the Interior Design Program are required to take either MATH 203 or STAT 218 to fulfill their mathematics requirement.

BULLETIN RULE

Degree Time Limits

Students will be required to complete course work for their degree within a ten year period from the time they are admitted into the professional program in the third year.

COLLEGE DEGREE REQUIREMENTS

Minimum Hours Required for Graduation

BSD in Architecture – 129 hours

BSD in Interior Design – 129 hours

BSD in Landscape Architecture – 129 hours

Grading Appeals

A student wishing to appeal a grade should contact his or her professor for clarification first before an appeal can be filed. If the dispute cannot be resolved with the instructor it is recommended that the student meet with their adviser to get clarification on the appeals process. Appeals are only considered where it can be demonstrated that prejudice or capricious treatment influenced the grade received by the student.

Having exhausted these avenues, a student may then choose to make a formal appeal. The appeal is in the form of a written statement from the student to the program chair. The Chair will then forward the letter to the Faculty Affairs Committee. The deadline for filing a grade appeal (which includes a written statement from the student) is 30 calendar days after the first day of classes of the next regular semester (fall or spring). Appeals filed after the deadline will not be heard.

Incomplete Grades

Incompletes for students in the pre-professional program shall be granted only for reasons outlined in the policy statement adopted by the University Senate. See the UNL Schedule of Classes for the complete text.

Incompletes given to students in the professional program are granted at the discretion of the faculty awarding the grade. The faculty and student together must file an incomplete form in the department office to register the anticipated completion date and the grade that will be registered if the work is not completed by that time.

Architecture students will be allowed a maximum of two weeks to remove incompletes from courses that are prerequisites to classes in which they are currently enrolled or they will be administratively dropped from those courses.

Scholastic Standing

The following scholastic standards have been established to maintain the level of quality for students enrolled in the Architecture Program:

Pre-Professional Program, Architecture, Landscape Architecture and Interior Design

Students in the first year are required to maintain both a semester and cumulative grade point average at or above 2.0. The standard rises to a grade point average of 2.6 in the second year. Admission into the third year of all programs requires a cumulative grade point average of 2.6. The College places students who fail to meet these standards on academic probation.

Third and Fourth Year, Architecture

Students in the third and fourth year of the BSD program are required to meet two parallel academic standards. First the student must maintain a semester grade point average of 2.6 to remain in good academic standing. The Program places students who fail to meet this standard on academic probation. Further, students whose GPA for the academic year is between 2.6 and 3.0 are required to submit their studio work for review by the Student Affairs Committee for determination of continuance in the program or repetition of the year’s studio sequence.

Third and Fourth Year, Interior Design and Landscape Architecture

Students in the third and fourth year of the BSD program are required to maintain a 2.6 cumulative grade point average to remain in good academic standing. The Program also requires that students earn a grade of a C or higher in all required courses. The Program places students who fail to meet this standard on academic probation.

Fifth and Sixth Year, Architecture

Students in the MArch program are required to maintain a semester grade point average of 3.0 to remain in good academic standing. The Program places students who fail to meet this standard on academic probation.

Minimum Grades

Students must earn at least a C (2.0) in all courses with an ARCH, IDES, or LARC prefix to earn credit toward their degree. Students will be required to retake all core required courses with a grade of C- or below, but will not be required to repeat courses that were taken as electives.

Removal of Grades C- or Below

A professional student receiving a grade of C- or below for an overall course grade may remove that grade by retaking the same course again and receiving a higher grade. The higher grade will be used to compute the student’s cumulative grade point average, but all grades appear on the student’s transcript. The Pass/No Pass option cannot be used to remove these grades from the grade point average. Please be advised that once a course is no longer taught and no longer offered by the department it is not possible to remove a grade of C- or below through substitution or any other means.

Should you perform poorly in many courses during a semester it is possible to bankrupt the entire semester’s grades. This is a drastic action and should be pursued only after a visit with your adviser.

Pass/No Pass Limits

None of the required classes offered in the professional program are offered Pass/No Pass, but a maximum of 12 Pass/No Pass credit hours of humanities, social sciences, or open electives may be taken from departments outside the College of Architecture.

Courses taken outside the Architecture or Interior Design Programs to fulfill the upper level outside elective requirement at the 800 level or 900 level, with or without a 400-level counterpart, in a minor, collateral, or supporting area of work, can be taken on a Pass/No Pass basis.

Transfer Credit Rules

All professional credit earned at another university to be applied toward the master of architecture degree must be approved by the Professional Program Committee in cooperation with the program director. At least 50 percent of the required course work for the professional degree must be completed at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln with the exception of those students who are applying to enter the program with a four year degree from an accredited architecture program. No professional transfer credit will be accepted from a non-accredited architecture program.

College Evaluation of Transfer Credit

First time students transferring to the College of Architecture from a similar accredited professional degree program will be evaluated on the basis of the current undergraduate bulletin in effect at the time the student enrolls in the College of Architecture.

Process

The program director will select and identify those courses that are applicable to the Professional Program in Architecture, Interior Design, and Landscape Architecture Programs. The College of Architecture will not accept courses for transfer which are below a 2.0 on a 4-point scale.

Evaluation of Technical and Nonaccredited Transfer Credits

Students who desire to transfer credits from technical or nonaccredited colleges must have architecture credits evaluated by the director and/or appropriate program representatives. Non-architecture credits will be evaluated by the appropriate university department.

Evaluation of Graphics, Design, and Production Drawing Credit

Transfer credit for graphics, basic and architectural and/or interior design work and production drawings will not be granted until the student’s work has been reviewed by the Architecture or Interior Design Program Director. Allowable transfer credit in the design, production drawings, and graphics areas, whether the grades presented are C, B, or A, will be determined from this review and the student placed accordingly.

Confirmation procedure:

1. It is the student’s responsibility to initiate this task,

2. The student procedure is to obtain the confirmation form from the Program Office and to seek review of appropriate materials, and

3. A “portfolio review” will determine confirmation of credit. This review will be done by the appropriate faculty member or committee.

Evaluation of General Education Credits

Transfer students who have formally applied for admission will have their academic credits evaluated by the University Office of Registration and Records and the College of Architecture. The College will evaluate all hours submitted on an admission application but reserves the right to reject any of these credits.

Clarification and Appeal

The student who has questions about or wishes to appeal the initial College evaluation of his or her transfer credit should contact the Program Office. If the evaluation is not satisfactorily resolved, the student has the right to register an appeal with the Student Affairs Committee of the Architecture or Interior Design Programs.

Independent Study

Credit hours earned through independent study (ARCH 398, 498, 598 and 898; LARC 398, 498, 598; and IDES 398, 498, 898) need to be formally arranged with the faculty member supervising the work prior to registration for those credit hours. This is accomplished through completion of the Independent Study Contract available in the Program Office. It must have the signature of the faculty sponsor and be filed with the Program Office in order to be valid.

Students are limited to a total of 9 credit hours of independent study over the course of their academic career in the professional program.

Other College Degree Requirements

Off-Campus Programs

The College of Architecture recognizes the need for some students to pursue their pre-architecture, pre-landscape architecture, and pre-interior design studies at other institutions. Up to two semesters (30 semester credit hours) of off-campus study should cause minimal delay in students’ educational timetables if courses can be selected from the following list and are approved by the College of Architecture. Students are encouraged to coordinate their off-campus Pre-Architecture, Pre-Landscape Architecture and Pre-Interior Design Programs with the College of Architecture.

Recommended Courses

Art Studio elective (10 hrs)

Calculus (5 hrs) for pre-architecture/landscape architecture or Statistics (3 hrs) for pre-interior design/landscape architecture

English Composition electives (6 hrs)

Humanities and Social Sciences electives (9 hrs) See UNL ACE requirements.

Physics (4 hrs) for pre-architecture or Natural Science (4 hrs) for pre-interior design

Speech (3 hrs)

DEGREES & MAJORS

Organization and Degrees

The College of Architecture consists of four academic programs: architecture, interior design, landscape architecture, and community and regional planning. Architecture, interior design, and landscape architecture all have a two year pre-professional program followed by professional degree programs. In architecture, it is a four year program in which students get a bachelor of science in design (BSD) degree and the professional master of architecture (MArch) degree. The landscape architecture program is three years in which students receive a BSD followed by the professional bachelor of landscape architecture (BLA) degree. The interior design program is two years and culminates in the professional BSD degree. The Community and Regional Planning Program is exclusively a graduate degree program.

Both architecture and interior design have post professional MS research degrees and architecture has a PhD degree program with the College of Education and Human Sciences.

Community and Regional Planning

The Community and Regional Planning Program offers the two-year professional master of community and regional planning degree which is fully accredited by the Planning Accreditation Board (PAB).

GRADUATE STUDENT INFORMATION

Graduate and Professional Teaching and Research Assistantships

The College of Architecture has several teaching and research assistantships available each year. Students accepted into the master of architecture program, MS, and PhD/EdD programs or those who are in the process of making application for admission to the master of architecture program are encouraged to apply for these assistantships. A brief letter of interest and qualifications plus completed graduate assistantship recommendation forms (which are available in the Architecture Program Office) should be sent to the Architecture Program before March 1 of each year for consideration for the fall semester and November 1 for the spring semester.

Course Hold for Professional Credit

Seniors who have obtained in advance the approval of the Architecture Program director may receive up to 12 hours credit towards their MArch degree prior to the completion of their BSD degree provided the following conditions are met:

they are above the courses required for their BSD degree;
are taken under the 500 number; and
are taken in the calendar year prior to the receipt of the BSD.

MINORS & AREAS OF SPECIALIZATIONS OFFERED

Landscape Architecture

The Landscape Architecture minor is administered through the College of Architecture’s Landscape Architecture program.

Students can earn a minor in landscape architecture by completion of the following course work:

Hours

Core Requirements 10

ARCH 240 History of Architecture 3

HORT 200 Landscape & Environmental Appreciation 3

HORT 498 Topics in Landscape Architecture 1

ARCH 360 Site Context Issues 3

Elective Requirements 6-8

Select one from: 3-4

HORT 130 Intro to Horticulture Science (4 cr)

HORT 212 Landscape Plants I (3 cr)

HORT 214 Perennials (3 cr)

HORT 266 Intro to Landscape Design (4 cr)

Select one from: 3-4

HORT 339/ARCH 467 Planting Design (4 cr)

HORT 341/ARCH 468 Landscape Construction (3 cr)

HORT 469/ARCH 469 Senior Design (4 cr)

Students can earn a minor for any course of study defined by the faculty offering the courses related to the minor. This generally requires additional work on top of that defined in the professional curriculum.

OTHER

Ownership of Class Work

Significant student work will be retained on file by the program each semester as a necessary record for accrediting purposes and periodic display. Other student work must be retrieved by the student no later than seven working days past the end of the semester.

The College of Architecture is not responsible for storing or returning student work. In addition, all padlocks left on lockers will be cut, and the materials in the lockers confiscated after completion of spring semester.

Nonprofessional Master of Science Degree and PhD/EdD Degrees

The scholarly-nonprofessional master of science degree is a scholarly, research-based curriculum. For more information, please see the University of Nebraska–Lincoln Graduate Bulletin.

Community and Regional Planning Program

Chair: Kim Wilson, 302 Architecture Hall

Professors: Scholz, Wilson

Associate Professor: Cantarero

Assistant Professors: Nam, Tang

Professors Emeritus: Fischer, Hulvershorn

The Community and Regional Planning Program offers the master of community and regional planning (MCRP) degree; however, several courses in the Department are also offered at the advanced undergraduate level and are available to undergraduate students in all majors.

The master of community and regional planning degree program provides preparation for professional planning practice in the public, private, and nonprofit sectors.

Planning is an interdisciplinary problem-solving profession that influences a broad range of future-oriented decision making. Planners work with individuals, groups, and organizations to formulate plans, policies, and strategies through which desired change can be achieved. Planners utilize a wide variety of methods and techniques to identify problems and needs and to formulate plans of action that effectively address those needs. Planners often need to accommodate differing viewpoints in the process of formulating desirable and compatible plan and policy recommendations.

The MCRP degree program emphasizes the understanding of the importance of and interrelationships among human resources, natural resources, socio-cultural characteristics, economic activity, political and institutional roles, and characteristics of the natural and built environment. The program provides students with a sound foundation in planning theory, methods, process, and application–a background which enables graduates to formulate, initiate, and coordinate a broad range of planning and development actions.

Master of Community and Regional Planning Curriculum

The MCRP degree program requires completion of 48 graduate credit hours, 24 of which are in a required core curriculum.

Required Core Courses

CRPL 400/800 Intro to Planning 3

CRPL 802 Planning Theory 3

CRPL 804 Legal Aspects of Planning 3

CRPL 810 Qualitative Techniques for Planners 3

CRPL 830 Intro to Computers in Planning 3

CRPL 840 Planning Methods & Analysis 3

CRPL 900 Professional Planning Practice 3

CRPL 990 Planning Studio 3

Total Required Core Course Credit Hours 24

Elective Courses

In addition to the required core courses in the MCRP program, students must complete at least 9 graduate credit hours in an area of concentration and 15 graduate credit hours in one of the following three tracks: 1) 9 credit hours of approved electives, a 6-credit-hour masters thesis, and an oral examination; 2) 9 credit hours of approved electives, a 6-credit-hour professional project, and an oral examination; or 3) 15 credit hours of approved electives and a comprehensive written examination.

The written comprehensive examination for track 3 is scheduled and administered by the Department typically no more than once each semester. The examination must be taken on one of the examination dates established by the Department. The examination covers the student’s program of studies for the MCRP degree, as approved by the Department and the Office of Graduate Studies.

Five areas of concentration are offered by the Department: 1) physical planning, 2) social planning, 3) environmental planning, 4) economic development planning, and 5) transportation planning. Courses in these concentrations are offered inside and outside the Department. Other individualized areas of concentration may be proposed and pursued by students, subject to approval by the Department graduate committee.

Dual Degree Programs

The MCRP degree may be pursued within either of three dual degree programs at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.

One program is the MCRP/JD dual degree program, offered in collaboration with the College of Law. This program enables completion of both the MCRP degree and the juris doctor degree in a four-year period.

The second program is the MCRP/MArch dual degree program, offered in collaboration with the Architecture Program. This program enables completion of both the MCRP degree and the master of architecture degree in a three-year period. This program is intended for persons who hold the bachelor of science in design (BSD) or equivalent undergraduate degree.

The third program is the MCRP/MS-CE (transportation specialization) in collaboration with the Civil Engineering Department. Persons interested in the dual degree programs should inquire with the chairperson of the Community and Regional Planning Program.

Interdepartmental Programs

The Community and Regional Planning Program cooperates with other disciplines in offering courses for three designated interdepartmental areas: 1) Water Resources Planning and Management, 2) Public Policy Analysis and Program Evaluation, and 3) Environmental Studies. Persons interested in these areas in conjunction with the MCRP degree should consult with the Chair of the Community and Regional Planning Program.

Admission to the Master of Community and Regional Planning Program

Students with diverse undergraduate, graduate, and professional backgrounds are encouraged to enter the MCRP degree program. No prior course work in planning is required. However, applicants are expected to have completed at least one course each in statistics, economics, and the social sciences, with a grade of C or better. The Department graduate committee may specify how the applicant is to make up deficiencies in any of these areas.

Applications for admission to the MCRP degree program must be submitted by March 15 for fall semester admission and by November 1 for spring semester admission. Applications must include the following:

1. Application for Admission to the Graduate College form, submitted to:

Office of Graduate Studies

University of Nebraska–Lincoln

1100 Seaton Hall

Lincoln, NE 68588-0619

2. Two official copies of all college transcripts, submitted to the Office of Graduate Studies;

3. Official score report for the Graduate Record Exam General Test, submitted to the Office of Graduate Studies;

4. Three letters of recommendation on standard Graduate Studies forms, submitted to:

Community and Regional Planning Program

University of Nebraska–Lincoln

302 Architecture Hall

PO Box 880105

Lincoln, NE 68588-0105

5. An essay responding to program application form questions, submitted to the Program office.

College of Arts & Sciences

DESCRIPTION

David C. Manderscheid, Ph.D., Dean and Professor of Mathematics

Amy Goodburn, Ph.D., Associate Dean for Faculty and Professor of English

Sunil Narumalani, Ph.D., Associate Dean for Academic Programs and Professor of Geography

Gregory Snow, Ph.D., Associate Dean for Research and Professor of Physics and Astronomy

Alecia Kimbrough, M.B.A, Assistant Dean for Business and Finance and Staff

William Watts, M.A., Assistant Dean for Advising Services

For additional information or questions, contact:

Bill Watts

Assistant Dean for Advising Services

107 Oldfather Hall

PO Box 880330

Lincoln, NE 68588-0330

402/472-4190

Mission

To educate undergraduate students of the College of Arts and Sciences to a high level of competence in their major fields through instruction that integrates formal course work with experience in research and creative activity.
To advance knowledge through research and creative activity that are national and international in stature.
To provide all undergraduate students with a range of knowledge and a broad intellectual experience that can form the basis for critical and imaginative thinking, thereby enabling them to become tolerant and responsible members of a global society.
To provide undergraduate and graduate students across the campus with courses in the arts, humanities, social sciences, and sciences to meet their academic needs in their major programs.
To serve the university and community-at-large and provide educational leadership for the state and region.

Careers

The possibilities are endless. Society has a growing need for graduates with the thinking and communication skills developed while obtaining a liberal arts degree, and who are broadly educated to be adaptable to the needs of a rapidly changing society.

Arts and sciences graduates have become financial planners, radiologists, teachers, doctors, airline pilots, ministers, lawyers, public relations directors, and resource managers.

Often there is no direct link between a student’s academic major and career choice. A student does not have to be a biology major to become a physician. Not all history majors become historians. The major is only one part of a student’s career preparation; it is a foundation for the entire program at the university, which may also include a minor, internships, special studies, and co-curricular activities.

The College works closely with Career Services, 230 Nebraska Union, to help students with their career planning. In addition, the Chief Advisers provide information and guidance.

ADMISSION

College Admission

The entrance requirements for the College of Arts and Sciences are the same as the UNL General Admission Requirements. Students who are admitted through the Admission by Review process with core course deficiencies will have certain conditions attached to their enrollment at UNL. These conditions are explained under “Removal of Deficiencies.”

In addition to these requirements, the College of Arts and Sciences strongly recommends a third and fourth year of languages. Four years of high school language will exempt students from the College of Arts and Sciences’ 16-hour language requirement. It will also allow students to continue language study at a more advanced level, and give more opportunity to study abroad.

Transfer Students

To be considered for admission a transfer student, Nebraska resident or nonresident, must have an accumulated average of C (2.0 on a 4.0 scale) and a minimum C average in the last semester of attendance at another college. Transfer students who graduated from high school January 1997 and after must also meet the UNL General Admissions Requirements. Those transfer students who graduated before January 1997 must have completed in high school 3 years of English, 2 years of the same foreign language, 2 years of algebra, and 1 year of geometry. Transfer students who have completed less than 12 credit hours of college study must submit either the ACT or SAT scores.

Ordinarily, hours earned at an accredited college are accepted by the University. The College, however, will evaluate all hours submitted on an application for transfer and reserves the right to accept or reject any of them. Sixty-six is the maximum number of hours the University will accept on transfer from a two-year college. Transfer credit in the major must be approved by the major adviser on a Request for Substitution Form to meet specific course requirements, group requirements, or course level requirements in the major. At least 9 hours in the major field must be completed at the University regardless of the number of hours transferred.

The College of Arts and Sciences will accept no more than 15 semester hours of C- and D grades from other schools. The C- and D grades cannot be applied toward requirements for a major or minor. This policy does not apply to the transfer of grades from UNO or UNK to UNL. All D grades may be transferred from UNO or UNK, but they are not applicable to a major or minor.

Readmitted Students

Students readmitted to the College of Arts and Sciences will follow the requirements stated in the bulletin for the academic year of readmission and reenrollment as a degree-seeking student in Arts and Sciences. In consultation with advisers, a student may choose to follow a bulletin for any academic year in which they are admitted to and enrolled as a degree-seeking student at UNL in the College of Arts and Sciences. Students must complete all degree requirements from a single bulletin year. Beginning in 1990-1991, the bulletin which a student follows for degree requirements may not be more than 10 years old at the time of graduation.

Admission Deficiencies/Removal of Deficiencies

You must remove entrance deficiencies before you can graduate from the College of Arts and Sciences. For students entering August 1997 or later and who graduated from high school January 1997 and after, courses taken to remove a high school core course deficiency may not be counted toward either the major, minor, college degree requirements, or university comprehensive education requirements. They may only be counted in the “electives” category in meeting degree requirements. The most common deficiencies are in foreign languages and mathematics.

Removing Foreign Language Deficiencies

A student who has had fewer than two years of one foreign language in high school will need 130 semester hours as a minimum for a degree from the College of Arts and Sciences. A student will also need to complete the “102” course in a language to clear the deficiency and the “202” course to complete the college graduation requirement in language.

Removing Mathematics Deficiencies

1. A deficiency of one year of geometry can be removed by taking two high school geometry courses by Independent Study or by completing a geometry course from an accredited community college or a four-year institution. Neither of these options count for college credit.

2. A deficiency of the first year of algebra can be removed by taking two high school Algebra I courses through Extended Education (not for college credit).

3. A deficiency of the second year of algebra can be removed by taking MATH 95C (not for college credit) or MATH 100A (may be taken for college credit but does not apply toward graduation).

4. A student whose deficiency is the additional (fourth) year of mathematics that builds on algebra must successfully complete MATH 101, 102, or 103, or an equivalent course at another institution.

Removing Other Deficiencies

Contact the Arts and Sciences Advising Center for specific courses to remove other entrance deficiencies.

ADVISING

Academic Advising

All students in the College of Arts and Sciences are assigned to an academic adviser to help them plan their academic careers and select appropriate courses. Incoming freshmen are counseled during New Student Enrollment by specially trained advisers from the Arts and Sciences Advising Center.

Students who have not decided on a major field of study will be assigned an adviser in the College Advising Center. Students “declaring” a major, changing majors (or colleges), or needing help with problems should also visit the Advising Center.

Students who have decided on (declared) a major, a pre-health area or pre-law will be assigned to an adviser by the appropriate chief adviser. The chief advisers and the Advising Center also are available to answer questions about majors, minors, and pre-health areas and pre-law a student is considering.

For complete and current information on chief advisers for majors, minors, and pre-health areas and pre-law, contact the Arts and Sciences Advising Center, 107 Oldfather Hall, 472-4190.

ACADEMIC PROGRAMS & POLICIES

Course Exclusions & Restrictions

Course Exclusions

No credit for graduation is allowed for non-college level courses or for courses that deal primarily with the development of skills including the following:

Driver training education
Industrial arts (including courses concerned primarily with manual skills, tools, machines, or industrial processes and design) For example at UNL: TEAC 101, 102, 103, 104, 109, 201, 203, 204, 205, 206, 229, 242, 243, 300, 301, 340, 346.
Agricultural education (credit is allowed for ALEC 102, 202, 337, 494, 496; or ALEC courses cross-listed with departments from which Arts and Sciences applies credit for graduation)
Any introduction computer course training in DOS, word processing, spread-sheets, data base management, or other business software packages (CSCE 137 or BSAD 150 or AGRI 271)
MATH 100A

Course Restrictions

Students majoring in the College of Arts and Sciences my use courses in the following areas toward their degree within the following limits:

Maximum 12 hours religion courses that advocate the doctrine or belief of a particular faith. This 12 hour limit does not apply to religious studies courses whose method and approach conforms to the standards of critical scholarship in the academic study of the humanities and social sciences.
Maximum 15 hours of C- and D grades are transferable from colleges outside UNL. The C- and D grades cannot apply to majors or minors. All C- and D grades from UNO or UNK may be transferred but they are not applicable to a major or minor.
Maximum 66 hours accepted from a community college.
Maximum 30 hours of clinical courses.
Maximum 16 hours of applied music lessons and/or music ensemble.
Maximum 4 hours Activity PE, Athletic Practice, or Basic Military Science with a maximum of 1 credit hour per semester.
Maximum 12 hours total from any combination of the following areas:

First Aid (NUTR 170 at UNL)

Orientation and Study Skills. For example at UNL: ALEC 397E and 397K (neither course is applicable to the courses numbered above 299 requirement); ASCI 107; BIOC 101; BIOS 150, 160; EDPS 150, 209; FDST 107; HRFS 183; NRES 101; NUTR 150; PSYC 100, 150; TEAC 210; VBMS 101

Military Science, Naval Science, or Aerospace Studies. (This restriction does not apply to cross-listed courses between military science, naval science, or aerospace studies and departments of the College of Arts and Sciences.)

Maximum 15 hours athletic coaching
Any restrictions noted specifically by departments. Credit towards the degree may be earned in only one course, including honors sections, from each group of courses listed below:

BIOS 312 or AGRO 360

BIOS 313 or 314

CHEM 105, 109, 111, 113,195

CHEM 116 or 221

CHEM 251 and more than 1 cr of CHEM 263

CHEM 471 or 481

CSCE 252D or CSCE 150E

CSCE 252D or ENGM 112

CSCE 252D or ELEC 121

CSCE 340 or 480

ECON 210 or 211 and 212

ECON 215, CRIM 300, EDPS 459 or STAT 218 (was STAT 180)

FREN 201 and 202, or FREN 210

GEOG 150 and/or 152 or 155

GEOL 100 or 101 or 101H

GEOL 103 or 105

GERM 201 and 202, or GERM 210

GREK 102 or 151

LATN 102 or 201

MATH 101 and/or 102 or 103

MATH 104 or 106

MATH 200 or 300

MATH 201 or 301

MATH 340 or ENGM 480

PHYS 141 or 151

PHYS 151 or MSYM 109

SOCI 205 or CRIM 251

SOCI 209 or CRIM 355

SOCI 311 or CRIM 337

SOCI 474 or CRIM 413

SPAN 201 and 202, or SPAN 210

For transfer students, course exclusions and restrictions will be determined on the Evaluation of Transfer credits.

Credit by Examination

Through study or experience that parallels a University of Nebraska–Lincoln course, a regularly enrolled University student may feel prepared to pass an examination on the course content of a specific course for credit in that course. To apply for credit, a student should:

1. Consult with the department chair.

2. Obtain a Credit by Examination Form at the Records Office, 107 Canfield Administration Building, 472-3649. Current enrollment in the University must also be verified.

3. Secure the approval signature from the department chair, instructor, and the dean of the student’s college. The Dean’s signature can be obtained in the Arts and Sciences Advising Center, 107 Oldfather.

4. Secure the bursar’s receipt for payment of the appropriate fee per course for credit by examination. Currently, the fee is one-half the resident tuition rate.

5. Present the completed form to the instructor designated by the department chair. The instructor will give the examination and report the results on the Credit by Examination Form to the Admissions Office, Alexander Building, 472-0130.

Examination for credit through UNL departments may be taken only by currently enrolled students. A student is not permitted to receive credit by examination in a course which is a prerequisite for a course already taken unless the course and its prerequisites cover essentially different subject matter.

The College of Arts and Sciences also gives credit for the subject and general examinations of the College Level Examination Program (CLEP) and the Advanced Placement (AP) Program administered by the College Entrance Examination Board. See the Arts and Sciences Advising Center, 107 Oldfather Hall, for current policy regarding CLEP and AP examinations.

Dual Degrees

Two Degrees from Arts and Sciences

A graduate who holds the bachelor of arts degree may earn the bachelor of science degree by completing an additional year of work in residence taking at least 30 more semester hours of course work for a minimum of 155 hours. The student must complete all degree requirements for the second degree, including the scientific base. A graduate who holds the bachelor of science degree may earn the bachelor of arts degree by completing another year of work in residence taking at least 30 semester hours of additional course work for a minimum of 155 hours. The student must complete all degree requirements for the second degree.

Two Degrees from UNL

A graduate who holds a bachelors degree from another college at UNL may earn the bachelor of science or bachelor of arts degree from the College of Arts and Sciences by completing an additional year of work in residence taking at least 30 more semester hours of course work beyond the first degree. The student must complete all degree requirements for the arts and sciences degree.

Intercollege Studies

With College of Fine and Performing Arts: A student in the College of Arts and Sciences pursuing a bachelor of arts degree with a major in arts and sciences may also complete a bachelor of arts major in the College of Fine and Performing Arts. In addition, a student in the College of Fine and Performing Arts pursuing a bachelor of arts degree with a major in fine and performing arts may also complete a bachelor of arts major in the College of Arts and Sciences. The student must complete all degree requirements and a major in the home college and a second bachelor of arts major in the visiting college.

With College of Journalism and Mass Communications: A student in the College of Journalism and Mass Communications pursuing a bachelor of journalism degree may also complete a second major in the College of Arts and Sciences. In addition to ACE and College of Journalism and Mass Communications requirements, students will be expected to meet all College of Arts and Sciences distribution requirements and major requirements. Because students choosing this option will not be earning a degree from arts and sciences, they will not be eligible for arts and sciences-based scholarships and aid, but they will be eligible for consideration for Phi Beta Kappa.

Transfer Students with a Non-UNL Degree

A transfer student who has received a bachelors degree from another institution must complete at least 30 hours of credit in residence at UNL in addition to transfer credit. Students must complete at least half of their major course work including 6 hours above 299 in their major, and 15 of the 30 hours required above 299 in residence. The student must complete all degree requirements for the arts and sciences degree.

Honors Program

The College of Arts and Sciences encourages qualified students to participate in the University Honors Program. In addition, several departments of the College of Arts and Sciences offer special honors sections of regular freshman courses to meet the needs of students with superior preparation in those subjects. In some departments such students may then progress more rapidly into advanced courses.

Student Recognition

Dean’s List

The College recognizes students for academic achievement during the fall and spring semesters by placement on the College Dean’s List. To qualify for the Dean’s List in the College of Arts and Sciences, students must complete 12 credit hours of course work (courses must be started and completed in one semester) by the census date of the grade reports and attain a minimum semester grade point average of 3.7. The following do not qualify as part of the 12 credit hours: Pass/No Pass credit, transfer hours, removals of incompletes, and grade changes submitted after the census grade reports.

Degrees with Distinction

In recognition of outstanding academic excellence, the College recommends the bachelors degree With Distinction, With High Distinction, and With Highest Distinction. The recommendations are made by the Committee on Academic Distinction and Awards for Students. To be recommended for distinction, candidates must fulfill the specific criteria for Highest Distinction, High Distinction, or Distinction, as described below in addition to all of the general criteria and procedures applicable to all distinction classifications.

Highest Distinction. Candidates for the bachelors degree may be recommended for “Highest Distinction” on the basis of the following criteria: outstanding scholastic standing (cum GPA of 3.92 or above) and the highest recommendation based upon a thesis or comparable creative effort and a comprehensive examination.

High Distinction. Candidates for the bachelors degree may be recommended for “High Distinction” by fulfilling one of two sets of criteria: 1) by achieving outstanding scholastic standing (cum GPA of 3.92 or above), or 2) by achieving excellent scholastic standing (cum GPA between 3.85 and 3.92) and by receiving a high recommendation based on a thesis or comparable creative effort and a comprehensive examination.

Distinction. Candidates for the bachelors degree may be recommended for degrees for “Distinction” by achieving one of two sets of criteria: 1) by excellent scholastic standing (cum GPA between 3.85 and 3.92), or 2) by achieving high scholastic standing of at least a cumulative grade point average of 3.5 and by receiving a recommendation for distinction based on a thesis or comparable creative effort and a comprehensive examination. No student will be considered for distinction with a cum GPA below 3.5.

The following criteria apply to all categories: The Committee may consider especially the work of the last two years, and ordinarily only students who have taken their last 48 hours of graded course work while registered in the College of Arts and Sciences are considered. The Committee reviews both grades and the program of courses.

Students who choose one of the thesis options described above should make arrangements with their academic adviser and major department. They should register for the independent study course in their major area of study (usually 399H), typically, starting with the semester prior to the semester in which they plan to graduate. A thesis prospectus form is to be filed by each student in the semester prior to graduation. This thesis prospectus form must be approved by two faculty co-advisers who have agreed to guide the student’s work. The student will submit the completed thesis to the same faculty co-advisers for final evaluation.

The deadline for the designated departmental distinction group to submit a student’s materials to the Dean’s office for consideration for distinction is six weeks prior to the Monday following commencement, except for the August commencement in which case the deadline is four weeks prior to the Friday before commencement. These materials must include a copy of the student’s thesis, the student’s thesis prospectus form, and the thesis evaluation form in support of a degree with distinction. The forms are available in 107 and 1223 Oldfather Hall and can also be found on the college Web site at http://ascweb.unl.edu/students/distinction.html. Students are urged to contact the department in which they are writing a thesis for department deadlines.

A degree with Distinction is an award which is recommended by the Committee on Academic Distinction and Awards for Students after it carefully weighs and considers all aspects of a student’s record: the GPA, the number of courses taken Pass/No Pass, number of courses at the 300/400 level, the strength of the program, and (when submitted) the quality of the thesis as defined by evaluations provided by the co-advisers and the major department.

College Scholarships

The Dean’s Office of the College of Arts and Sciences, in conjunction with the College Committee on Student Academic Distinction Awards and Appeals, chooses recipients for College scholarships and also recommends students for certain scholarships awarded by the Office of Scholarships and Financial Aid and by external agencies. For a complete list of the scholarships awarded by the College, see http://ascweb.unl.edu/students/scholarships.html.

Many of the College scholarships require demonstrated need. If you wish to be considered for any of these scholarships, it is necessary that you also complete the following on-line applications:

A. Free Application for Federal Student Aid (FAFSA) by going to www.fafsa.ed.gov

B. The Upper Class Scholarship Application with the Office of Scholarships and Financial Aid.

Departmental Scholarships

There are numerous awards and scholarships earmarked for specific majors, all of which are administered individually by the departments in the College of Arts and Sciences. To find out which scholarships you might be eligible for and the procedures for applying, please contact the appropriate Department for information.

University Scholarships

The Office of Scholarships and Financial Aid administer numerous funds. Consideration for these scholarships is based on submission of the Upper Class Scholarship Application. This is an on-line application that can be found at www.unl.edu/scholfa/.

Other Scholarships

Edythe Wiebers International Studies Program Scholarship. Special application forms can be obtained from college offices across campus and from the International Affairs Office.
Barry M. Goldwater Scholarship. Contact Dr. Patrice Berger in the University Honors Program for more information and application materials.

Fulbright-Hays Fellowships

These fellowships are awarded annually and selections are made by various national committees from the applications submitted. Graduating seniors interested in applying should contact:

Institute for International Studies

University of Nebraska

1237 R Street

PO Box 880221

Lincoln, NE 68508-0221

Campus deadline for submitting applications is October 1.

NOTE: Students who wish to pursue graduate work should inquire in the Office of Graduate Studies, 301 Canfield Administration Building, concerning scholarships, fellowships, and assistantships open to graduating seniors.

International Study/Study Abroad

International Opportunities

The College supports the following international interdisciplinary programs offering a major or a minor: African American and African Studies, Asian Studies, European Studies, International Studies, and Latino and Latin American Studies. Departments and faculty in the College of Arts and Sciences are also actively involved as sponsors, teachers and leaders in many of the numerous Study Abroad programs administered by the Office of International Affairs.

The College encourages students to study overseas as part of their University experience. The University participates in exchange and several formal study abroad programs world-wide and Nebraska Semester Abroad. International Affairs can arrange for individuals to earn University credit for study at foreign universities. The International Affairs Office has study abroad, overseas opportunities, and flights and study tours programs that assist students wishing to participate in overseas studies.

Senior Check/Degree Audit

In the term after which a student has completed 85 hours, Graduation Services in Registration and Records, 109 Canfield Administration Building, will perform a “senior check.” Students will be provided with a copy of the senior check. This check will inform students about the requirements that still need to be fulfilled in their chosen degree program. Questions about remaining requirements should be directed to the chief adviser for the major or the Arts and Sciences Advising Center, 107 Oldfather Hall.

Each student who expects to receive a diploma must file an application of candidacy for the diploma in the Office of Registration and Records, 107 Canfield Administration Building. Announcements about deadline dates are posted on bulletin boards and the online University calendar, and are printed in the Daily Nebraskan.

Students are responsible for informing the Office of Registration and Records of their graduation plans, including their addresses; the manner in which they are completing their requirements such as by correspondence, by clearance of incompletes, by enrollment at another institution, by taking special examinations, etc.; and of any later revision of such plans. Failure to follow this procedure may cause postponement of graduation until a later semester.

Classification of Students

Freshman Program

The first-year program is designed to give students a broad basis for future study. It includes English composition, a foreign language, and courses in science, the humanities, social sciences or mathematics for a total of about 12-15 hours per semester. During this year, the student will progress toward meeting University ACE requirements and will have an opportunity to explore various areas of study while starting or deciding upon a major. With the help of New Student Enrollment and their academic advisers, students choose specific courses according to their needs and interests.

Class Standing

Sophomore Standing. For admission to sophomore standing a student must have completed all of the College entrance requirements, earned a minimum of 27 semester hours of credit, and attained a total grade point average of at least C.

Junior Standing. A student has junior standing after meeting the requirements for sophomore standing and completing 53 semester hours of credit.

Senior Standing. A student has senior standing after meeting the requirements for junior standing and completing 89 semester hours of credit.

Substitutions and Waivers

Special requests concerning degree programs, including inquiries about exceptions to degree requirements, waivers, and substitutions should be made to the Arts and Sciences Advising Center, 107 Oldfather Hall.

ACHIEVEMENT-CENTERED EDUCATION (ACE) REQUIREMENTS

Consistent with the mission and values of the University, ACE is based on a shared set of four institutional objectives and 10 student learning outcomes. The ACE program was approved by faculty in all eight undergraduate colleges and endorsed by the Faculty Senate, the student government, and the Academic Planning Committee in January 2008 for implementation in the fall 2009. ACE aligns with current national initiatives in general education.

Key characteristics of ACE demonstrate the benefits of the program to students:

Students receive a broad education with exposure to multiple disciplines, critical life skills and important reasoning, inquiry, and civic capacities.
ACE is simple and transparent for students, faculty and advisers. Students complete the equivalent of 3 credit hours for each of the ten student learning outcomes.
Students connect and integrate their ACE experiences with their selected major.
Students can transfer all ACE certified courses across colleges within the institution to meet the ACE requirement and any course from outside the institution that is directly equivalent to a UNL ACE-certified course. Courses from outside institutions without direct equivalents may be considered with appropriate documentation for ACE credit (see academic adviser).

ACE allows faculty to assess and improve their effectiveness and facilitate students’ learning.

ACE Institutional Objectives and Student Learning Outcomes

To meet the ACE Program requirement, a student will complete the equivalent of 3 credit hours for each of the ten ACE Student Learning Outcomes (a total of 30 ACE credit hours). See the ACE Web site at: http://ace. unl.edu for the most current information and the most recently certified courses.

COLLEGE DEGREE REQUIREMENTS

College General Education Requirements

The College of Arts and Sciences distribution requirements are designed to further the purposes of liberal education by encouraging study in several different areas. Courses satisfying these requirements may impart specialized knowledge or broadly connect the subject matter to other areas of knowledge.

All requirements are in addition to University ACE requirements. A student may not use a single course to satisfy more than one of the following five distribution requirements. A student cannot use a single course to satisfy both an ACE outcome and a College distribution requirement. Independent study or reading courses and internships cannot be used to satisfy distribution requirements. To see a complete list of excluded courses, run a degree audit through WAM.

Courses from interdisciplinary programs will count in the same area as courses from the home/cross-listed department(s). See http://ascweb.unl.edu/academics/depts.html for a complete list.

Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science (19 credits + Language)

A. Written Communication: 3 hours

To be selected from courses approved for ACE outcome 1.

B. Natural, Physical and Mathematical Sciences: 7 hours

From two different departments, including at least one lab science course from the natural or physical sciences. Lab courses may be selected from biochemistry, biological sciences, chemistry, geology, meteorology, physics and astronomy, geography, and anthropology*. All other courses select from: biochemistry, biological sciences, chemistry, computer science and engineering, geology, meteorology, mathematics, physics and astronomy, and statistics.

* See degree audit or College of Arts and Sciences adviser for approved geography and anthropology lab courses, approved non-lab psychology courses, or courses cross-listed with an Arts and Sciences department.

C. Humanities: 6 hours

From two different departments, select from classics*, English, history, modern languages and literatures*, philosophy, and religious studies*.

*Language courses numbered 210 or below apply only for the foreign language requirement.

D. Social Sciences: 3 hours

Select from anthropology, communication studies, geography, political science, psychology, or sociology

E. Languages Classical and Modern: 0-6 hours

Fulfilled by the completion of the 6-credit-hour second-year sequence in a single foreign language in one of the following departments: Classics and religious studies, modern languages and literatures, or anthropology. Instruction is currently available in Biblical Hebrew, Chinese, Czech, French, German, Greek, Japanese, Latin, Omaha, Russian, and Spanish. A student who has completed the fourth-year level of one foreign language in high school is exempt from the languages requirement.

Scientific Base

In addition to University ACE requirements and the College distribution requirements, the bachelor of science degree requires students to complete 60 semester hours in mathematics and natural sciences, including:

1. At least one of the following quantitative courses: CSCE 235, MATH 104, PHIL 211, or any mathematics or statistics course numbered 106 or above, except MATH 200 and MATH 201.

2. At least one natural or physical science course and at least 1 credit of laboratory work, taken as part of a course or separately, from the following departments: biochemistry, biological sciences, chemistry, geosciences, or physics and astronomy, ANTH 242/242L, GEOG 155, and the following geography techniques courses also apply: GEOG 317, 412, 414, 415, 417, 418, 419, 420, 422, and 425. Other courses that may be applied toward the 60 hour total include courses in actuarial science for which calculus or above is a prerequisite and up to 12 hours of scientific and technical courses offered by other colleges with approval of the academic adviser.

Foreign Languages/Language Requirement

Languages Exemption Policy

UNL and Arts and Sciences will exempt or waive students from the UNL entrance requirement of two years of the same foreign language or from the College’s language distribution requirement based on documentation only. The following are the options and procedures for documentation:

High School Transcripts

1. For the University entrance requirements, students must show an official high school transcript with two or more years of the same foreign language in high school.

2. For the College of Arts and Sciences College Distribution Requirements Area 5 languages requirement, students must show an official high school transcript with four or more years of the same foreign language in high school, or show evidence of graduation from a non-English-speaking foreign high school.

3. For the College of Arts and Sciences College Distribution Requirements Area 5 languages requirement, students whose native language is not English must show English as a Second Language study on an official high school transcript. Four years of ESL at the high school level (9th, 10th, 11th and 12th grades) will be the basis for a waiver of the Area I Language requirement.

Proficiency Examination at UNL

1. For the University entrance requirement, students who do not have transcript documentation can request to take a proficiency exam in the language. (This is not the same test as the Modern Languages Placement Exam.) However, UNL will provide testing only in the languages it teaches. Currently, these languages are:

French

German

Spanish

Russian

Czech

Japanese

Chinese

The Department of Modern Languages will oversee the test and provide written documentation to the Admissions Office that the student has passed the proficiency test at the 102 level.

2. For the College of Arts and Sciences College Distribution Requirements Area 5 requirement, the Department of Modern Languages will oversee the test at the 202 level. If the student passes the test, the department will sign the College Request for Waiver form and indicate the level of proficiency. The form is then forwarded to the Arts and Sciences Advising Center for approval.

Distance Education

1. For the University entrance requirement, students without transcript documentation who claim proficiency in a language not taught at UNL, have the option of seeking out a distance education program in languages. If the student completes the equivalent of 102 from an approved distance education program, the student will meet the UNL entrance requirement. The student must have the course work approved before he/she takes/completes the course as equivalent to 102 by the modern languages department. The student then completes the course and has the distance education program send the transcript to the Admissions Office.

2. For the College of Arts and Sciences College Distribution Requirements Area 5 languages, the student can seek out a distance education program and complete the equivalent of the 202-level course. The student must submit the request on the College Request for Substitution form and have the course work approved by the Department of Modern Languages and the assistant dean for Advising Services. The student then completes the course and has the distance education program send the transcript to the Admissions Office.

Third Language Option

If a student demonstrates knowledge of two foreign languages at the 102 level, the College of Arts and Sciences may consider waiving two semesters of the four semester College Distribution Requirements Area 5 languages requirement. If this waiver were granted, the student would then be required to complete 101 and 102 in another (3rd language) at UNL.

Minimum Hours Required for Graduation

A minimum of 125 semester hours of credit is required for graduation from the College of Arts and Sciences. Students who enter the College with fewer than two units of one foreign language from high school are required to take 130 semester hours as a minimum for the bachelor of arts or bachelor of science degree. A total grade point average of at least 2.0 is required.

Grade Rules

Restrictions on C- and D Grades

The College will accept no more than 15 semester hours of C- and D grades from other schools except for UNO and UNK. No transfer C- and D grades can be applied toward requirements in a major or a minor. No UNL C- and D grades can be applied toward requirements in a major or a minor.

Pass/No Pass Privilege

University regulations for the Pass/No Pass (P/N) privilege state:

The Pass/No Pass option is designed for your use by seeking to expand your intellectual horizons by taking courses in areas where you may have had minimal preparation.
For students in Arts and Sciences, the University regulations for Pass/No Pass apply as follows:

1. Neither the P nor the N grade contribute to your GPA.

2. P is interpreted to mean C or above.

3. A change to or from a Pass/No Pass may be made until mid-term (1/2 of the course).

4. The Pass/No Pass or grade registration cannot conflict with the policy of the professor, department, college, or University governing the grading option.

5. Changing to or from Pass/No Pass requires using the eNRoll system to change the grading option or filing a Drop/Add form with the Registration and Records, 107 Canfield Administration Building. After mid-term of the course, a student registered for Pass/No Pass cannot change to a grade registration unless the Pass/No Pass registration is in conflict with the policy of the professor, department, college, or University governing Pass/No Pass. The Pass/No Pass grading option is not available to students on academic probation unless the course is offered only on a Pass/No Pass basis.

6. The Pass/No Pass grading option cannot be used for the removal of C- or D or F grades.

Pass/No Pass privileges in the College of Arts and Sciences are extended to students according to the following additional regulations:

1. Pass/No Pass hours can count toward fulfillment of University ACE requirements and college distribution requirements up to the 24-hour maximum.

2. Many Arts and Sciences departments and programs do not allow courses in the major or minor to be taken Pass/No Pass; students should refer to the department’s or program’s section of the bulletin for clarification. By college rule, departments can allow up to 6 hours of Pass/No Pass in the major or minor.

3. Freshmen and sophomores may enroll for no more than 6 hours of P/N work per semester.

4. Departments may specify that certain courses of theirs can be taken only on a P/N basis.

5. The college will permit no more than a total of 24 semester hours of P/N grades to be applied toward degree requirements. This total includes all Pass grades earned at UNL and other U.S. schools. NOTE: This 24-hour limit is more restrictive than the University regulation.

Students who wish to apply P/N hours to their major and minor(s) must obtain approval on a form that is available in the Arts and Sciences Advising Center, 107 Oldfather Hall.

Grading Appeals

A student who feels that he/she has been unfairly graded must ordinarily take the following sequential steps in a timely manner, usually by initiating the appeal in the semester following the awarding of the grade:

1. Talk with the instructor concerned. Most problems are resolved at this point.

2. Talk to the instructor’s department chairperson.

3. Take the case to the Grading Appeal Committee of the department concerned. The Committee should be contacted through the department chairperson.

4. Take the case to the College Grading Appeals Committee by contacting the Dean’s Office, 1223 Oldfather Hall.

Course Level Requirements

Courses Numbered above 299

Thirty of the 125 (or 130) semester hours of credit must be in courses numbered above 299. Of the 30 hours above 299, 15 hours (1/2) must be completed in residence at UNL. NOTE: ALEC 397E and ALEC 397K do not count toward these 30 hours.

Graduate Courses

Seniors in the University who have obtained in advance the approval of the dean for Graduate Studies may receive up to 12 hours credit for graduate courses taken in addition to the courses necessary to complete their undergraduate work, provided that such credits are earned within the calendar year prior to receipt of the baccalaureate. For procedures, inquire at the Office of Graduate Studies.

Course work taken prior to receipt of the baccalaureate may not always be accepted for transfer to other institutions as graduate work.

Residency

Residency Requirement and Open Enrollment and Summer Independent Study Courses

Students must complete at least 30 of the 125 (or 130) total hours for their degree at UNL. Students must complete at least 1/2 of their major course work including 6 hours above 299 in their major, and 15 of the 30 hours required above 299 in residence. Credit earned during study abroad may be used toward the residency requirement if students register through UNL and participate in prior-approved study abroad programs. UNL open enrollment and summer independent study courses count toward residence.

Bulletin Rule

Students must fulfill the requirements stated in the bulletin for the academic year in which they are first admitted to and enrolled as a degree-seeking student at UNL. In consultation with advisers a student may choose to follow a subsequent bulletin for any academic year in which they are admitted to and enrolled as a degree-seeking student at UNL in the College of Arts and Sciences. Students must complete all degree requirements from a single bulletin year. Beginning in 1990-1991 the bulletin which a student follows for degree requirements may not be more than 10 years old at the time of graduation.

DEGREES & MAJORS

Degree Programs and Areas of Study

The College of Arts and Sciences offers curricula leading to the degrees of bachelor of arts and bachelor of science.

Cross-listed Course Policy

The College of Arts and Sciences recognizes cross-listed courses as equivalent for the purposes of degree requirements. Therefore, a course taken under one department which is cross-listed can be used in all the majors and minors affected by all the cross-listings of the course.

Requirements for the Bachelor of Arts Degree

Students who wish to graduate with a bachelor of arts degree must complete the College graduation requirements, the University ACE requirements, the College of Arts and Sciences distribution requirements, the requirements for a major, and the requirements for a minor or minors if required by the major.

Requirements for the Bachelor of Science Degree

The bachelor of science degree is characterized by a strong prescriptive major, an essential scientific base, and the inclusion of a general liberal education as an important aspect of the degree. Requirements for the BS are the same as those for the BA, with the following exceptions:

1. The major must include between 50-70 credit hours including required collateral courses in other departments. For students who wish to acquire two majors in two departments, the departments will be asked to make some accommodation for the students.

2. In addition to the College of Arts and Sciences distribution requirements, the bachelor of science degree requires students to complete 60 semester hours in the natural and mathematical sciences. (See scientific base information under College General Education Requirements.)

Areas of Study for the Major

Students are advised to choose a major before the end of the sophomore year to avoid extending the period of time necessary to complete the degree. By gaining a deeper knowledge of one field, the student will further his or her general liberal education, prepare for a career in his or her specialization, and possibly advance to graduate work or a professional program. It is sometimes possible, through careful planning, for students to complete more than one undergraduate major. Students should consult their advisers about this possibility. The student who majors in more than one field will be assigned to an adviser in each field.

If a student receives a grade lower than C in a course in his or her chosen major, it will not count toward the major.

Students must complete at least 1/2 of the course work in their chosen major field in residence including 6 hours above 299, regardless of the number of hours transferred.

Areas of Study

The College of Arts and Sciences offers study toward the major and minor in many areas.

A summary of the major areas of study for degrees offered by the College of Arts and Sciences includes:

Bachelor of Arts and Bachelor of Science

Actuarial Science

Anthropology

Biological Chemistry (BS only)

Biological Sciences

Chemistry

Classical Languages

Classics & Religious Studies

Communication Studies

Computer Science

Economics

English

Environmental Studies

Ethnic Studies

European Studies

Film Studies

French

Geography

Geology

German

Great Plains Studies

History

Individualized Program of Studies

International Studies

Latin American Studies

Mathematics

Medieval and Renaissance Studies

Meteorology-Climatology (BS only)

Philosophy

Physics

Plant Biology

Political Science

Psychology

Russian

Sociology

Spanish

Speech-Language Pathology and Audiology

University Studies

Women’s and Gender Studies

MINORS & AREAS OF SPECIALIZATIONS OFFERED

The Minor

The requirement of minors is variable within the College and depends upon the student’s major department. Some departments require either one or two minors, and other departments require none. Two minor plans are available.

Plan A. Students must complete at least 6 hours of course work in a Plan A minor in residence regardless of the number of hours transferred.

Plan B. Plan B minors consist of either two minors which are completed with fewer hours in each subject than required for a single Plan A minor or two majors and one Plan B minor. Hour requirements for individual Plan B minors are stated in each department’s or program’s listings.

Minors in Other Colleges

A student with a major leading to a bachelor of science or bachelor of arts degree in the College of Arts and Sciences who wants to obtain a minor in another college should use the following procedure in making his/her request:

1. In consultation with the student’s major adviser, prepare the list of courses required for the other college’s minor as indicated in the bulletin.

2. Submit the College-Degree-Major-Adviser Change form to the College of Arts and Sciences Advising Center prior to the deadline for submitting the application for graduation.

Students who have questions related to the minor after it is declared should consult an adviser in the college through which it is offered. The minor will be recorded on the student’s transcript.

Minors Offered by Arts and Sciences

Actuarial Science

Aerospace Studies

African American Studies

African Studies

Anthropology

Archaeology Archeology

Asian Studies

Biological Chemistry

Biological Sciences

Chemistry

Chicano Studies

Classical Languages

Classics

Communication Studies

Community and Regional Planning

Computer Science

Conflict and Conflict Resolution

Czech

Economics

English

Environmental Studies

Ethnic Studies

European Studies

Film Studies

French

Geography

Geology

German

Great Plains Studies

Greek

History

Human Rights & Human Diversity

Humanities in Medicine

Individualized Program of Studies

International Studies

Japanese

Judaic Studies

Latin

Latin American Studies

Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Transgender, Queer/Sexuality Studies

Mathematics

Medieval and Renaissance Studies

Meteorology-Climatology

Native American Studies

Philosophy

Physics

Plant Biology

Political Science

Psychology

Public Policy Analysis and Evaluation (Certificate)

Religious Studies

Russian

Sociology

Spanish

Statistics

Textiles, Clothing and Design

University Studies

Women’s and Gender Studies

Pre-Health, Pre-Law, and Combined Degree Programs

Pre-Chiropractic

Pre-Clinical Laboratory Science

Pre-Clinical Perfusion Science

Pre-Cytotechnology

Pre-Dental Hygiene

Pre-Dentistry

Pre-Law

Pre-Medicine

Pre-Mortuary Science

Pre-Nursing

Pre-Occupational Therapy

Pre-Optometry

Pre-Pharmacy

Pre-Physical Therapy

Pre-Physician Assistant

Pre-Radiation Science Technology

Pre-Veterinary Science

OTHER

Affiliated Academic Centers, Facilities, Programs and Publications

For more information on the following, see http://ascweb.unl.edu/units.html.

ANDRILL Science Management Office (SMO)

Atomic, Molecular, Optical, and Plasma Physics Laboratory

Behlen Observatory

Bureau of Sociological Research

Cedar Point Biological Station

Center for Biotechnology

Center for Environmental Health and Toxicology

Center for Great Plains Studies

Center for Plant Science Innovation

Center for Science, Mathematics and Computer Education

Center on Children, Families, and the Law

Harris Center for Judaic Studies

Human Rights and Human Diversity Initiative

Institute for Ethnic Studies

Intensive English Program

International Studies

Law/Psychology

Materials Research Science and Engineering Center

Nebraska Center for Mass Spectrometry

Nebraska Center for Materials and Nanoscience

Nebraska Center for Virology

Nineteenth Century Studies Program

Prairie Schooner

Psychological Consultation Center

Raikes School of Computer Science and Management

Survey Research and Methodology

Water Center

Women’s and Gender Studies

###

College of Agricultural Sciences & Natural Resources

COLLEGE: Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources

http://casnr.unl.edu

Steven S. Waller, Ph.D., Dean and Professor of Agronomy

David K. Hardin, D.V.M., Associate Dean and Professor of Veterinary and Biomedical Sciences

Dann E. Husmann, Ph.D., Associate Dean and Professor of Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communication

John P. Markwell, Ph.D., Associate Dean and Professor of Biochemistry

Jack L. Schinstock, Ph.D., Associate Dean and Professor of Biological Systems Engineering

ADMISSION

College Admission

Requirements for admission into the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources (CASNR) are consistent with general University admission requirements (one unit equals one high school year): 4 units of English, 4 units of mathematics, 3 units of natural sciences, 3 units of social studies, and 2 units of foreign language. Students must also meet performance requirements (ACT composite of 20 or higher OR combined SAT score of 950 or higher OR rank in the top one-half of graduating class; transfer students must have a 2.0 (on a 4.0 scale) cumulative grade point average and 2.0 on most recent term of attendance.

Admission Deficiencies/Removal of Deficiencies

Students who are admitted to CASNR with core course deficiencies, must remove these deficiencies within the first 30 credit hours at UNL, or within the first calendar year at UNL, whichever takes longer, excluding foreign languages. Students have up to 60 credit hours to remove foreign language deficiencies. College-level course work taken to remove deficiencies may be used to meet degree requirements in CASNR.

Deficiencies in the required entrance subjects can be removed by completion of specified courses in the University or by correspondence.

The Office of Admissions, Alexander Building (east entrance), City Campus, provides information to new students on how deficiencies can be removed.

ADVISING

Academic Advising

Undergraduate Advising: Dann E. Husmann

Advising activities are coordinated by the Associate Dean for Student Affairs in the CASNR Dean’s Office. Each student in the College is assigned a faculty or professional adviser to assist in career planning, implementing, and completing academic programs. Assignments are made so that students will be working with an adviser who shares their academic interest. Students are encouraged to visit with their faculty or professional adviser about their career interests and development opportunities. Students may change their college, degree, and/or adviser. Such changes must be initiated in 103 Agricultural Hall.

Student Responsibility

Students are ultimately responsible for fulfilling all the requirements of the curriculum in which they are enrolled. Students are also responsible for initiating advising contacts and preparing for advising sessions. The mentoring relationship between academic advisers and students is confidential and is strengthened by advisers’ listening with empathy.

Students are expected to take responsibility for successful university experiences and effective advising sessions by:

1. Participating in New Student Enrollment and priority registration programs;

2. Scheduling appointments with advisers well in advance of priority registration and at other times as needed;

3. Identifying class choices from requirements of the selected program;

4. Identifying questions to address in advising sessions;

5. Informing advisers of any special needs, deficiencies or barriers that might affect academic success;

6. Following academic policies and procedures and meeting academic calendar deadlines (e.g. registration, fee payment, degree audit, filing for degree, etc.);

7. Knowing and completing degree or program requirements;

8. Monitoring their progress toward meeting degree requirements by maintaining a copy of their academic records and seeking assistance to resolve any errors or questions;

9. Acting on recommendations to seek assistance from the various student support services provided by the University; and

10. Achieving requirements for BS candidacy prior to senior year.

ACADEMIC PROGRAMS & POLICIES

Academic Load

Students need to be enrolled for 12 UNL credit hours to be considered full-time students.

Course Exclusions & Restrictions

Not more than 12 hours of independent study.
Not more than 24 hours of Pass/No Pass grade option.
Not more than 66 hours from two-year colleges.
Not more than 95 hours from other four-year institutions.
Not more than 6 hours of non-UNL courses can be counted among the last 36 hours earned.
No credit toward the BS degree is allowed for MATH 100A.
No more than 10 semester hours of below C grades are transferable from colleges outside the NU system. Grades below C can only be applied to free electives.

Credit Rules

Some currently-enrolled students, through outside study or relevant experience, may feel prepared to demonstrate that they have attained the knowledge and/or skills required to pass a particular UNL course. As an alternative to enrolling in the course, such students may elect to take a proficiency exam which tests for mastery of the course material. If a student scores satisfactorily on the examination, the student may be awarded credit for the course. Students can obtain detailed information from the Dean’s Office, 103 Agricultural Hall.

Dual Degrees

Dual Degrees from the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources

Students in CASNR may earn a bachelor of science degree in more than one program. They must complete all requirements for both programs.

Dual Degrees from CASNR and Other UNL Colleges

Students in other colleges may earn a bachelor of science from CASNR and a degree from another UNL college. Students will need to consult with both colleges to ensure all requirements are satisfied.

Honors Program

The College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources encourages qualified students to participate in the University Honors Program which is a UNL-wide program. The College’s honors students pursue degree programs offered by the College while completing the required honors courses.

All University Honors Program students are expected to complete a mentored thesis project with a faculty member of their choosing. Students should enroll in AGRI 299H in the spring semester of their sophomore year. As a part of AGRI 299H, students will identify a faculty thesis mentor and write a thesis proposal with their faculty thesis mentor. Because of the breadth of degrees, the program relies on faculty mentors within individual degree programs to determine the criteria for an undergraduate thesis in their area of endeavor. General guidance for mentors is provided as requested by Dr. Madhavan Soundararajan.

The Agricultural Research Division supports a competitive grants program to assist the College’s Honors Program students in the pursuit of their mentored theses. Students may also seek support from UNL’s Undergraduate Creative Activities and Research Experience (UCARE) program.

For more information about the University Honors Program, contact:

Dr. Madhavan Soundararajan

University of Nebraska–Lincoln

N251 Beadle

PO Box 88664

Lincoln, NE 68588-0664

Student Recognition

Each semester, students having 12 UNL semester-graded hours with a minimum grade point average of 3.75 or above are eligible for the Dean’s List.

Degrees with Distinction

In recognition of outstanding academic excellence, CASNR recommends the bachelors degree With Distinction, With High Distinction, and With Highest Distinction. Recommendations are made by the CASNR Committee on Scholarship. To be eligible for consideration by the Committee, undergraduate students must complete 45 credit hours for a letter grade (excluding Pass/No Pass marks) at UNL prior to the semester in which they graduate and must have completed 60 such credit hours at UNL at the time they graduate. To determine which of the eligible candidates will be recommended for the honor, the Committee currently uses the cumulative grade point average as follows:

With Distinction 3.800-3.899

With High Distinction 3.900-3.949

With Highest Distinction 3.950-4.000

NOTE: An undergraduate thesis is required to graduate With Highest Distinction regardless of a student’s grade point average.

International Study/Study Abroad

The College offers a variety of opportunities for students to enhance their international awareness. All students are required to demonstrate that they have a minimal international awareness, either through course work or experience. A minor in International Agriculture and Natural Resources can be designed for students who seek a broad understanding of the nature and role of agriculture and natural resources in the integrated world economy and the implications of world events for agriculture and natural resources. International study tours of one to three weeks in duration are also sponsored by CASNR to assist students in discovering different ways of thinking and acting as well as making them more informed global citizens. CASNR also promotes the Study Abroad program offered through the UNL Office of International Affairs which has opportunities of various lengths in numerous countries on all continents.

For financial assistance, the College offers the Robert and Beatrice Kleis Fund. One or more grants are awarded annually to undergraduate students in agriculture-related degree programs at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln. These grants shall be used to subsidize expenses associated with an international study program for credit. For more information on international opportunities, contact Dr. Arlen Etling, 103 Agricultural Hall, the International Affairs Office, or refer to “Study Abroad and Exchange Programs” on page 20 of this bulletin.

Senior Check/Degree Audit

UNL Registration and Records will identify CASNR students that have achieved senior status (89 credit hours or more) and inform the CASNR Dean’s Office.

Student Standing/Classification

Sophomore Standing. For admission to sophomore standing, a student must have completed all of the College entrance requirements except foreign language, earned a minimum of 27 semester hours of credit, and attained a total grade point average of at least 2.0.

Junior Standing. A student has junior standing after meeting the requirements for sophomore standing and completing 53 semester hours of credit.

Senior Standing. A student has senior standing after meeting the requirements for junior standing and completing 89 semester hours of credit.

Substitutions and Waivers

Requests for substitutions and waivers involving courses that fall within the basic four-year curriculum must be filed before the start of the fall semester for December graduates, before the start of the spring semester for May graduates and prior to the last day of classes of the spring semester for August graduates. Forms are available in 103 Agricultural Hall, from the student adviser, or on the Web site.

ACE REQUIREMENTS

All students must fulfill the Achievement Centered Education (ACE) requirements. Information about the ACE program may be viewed at ace.unl.edu.

The minimum requirements of CASNR reflect the common core of courses that apply to students pursuing degrees in the college. Students should work with an adviser to satisfy ACE outcomes 1, 2, 3, 4, 6 and 10 with the college requirements.

COLLEGE DEGREE REQUIREMENTS

College General Education Requirements (those separate or related to ACE)

Hours

College Integrative Course 3

AGRI/NRES 103 Intro to Agricultural & Natural Resource Systems 3

Mathematics and Statistics (beyond college algebra) 5

Select from: MATH 102, 104, 106, 203, and STAT 218.

NOTE: Proficiency at the college algebra level must be demonstrated either
by a placement exam or through course work. If MATH 103 is taken, only 2 cr hrs can be counted toward this requirement. Students must take MATH 203 prior to STAT 218 to receive UNL credit for both MATH 203 and STAT 218. Students who transfer STAT 218 credit to UNL will not receive UNL credit
for MATH 203.

Communications 6

Written Communication 3

Select from: ENGL 150, 151, 254; JGEN 120, 200

Communication and Interpersonal Skills electives 3

Select from: ENGL 101, 150, 151, 252, 253, 254; ALEC 102; JGEN 120, 200, 300; COMM 109, 209, 212, 286

Natural Sciences 8-9

Select two from the following three areas/courses:

CASNR Approved Life Sciences (4 cr)

CHEM 105 Chemistry in Context I or CHEM 109 General Chemistry I
(4 cr)

Select one from: (4-5 cr)

PHYS 141 Elementary General Physics (5 cr)

PHYS 151 Elements of Physics (4 cr)

PHYS 211 General Physics (4 cr)

MSYM 109 Physical Principles in Agriculture (4 cr)

Economics, Humanities and Social Sciences 18

ECON 211 or ECON 212 or AECN 141 3

ACE Courses 12

Select one course each from ACE outcomes 5, 7, 8, and 9.

Select one elective in this area 3

Major Requirements and Electives 85

Including Capstone Course 3

Minimum Credit Hours Required for Graduation 125

Foreign Languages/Language Requirement

Two units of a foreign language are required

Minimum Hours Required for Graduation

The College grants the bachelor of science degree in programs associated with agricultural sciences and natural resources. Students working toward a degree must earn at least 125 semester hours of credit. A minimum cumulative grade point average of C (2.0 on a 4.0 scale) must be maintained throughout the course of studies and is required for graduation.

Grade Rules

Removal of C-, D and F Grades

Only the most recent letter grade received in a given course will be used in computing a student’s cumulative grade point average if the student has completed the course more than once and previously received a grade or grades below C in that course.

The previous grade (or grades) will not be used in computation of the cumulative grade point average, but it will remain a part of the academic record and will appear on any transcript.

A student can remove from his/her cumulative average a course grade of C-, D+, D, D- or F if the student repeats the same course at the University of Nebraska and receives a grade other than P (pass), I (incomplete), N (no pass), W (withdrew), or NR (no report). If a course is no longer being offered, it is not eligible for the revised grade point average computation process.

For complete procedures and regulations, see the Schedule of Classes and the Summer Sessions Bulletin.

Pass/No Pass Limits

Students in CASNR may take any course offered on a Pass/No Pass basis within the 24-hour limitation established by the Faculty Senate. However, a department may specify that the Pass/No Pass status of its courses be limited to non-majors, or may choose to offer some courses for letter grades only.

GPA Requirements

A minimum cumulative grade point average of C (2.0 on a 4.0 scale) must be maintained throughout the course of studies and is required for graduation.

Transfer Credit Rules

Not more than 95 semester hours of credit from a four-year institution or another UNL college, can be applied toward programs in CASNR. A maximum of 66 hours may be transferred from a two-year college. Half of the credit needed for graduation can be earned through non-UNL courses, but such credit does not count toward residence; no more than 6 hours can be counted among the last 36 credit hours earned.

CASNR accepts no more than 10 semester hours of grades below C transferred from colleges outside the University of Nebraska system. Grades below C can only be applied to free electives.

Applicants must have a minimum cumulative grade point average of C (2.0 on a 4.0 scale) and at least a C average in the last semester of college enrollment at the student’s originating institution.

Residency

At least 30 of the last 36 hours of credit in all but excepted programs must be registered for and completed in residence in the UNL or at least 90 hours total must be registered for and completed in residence at UNL.

Extended Education and Independent Study Rules

There are many opportunities to earn college credit through the University of Nebraska–Lincoln Office of Extended Education and Outreach. Some of these credits may be applicable not only as elective credits, but also toward the fulfillment of the College’s education requirements. Half of the credit needed for graduation can be earned through non-resident courses, but such credit does not count toward residency.

For further information, contact:

Office of Extended Education and Outreach

University of Nebraska–Lincoln

900 N 21st Street

Lincoln, NE 68588-8307

402-472-2175

http://extended.unl.edu/

Students wishing to take part in independent studies must obtain permission; complete and sign a contract form; and furnish copies of the contract to the instructor, adviser, departmental office, and the Dean’s Office. The contract should be completed before registration. Forms are available in 103 Agricultural Hall.

Independent study projects include research, literature review or extension of course work under supervision and evaluation of a departmental faculty member.

Students may only count 12 hours of independent study toward their degrees and no more than 6 hours can be counted during their last 36 hours earned, excluding senior thesis, internships, and courses taught under an independent study number.

Bulletin Rule

Students must follow the undergraduate bulletin in effect when they enroll in the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources or any subsequent bulletin published while the student is enrolled in the College, provided the bulletin they follow is no more than 10 years old at the time of graduation. Students must, however, meet the requirements from one bulletin only.

Other College Degree Requirements

Capstone Course Requirement

A capstone course is required for each CASNR degree program. A capstone course is defined as a course in which students are required to integrate diverse bodies of knowledge to solve a problem or formulate a policy of societal importance.

DEGREES & MAJORS

Degree Programs

Agribusiness (Offered jointly with College of Business Administration)

Agricultural Economics

Agricultural Education

Agricultural Journalism

Agronomy

Animal Science

Applied Science

Biochemistry (Offered jointly with the College of Arts and Sciences)

Environmental Restoration Science

Environmental Studies (Offered jointly with the College of Arts and Sciences)

Fisheries and Wildlife

Food Science and Technology

Food Technology for Companion Animals

Forensic Science

Grassland Ecology and Management

Grazing Livestock Systems

Horticulture

Hospitality, Restaurant & Tourism Management (Offered jointly with the College of Education and Human Sciences)

Insect Science

Mechanized Systems Management

Natural Resource and Environmental Economics

Plant Biology (Offered jointly with the College of Arts and Sciences)

Plant Protection Sciences

PGA Golf Management

Turfgrass and Landscape Management

Veterinary Science

Veterinary Technology (Offered jointly with the Nebraska College of Technical Agriculture)

Water Science

Multiple Degrees

Students may complete requirements for more than one degree by declaring, prior to the last 30 hours of study, a dual degree. This is made possible through a common core required for all CASNR students. Students may consider these options with their faculty advisers.

An adviser is assigned for each additional degree declared. Appropriate forms must be processed in 103 Agricultural Hall.

Pre-Professional Programs

Integrated Science

Preforestry

Prelaw

Preveterinary Medicine

Related Degree Programs

Agricultural Engineering (Offered jointly with the College of Engineering)

Biological Systems Engineering (Offered jointly with the College of Engineering)

Landscape Architecture (Offered jointly with the College of Architecture)

Statistics (Offered jointly with the College of Arts and Sciences)

Professional Programs

Doctor of Plant Health

Veterinary Medicine

Certificate Programs

Contact John Markwell in the CASNR Deans’ Office

GRADUATE STUDENT INFORMATION

Graduate work leading to the masters degree is offered in the departments of Agricultural Economics; Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communication; Agronomy and Horticulture; Animal Science; Biochemistry; Biological Systems Engineering; Entomology; Food Science and Technology; Plant Pathology; Statistics; School of Veterinary Medicine and Biomedical Sciences; School of Natural Resources; the Center for Biological Chemistry; and in the interdepartmental area of nutrition. A master of applied science degree is also available.

Graduate work leading to the doctor of philosophy degree is offered by the departments of Agricultural Economics; Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communication (offered jointly with the College of Education and Human Sciences); School of Natural Resources (agricultural meteorology and forestry, fisheries and wildlife); Agronomy and Horticulture; Animal Science; Biological Systems Engineering/Agricultural Engineering; Entomology; Food Science and Technology; Plant Pathology (offered jointly with the School of Biological Sciences); Statistics; Veterinary Medicine and Biomedical Sciences; the Center for Biological Chemistry (offered jointly with the College of Arts and Sciences); and in the interdepartmental area of nutrition.

Further information appears in the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

MINORS & AREAS OF SPECIALIZATIONS OFFERED

Minors in the College will consist of 18 hours in the minor area of study, including at least six hours at the 300 and/or 400 level. Alternatively, 12 hours of 300- and/or 400-level courses will meet the requirement. At the discretion of the department(s) responsible for the minor, up to three hours of independent study may be counted toward the minor. Departments may specify additional requirements for their minor(s).

Minors offered through CASNR:

Agribusiness

Agricultural Economics

Agronomy

Animal Science

Applied Science

Biochemistry

Community Economics and Social Dynamics

Cooperative Extension

Energy Science

Environmental Communications

Environmental Education (ALEC)

Environmental Studies

Food Science and Technology

Forensic Science

Fisheries and Wildlife

Grassland Ecology & Management

Grazing Livestock Systems

Horticulture

Insect Science

Integrated Pest Management

International Agriculture and Natural Resources

Landscape Architecture

Leadership and Communication

Mechanized Systems Management

Natural Resource & Environmental Economics

Soil Science

Turfgrass and Landscape Management

Veterinary Science

Water Science

Filing for a Minor

Students wishing to declare a minor, must file a new C-D-M-A (College-Degree-Major-Adviser) form with the Dean’s Office prior to filing for graduation if the minor is exactly the same as that published in the student’s Undergraduate Bulletin. If there are any variations from the published minor, then the student must file the “Application for a Minor” form with the Dean’s Office.

Minors in Other Colleges

A student with a degree leading to a bachelor of science degree who wants to obtain a minor in a department in the College of Arts and Sciences should use the following procedure in making his/her request:

1. In consultation with the adviser, prepare the list of courses required for either Plan A or Plan B in the chosen minor as indicated in the College of Arts and Sciences section of this bulletin. Plan A indicates a single minor; Plan B indicates two minors with fewer hours in each subject than the number required for a single minor.

2. Submit the C-D-M-A form for the minor to the CASNR Dean’s Office prior to the deadline for submitting the application for graduation.

Students who have questions related to the minor after it is declared should consult an adviser in the college through which it is offered. The minor will be recorded on the student’s transcript.

Energy Science Minor

Coordinator: Assistant Professor Adam Liska, 246 Chase Hall

Professors: Conley, Hudgins, Schinstock, Verma, Walters, Yoder

Web site: http://energysciences.unl.edu

The energy science minor is designed to offer an educational component to University of Nebraska students that will prepare them with the knowledge, expertise, and background to successfully compete for positions with companies that are producing or developing renewable energy sources. The minor is for students who desire a broad understanding of energy related issues and an in-depth knowledge of energy in one or more of four elective thematic areas as well as for those seeking employment in agriculture, business/industry, communication, transportation, and government plus domestic use.

Minor Requirements

A minor in energy science (ENSC) will include a minimum of 18 credit hours of energy-related courses including three core courses (ENSC 110 Energy in Perspective, ENSC 220 Introduction to Energy Systems, and ENSC 230 Energy and the Environment: Economics and Policy). The remaining energy-related courses must come from one or more of the four elective thematic tracks (Energy and Natural Resources; Plant and Animal Bioenergy; Energy Engineering; and Energy Economics, Policy, and Human Dimensions) or be approved by the student’s academic adviser and the minor coordinator. Additionally, a 1-credit-hour Energy Seminar (AGRI 389) will be required, and an optional 1-credit-hour Nebraska Energy Study Tour (AGRI 311) and an optional 1-credit-hour Independent Energy Study (AGRI 496) will be offered. Completing each of the 1-credit-hour courses will allow a student to use those 3 credit hours in place of a course from one of the four thematic areas. At least 6 credit hours must be at the 300 or 400 level and up to 3 hours of energy-related independent study course work may be included.

Courses of Instruction (ENSC)

Courses suitable for automatic inclusion in one of the four elective thematic areas have been identified and the list can be obtained from the minor coordinator or any of the minor advisers listed above. Other courses may be included with prior approval of the minor coordinator.

A student in consultation with the academic adviser and a minor adviser (chosen from those above) prepares a list of courses on the CASNR Application for Minor form, obtains the appropriate signatures and submits the minor form to the minor coordinator prior to deadline for submitting the application for graduation. Upon approval, the minor program will be forwarded to the director of Registration and Records, with a copy supplied to the student’s major college. The minor will be recorded on the student’s transcript upon graduation.

International Agriculture and Natural Resources Minor

Coordinator: Professor Arlen Etling, 103 Agricultural Hall

Professors: Brink, Husmann, Francis, Mason, Schinstock, Peterson, Weller, Fulginiti

Associate Professor: Powell

Assistant Professors: Ellis, Thomas, Yiannaka

Professor of Practice: Hardin

Undergraduate Adviser: Swartz

The International Agriculture and Natural Resources minor is designed for students who seek a broad understanding of the nature and role of agriculture and natural resources in the integrated world economy and of the implications of world events for agriculture and natural resources in both the United States and abroad. The minor adds a global perspective to professional preparation. It is for students who desire a broad understanding of international trade and development issues as well as for those seeking employment in business firms or government agencies with international operations or interests.

Students typically build their minor program from courses organized around three areas: 1) a group of international courses in CASNR; 2) complimentary international courses offered in arts and sciences, and business administration; and 3) optional but highly recommended modern language instruction or experience as a base for building international communications skills. Two minor plans are available. One plan requires 12 credits in courses at or above the 300 level while the other plan requires 18 credits, including a minimum of 6 credits in courses at or above the 300 level.

12-Credit-Hour Plan

Overall 12 credits in approved courses* at or above the 300 level
Minimum 3 credits in CASNR courses other than Independent Study, AGRI 310 or NRES 315
Maximum 6 credits from any one department or program
Maximum 6 credits of modern languages at or above the 200 level
Maximum 3 credits of Independent Study and AGRI 310 or NRES 315 combined

18-Credit-Hour Plan

Overall 18 credits in approved courses*
Minimum 6 credits in CASNR courses
Minimum 6 credits in courses at or above the 300 level
Maximum 9 credits from any one department or program
Maximum 6 credits of modern languages at or above the 200 level
Maximum 3 credits of Independent Study
Maximum 3 credits of AGRI 310 or NRES 315

A student in consultation with the academic adviser and a minor adviser (chosen from those above) prepares a list of courses on the CASNR Application for Minor form, obtains the appropriate signatures and submits the minor form to the minor coordinator prior to deadline for submitting the application for graduation. While students may apply during their senior year, planning for the minor and application are recommended earlier in order to get maximum benefit from the minor.

Upon approval, the minor program will be forwarded to the director of Registration and Records, with a copy supplied to the student’s college. The minor will be recorded on the student’s transcript upon graduation. Students interested in pursuing an International Agriculture and Natural Resources minor should contact the minor coordinator or the CASNR Dean’s Office, 103 Agricultural Hall.

Pre-Professional Programs

Integrated Science Program

Coordinator: Associate Dean Dann Husmann, 103 Agricultural Hall

Many students are unsure of which degree program to choose when entering the university. In fact, over half of all students entering UNL change their degree program at least once. The following program is available for students not yet ready to make the decision.

Integrated Science

The courses listed below compose a nondegree program entitled Integrated Science. The program is designed for students who are interested in a bachelor of science degree in the applied life sciences, agricultural sciences, natural resource sciences, or social sciences offered in the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources, but are uncertain about a specific degree program. Such students will receive individualized advising and mentoring from a faculty member and be encouraged to participate in clubs and other pre-professional activities to help them decide which career path is right for them.

This list of suggested courses for the first semester should provide the student maximum flexibility while ensuring that courses contribute to any of the degree programs within the College as well as most programs in other colleges. During the first semester, students should contact Associate Dean Dann Husmann to identify an appropriate adviser(s) in a degree program(s) of their area of interest to plan appropriate courses for subsequent semesters. Students may be in the program for two years (62 credit hours). Students may declare a degree program at any time, but must declare a degree program at the completion of 62 hours.

Semester 1 Hours

ENGL 150 or ENGL 151 or JOUR 200 3

NRES/AGRI 103 Intro to Agricultural & Natural Resource Systems 3

BIOS 101 & BIOS 101L General Biology & Lab 4

MATH 101, 102, 104 or 106 2-5

Comprehensive elective 3

Total 15

Options:

If interested in Natural Resources and Environmental Science:

NRES 101 Natural Resources Orientation (1 cr)

If interested in Economics:

AECN 141 for humanities or social science

If interested in physical sciences:

PHYS 141, 211/221 or MSYM 109 for BIOS 101/101L

If math placement exam MATH 106:

Substitute STAT 218 (3 cr)

To learn about a particular degree program substitute humanities or social science with an entry-level course in one of the College disciplines.

Natural Resources Program

Natural Resources programs in CASNR emphasize an interdisciplinary approach to undergraduate and graduate education while providing students with a strong grounding in the program of their choice. The School of Natural Resources (SNR) is the administrative home to the natural resources programs: Environmental Restoration Science, Environmental Studies (Applied Climate Science emphasis and Natural Resources emphasis), Fisheries and Wildlife, Grassland Ecology and Management, Preforestry, and Water Science. The SNR is comprised of faculty from units within the Institute of Agriculture and Natural Resources (IANR), the College of Arts and Sciences, and other University colleges who focus on many critical natural resources and environmental issues.

The core requirements apply to every natural resources program leading to a bachelor of science degree and reflect the philosophy that there is a common foundation of knowledge essential for professionals in natural resource sciences. The specific requirements for each program are listed under each program description.

Courses of instruction in the natural resources programs provide students with the tools to describe the characteristics of natural resource systems which include the atmosphere, hydrosphere, geosphere and biosphere. In addition, graduates of these programs are expected to be able to understand the interactions among natural resource systems and to evaluate the impacts of humans as stewards and managers of these systems. Along with this technical expertise, each student will develop problem solving and communications skills which will enable them to take their place as a professional in a diversity of natural resources careers.

Hours

Core Requirements 69

Natural Resources 21-23

AGRI 103/NRES 103 Intro to Agricultural & Natural Resource Systems 3

Senior Capstone Course 3

Geographic Information Science Course (NRES 312, NRES 412, or NRES 418) 3-4

NRES 220 Principles of Ecology 3

NRES 323 Natural Resources Policy 3

Earth Science Course (GEOL 100, GEOL 101, GEOL 106; METR 200; NRES 108, NRES 208; SOIL 153; WATS 281) 3-4

Natural Resources & Environmental Economics I or II (NREE 265, NREE 465) 3

Mathematics and Statistics (beyond college algebra) (ACE 3) 5

Select from: MATH 102, MATH 103, MATH 104, MATH 106, and STAT 218

NOTE: Proficiency at the college algebra level must be demonstrated either by a placement exam or through course work. If MATH 103 is taken, only 2 cr hrs can be counted toward this requirement.

Natural Sciences (ACE 4) 16-17

BIOS 101 & 101L General Biology & Lab or BIOS 102 Cell Structure &

Function or AGRO 131 & 132 Plant Science & Lab 4

CASNR approved life sciences (other than BIOS 220) 4

CHEM 105 Chemistry in Context I or CHEM 109 General Chemistry I 4

Select from:

PHYS 141 Elementary General Physics I (5 cr)

PHYS 151 Elements of Physics (4 cr)

PHYS 211 General Physics I (4 cr)

MSYM 109 Physical Principles in Agriculture (4 cr)

Communication 9

Written Communication (ACE 1) 3

Oral Communication (ACE 2) 3

Communication and Interpersonal Skills electives 3

Economics, Humanities and Social Sciences 18

ECON 211 or ECON 212 or AECN 141 (ACE 6) 3

Select one course each from ACE outcomes 5, 7, 8 and 9 12

Select one elective in this area 3

Specific Major Requirements and Electives (including ACE 10) 56

Scholarships

The School of Natural Resources annually awards scholarships to freshmen and upperclassmen worth more than $25,000. Scholarship awards are made possible through generous gifts of alumni, local and state organizations and private donors.

Most SNR scholarships are based on academic performance and do not require an application. A number of scholarships are available. For more information on these scholarships contact the Natural Resources advising coordinator at 402/472-0636 or visit http://snr.unl.edu.

Academic Advising

Students are assigned a faculty adviser after admission into their programs. The adviser serves as a resource regarding the degree, academic plans and progress, and career options. Students are encouraged to regularly consult with their adviser, especially before registering for classes. The natural resources advising coordinator assist the faculty advisers with student consultations, is a resource for internship and employment opportunities, and will assist students in reviewing their academic records and course options.

Preforestry

Coordinator: Professor James R. Brandle, School of Natural Resources, 407 Hardin Hall

Forestry deals with the development and use of forests and related lands for a variety of uses– wood, water, wildlife, forage, recreation, and aesthetics. Multiple use is the foundation upon which management of our national forests is based; foresters today, through their forest management programs, are expected to provide a broad array of benefits to meet public demands. Students graduating from forestry programs find employment with federal, state, and local governments, and with private industry.

CASNR offers a two-year preforestry program, but does not offer a four-year forestry degree. Students must transfer at the end of their freshman or sophomore year. Graduate training in forestry is offered by the School of Natural Resources.

The preforestry curriculum consists of 60-70 hours selected from the courses listed below. Course selection is based on a student’s background and career goals. A program of study will be developed by the student and the adviser that involves one or two years at the University of Nebraska before transferring to the University of Missouri or another accredited forestry school. If a student desires to enter the University of Nebraska and later transfer to a forestry school other than the University of Missouri, the student should obtain information about the school’s entrance requirements and curriculum as early as possible to avoid unnecessary loss of credit.

An agreement with the University of Missouri allows Nebraska residents with the proper scholastic qualifications to enter that institution without paying out-of-state fees. Under this program a student may enter the University of Missouri directly from high school or transfer after one or two years at the University of Nebraska. Students interested in pursuing a preforestry program should select courses from the list below:

Hours

STAT 218 Intro to Statistics 3

BIOS 101 & BIOS 101L General Biology & Lab 4

BIOS 109 General Botany 4

BIOS 112 Intro to Zoology 4

CHEM 109 & CHEM 110 General Chemistry I & II 8

COMM 109 or COMM 209 Public Speaking 3

ECON 211 or ECON 212 Principles of Economics 3

ENGL 150 or ENGL 151 or ENGL 254 Composition 3

GEOL 101 Physical Geology 4

JGEN 200 Technical Communication 3

MATH 104 Calculus for Managerial & Social Sciences (3 cr)

or MATH 106 Analytical Geometry & Calculus I (5 cr) 3-5

NRES 101 Natural Resources Orientation 1

NRES/AGRI 103 Intro to Agricultural & Natural Resource Systems 3

PHYS/ASTR 151 Elements of Physics 4

SOIL 153 Intro to Soil Science 4

PreLaw

Law schools prefer students with broad academic backgrounds. Accordingly, there is no “prelaw” designation. Study toward a bachelor of science degree is excellent prelaw curriculum. There are no particular degree programs or courses students are advised to take to enhance their chances of admission to law school. Students should choose programs and courses that interest them. However, students should take many courses that require writing and complex readings. Students, especially those uncertain about law school, may want to take some courses that focus on law and the courts. While these courses will not enhance chances of admission, they will provide information about the legal system and the legal profession.

Prospective applicants are advised to take the Law School Admission Test (LSAT) during the summer before their last year or the fall of their last year. Information and application materials are available from the Career Services. The Official Guide to US Law Schools, available from the LSAT organization, contains material about the legal profession, the law school experience, the application process, and the individualized information on all American law schools approved by the American Bar Association.

CASNR students contemplating application to law school may contact Professor David Aiken, adviser in the Department of Agricultural Economics, 103 Filley Hall.

Veterinary Medicine Pre-Professional Program

Head: Professor David Hardin, Department of Veterinary and Biomedical Sciences, 120C Vet Basic Sciences

Interim Head: Professor Sheila Scheideler, Department of Animal Science, C203 Animal Sciences

Individuals wishing to enter the four-year professional curriculum leading to the degree, doctor of veterinary medicine (DVM), must first complete two or more years of preveterinary general education. Courses taken during preprofessional education must satisfy the entrance prerequisites for the college of veterinary medicine of the person’s choice. At the University of Nebraska–Lincoln, it usually requires a minimum of three years to complete the preprofessional requirements, but students must declare an acceptable degree program at the conclusion of their sophomore year. Certain options in the veterinary science and veterinary technology degree programs meet the pre-veterinary requirements of colleges of veterinary medicine. 8 The student should discuss special variations and other colleges of interest with their academic adviser at the earliest possible date.

The Preveterinary Program IS NOT a degree-granting program. Completion of the preprofessional program alone in fulfilling the prerequisites for admission to a college or school of veterinary medicine does not result in the awarding of a degree from the University of Nebraska. Students are to select an appropriate field within which to work toward a college degree while concurrently working toward completion of preprofessional requirements. Students are encouraged to consider courses of study with a degree-granting program in veterinary science (biomedical science, microbiology options, or veterinary medicine options), veterinary technology, animal science, food science and technology, biochemistry or other fields compatible with the preprofessional program that leads to a bachelor of science degree. Students can also complete preveterinary prerequisites with a degree program in wildlife or environmental studies, leading to a bachelor of science degree. It is also possible to pursue these preveterinary requirements in degree-granting programs outside the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources, such as the College of Arts and Sciences.

Students are expected to designate an acceptable degree program by the end of their sophomore year and to work with an adviser in that field. Additional advisory support relating to preprofessional requirements and admission policies is provided by advisers within the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources, University of Nebraska–Lincoln.

The program utilizes an “Advising Plus” model which involves faculty from the Department of Veterinary and Biomedical Sciences (Laura Hardin, Rodney Moxley, and Michael Carlson) and the Department of Animal Science (Dennis Brink and Thomas Burkey). Team advising will be utilized to expose students to all the opportunities in animal health and assist them in identifying the appropriate degree program.

Students interested in veterinary medicine are encouraged to participate in the Pre-veterinary Club to learn about the exciting advancement and developments within the profession.

It is not recommended that preveterinary students take any courses on a Pass/No Pass basis (unless this is the only grading option for a given course, e.g. VBMS 101) because courses taken Pass/No Pass may not be accepted for preprofessional prerequisites. Letter grades are required to evaluate credentials of applicants for veterinary college admission.

See individual degree programs for specializations in those areas.

###

College of Education and Human Sciences

Admission (Content Box Heading) (Major Page):

College Admission

General

Students accepted by the University must have an ACT of 20 or SAT of 950, or rank in the upper half of their high school graduating class, and have the following high school preparation to be eligible for admission to the College of Education and Human Sciences:

four years of English that include intensive reading and writing experience;
two years of one foreign language;
four years of mathematics that include Algebra I, II, geometry and one year that builds on a knowledge of algebra;
three years of natural sciences that include at least two years selected from biology, physics, chemistry, and earth science and one year of laboratory instruction;
three years of social studies, that include at least one year of American and/or world history and one year of history, American government, and/or geography.

To remain current, College of Education and Human Sciences students must enroll in, and complete, at least one UNL course that will apply toward degree requirements during a 12 month period.

Transfer Students

Transfer students from universities or colleges outside of UNL and readmitted students seeking admission to the College of Education and Human Sciences must have an accumulated average of 2.0 on a 4.0 scale or above and no high school deficiencies. Students who do not meet these requirements must enroll as deciding students in the Division of General Studies or in another college. Once they have completed 12 graded hours at UNL with a minimum 2.0 grade point average, and have removed any high school deficiencies, UNL students may apply for admission to the College.

International Students

The College of Education and Human Sciences welcomes undergraduate international students.

As a part of admission to the College, international students must present a TOEFL score of 550 or higher, and TSE score of 230 or higher. Students seeking teacher education and state certification must meet the same requirements as any other undergraduate students, including the Pre-Professional Skills Test or other basic skills test approved by the Nebraska Department of Education.

Students who have received a degree outside of the United States and are interested in teacher certification are required to have a transcript review completed by an approved agency not directly associated with the University of Nebraska. See the director of advising in the College Student Services Center in Henzlik 105 for details.

Students Transferring from Another UNL College

Students transferring to the College of Education and Human Sciences from another University of Nebraska–Lincoln college or from the Division of General Studies must have a minimum cumulative GPA of 2.0, be in good academic standing, and meet the freshman entrance requirements that exist at the time of their admission to the College of Education and Human Sciences.

Readmitted Students

Students who readmit following an absence of one year or more must meet all requirements in the undergraduate bulletin in effect at the time of readmission and enrollment. Students who transfer to another UNL college and later return to the College of Education and Human Sciences will be considered readmitted students.

Students who transfer out of a teacher education program, but who continue their certification program while seeking a degree in another UNL college, are exempt from this policy.

Students who left the College on probation or who were dismissed may seek readmission to the College after two semesters by applying to the UNL Admissions Office. Readmission is not assured. However, the admissions committee is receptive to giving students a second opportunity to be successful. The committee is interested in knowing what the student has done in the intervening period that would suggest the student will be successful when readmitted. Successfully completing correspondence courses and/or community college courses is an effective way to demonstrate one’s commitment to academic success.

Admission Deficiencies/Removal of Deficiencies

All admission deficiencies must be removed prior to admission to the College.
Students admitted to the University with three or more high school deficiencies, or two deficiencies in a single category other than foreign language, will not be admitted to a teacher education program until such deficiencies are removed.
Students who are admitted through the Admission by Review process with core course deficiencies will have certain conditions attached to their enrollment at UNL. JIM--These conditions are explained under “Removal of Deficiencies.” on page 6—gotta do something with red text!
The Dean of the College of Education and Human Sciences will make the final decision concerning any problems or questions that may arise in satisfying requirements to remove deficiencies.

Other Admission Requirements

Pre-education

All newly admitted students who are pursuing a teacher preparation program, except those in nonteaching majors, are classified as pre-education until admitted to a Teacher Education Program.

Admission to a Teacher Education Program (TEP)

College of Education and Human Sciences does not guarantee admission to a teacher education program. Admission to the advanced phases of teacher education is selective and, in some endorsements, highly competitive. Selection to a TEP is based upon the following criteria:

1. Elementary education students must earn a minimum of 30 credit hours of college credit; secondary education students must earn a minimum of 42 credit hours of college credit.

2. Completion and submission of the Teacher Education Program Approval Form.

3. Completion of TEAC 331 or 430 or 431 or 434 or 437 or 496 (3 hrs) or approved transfer course, and EDPS 250 or 251 with a 2.5 cumulative average in the two classes, and no grade lower than C.

4. Documentation of proficiency in reading, writing, and mathematics through successful completion of a basic skills examination that meets the Nebraska Department of Education competency requirement.

5. Completion of one course in communication studies selected from COMM 109, 205, 209, 210, or 286, or approved substitute.

6. Faculty recommendations.

7. Completion of a personal and professional fitness self-disclosure form as well as the completion of a formal criminal history review. (See Felony and Misdemeanor Convictions under OTHER.)

8. Specific programs may have particular learning outcomes that students must address as part of the application process.

Post-baccalaureate Students Seeking Initial Teaching Certification

Students who have received a bachelors degree or higher and desire to obtain an initial teaching certificate may do so by pursuing a non-degree post-baccalaureate initial certification program with or without a masters degree. They must apply to the Graduate College for admission to the University of Nebraska–Lincoln and apply to a Teacher Education Program (TEP) for admission to the initial teaching certification program. Students are also required to apply for admission to a degree program if they desire to pursue a masters degree with their certification program. All students seeking initial certification must meet with the post baccalaureate assistant academic adviser. Those seeking a masters degree will also meet with a faculty adviser. Post-baccalaureate students interested in completing a teacher education program should refer to this bulletin as to policies and regulations for program completion. For specific guidelines, see the Student Services Center.

Admission to Student Teaching

All students who are candidates for an appropriately endorsed Nebraska Teacher’s Certificate are required to student teach. Students who plan to student teach in the fall semester must complete the student teaching application form and submit it by the preceding March 1 to the Director of Field Experiences in 104 Henzlik Hall; students planning to student teach in the spring semester must apply by the preceding October 1. The basic program for student teaching provides for a full-day experience on a semester basis. Students enrolled in an elementary education dual major will complete requirements for student teaching in both majors. Admission to student teaching requires the following:

1. Matriculation in a teacher education program in the College of Education and Human Sciences, the Graduate College, or dual matriculation in the College of Education and Human Sciences and another college.

2. Admission to a teacher education program.

3. Senior standing (89 hours or more) with a minimum cumulative GPA of 2.5.

4. Minimum average of 2.5 in each endorsement area with no grade below C.

5. A minimum grade point average of 2.5 in preprofessional and professional education courses and no grade below C in pre-professional education courses and no grade below a C+ in professional education courses.

6. Completion of a criminal history check that will be conducted by an independent party (fee required).

ADVISING (Content Box Heading):

Academic Advising

The College of Education and Human Sciences Student Services Center is staffed with professional advisers who assist students with assessing educational goals, planning programs of study, understanding program requirements and knowing policies and procedures. As course selection and registration are critical to the timely completion of their academic goals, students are well advised to seek regular academic counseling from their assigned advisers in the Center to obtain the most up-to-date information regarding current requirements and timely completion of degree programs.
The Center is also staffed with professionals to coordinate field placements, student teaching and teaching certificate application.
Ultimately, students are themselves responsible for fulfilling all the requirements of the curriculum in which they are enrolled. The intellectual mentoring relationship between academic adviser and student is protected by confidentiality and strengthened by listening with understanding to student concerns. A student remains with an adviser for the duration of the educational program unless the student changes his/her program of study.
Intellectual mentoring by the academic adviser fosters:

1. Development of an awareness of available choices, alternatives and resources;

2. Guidance with decision making;

3. Encouragement to expand horizons by full participation in university life; and

4. Promotion of readiness to meet career, life and graduate/professional school challenges.

Student Responsibility

Students are expected to take responsibility for a successful university experience and effective advising sessions by:

1. Participating in orientation/early enrollment programs;

2. Scheduling appointments with advisers prior to priority registration and at other times as needed;

3. Identifying class choices from requirements of the preferred program or major;

4. Identifying questions to address;

5. Informing advisers of any special needs, deficiencies or barriers that might affect academic success;

6. Knowing academic policies and academic calendar deadlines, procedures (e.g., registration, fee payment) and degree or program requirements;

7. Remaining informed about progress in meeting academic requirements by maintaining careful academic records and seeking assistance to resolve any errors or questions; and

8. Following through on recommendations to seek assistance from the various student support services provided by the university.

ACADEMIC PROGRAMS & POLICIES (Content Box Heading):

Academic Load

A maximum of 18 credit hours may be taken each semester (4 hours in the Pre Session; 7 in each five week session; 9 in the eight week session) without special authorization from the Director of Advising. UNL students must be enrolled in 12 hours in a semester to be considered full time. Most first-year students are advised to take no more than 12-15 credit hours in the first semester. This allows new students to make an easier transition from high school to college study. Most students require 2-3 hours of preparation for every hour in class, so a schedule of 12 credit hours is actually equivalent to a 36-48 hour a week job.

Outside work may interfere with academic success. The student who must work should plan to take a lighter load and consider taking some summer sessions or an extra semester or two to complete the work required for a degree.

Students should check if restrictions on the number of graded hours each term govern their continued eligibility for medical insurance, scholarships, and/or financial aid.

Course Exclusions & Restrictions

MATH 95C, MATH 100A, CSCE 137 and courses taken to remove high school deficiencies may not be applied toward graduation requirements, not even as elective credit.

Credit Rules

Credit by Exam

Students who believe that previous experience satisfies course requirements may approach the appropriate academic department for possible credit by exam options. Credit is rarely given simply for work experience.

Student Recognition

A College Student Award Committee determines criteria for awards and recognizes outstanding students.

Dean’s List

A Dean’s List of Education and Human Sciences and dual matriculated students who meet the stated criteria is published in the fall and spring semesters. To be eligible, students must have a minimum semester grade point average of 3.75 in 12 or more graded semester hours. Exceptions are made for students taking required courses offered only on a Pass/No Pass basis.

Student teachers and practica students who either 1) enter the semester of student teaching with a cumulative GPA of 3.75 or above, or 2) earn a 3.75 GPA during the preceding semester on the basis of 12 or more graded semester hours, will be eligible for the Dean’s List with recommendation from the University supervisor.

Post-baccalaureate students working on certifications are eligible upon request to the Director of Advising, but only undergraduate hours apply.

Degrees with Distinction

In recognition of outstanding academic excellence, the College of Education and Human Sciences recommends the bachelors degree With Distinction, With High Distinction and With Highest Distinction. All students graduating with distinction must meet the following criteria:

Candidates must have completed at least 60 hours at UNL (Child, Youth and Family Studies students enrolled at UNO) by the time of graduation.
Persons in teaching endorsement programs must satisfactorily complete student teaching; persons in non-endorsement programs must satisfactorily fulfill practica or other internship experiences as required by their programs of study.
Eligibility is based on the cumulative grade point average of all credit hours taken at UNL (UNO) prior to the beginning of the term in which the student receives his or her degree.

Highest Distinction. Candidates for the bachelors degree who have successfully completed the program to which they were admitted and achieved a 4.0 cumulative grade point average.

High Distinction. Candidates for the bachelors degree who have successfully completed the program to which they were admitted and achieved a 3.950 thru 3.999 cumulative grade point average.

Distinction. Candidates for the bachelors degree who have successfully completed the program to which they were admitted and have achieved a 3.850 thru 3.949 cumulative grade point average.

International Study/Study Abroad

Substitutions & Waivers

Special Requests for Substitutions and Waivers

In rare cases, there may be a need for students to request a special substitution or waiver to curriculum requirements. Such a request is made only in exceptional and unusual circumstances and cannot serve as an excuse for not following correct degree requirements. Specific instructions and procedures are available from students’ academic advisers in the Student Services Center, 105 Henzlik Hall.

ACE REQUIREMENTS (Content Box Heading) (Major Page):

All students must fulfill the Achievement Centered Education (ACE) requirements. Information about the ACE program may be viewed at ace.unl.edu.

The goals of a general, liberal education are to promote the understanding of broad areas of knowledge and to develop attitudes, values, thought processes, and basic abilities expected from an educated person. All UNL students who are following the 2010-11 bulletin will be required to complete a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated ACE Student Learning Outcome (SLO) areas which are described on page at ace.unl.edu. It is highly recommended that students contact their adviser prior to registering for ACE classes in order to insure that each of the class selections are in the best interest of the students’ academic program.

Additional ACE Course Work for Secondary Education:

Students in secondary education programs need four additional ACE courses.

One of the 14 total ACE courses must be an approved speech course: COMM 109, 205, 209,210. At least two of the 14 ACE courses must be at the 300 or 400 level.

BULLETIN TO USE (Content Box Heading) (Major Page):

Transfer and readmitted students must meet the graduation requirements for the College of Education and Human Sciences as stated in the current catalog in effect at the time they enter or reenter the College. Students must fulfill degree requirements that exist at the time of their admission to the college, not at the time they enter UNL.

COLLEGE DEGREE REQUIREMENTS (Content Box Heading) (Major Page):

College General Education Requirements (those separate or related to ACE)

Foreign Languages/Language Requirement

Minimum Hours Required for Graduation (if the college has a minimum hour requirement)

Total hours required for graduation vary by program. Students must refer to the specific major link to learn more about specific degree requirements for each undergraduate major.

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Education Majors:

Grades below C (C-, D+, D and D-) may not be applied in any endorsement, professional education requirement or non-teaching major professional course requirement in degrees leading to teacher preparation.

Up to 9 hours of transfer credit with grades below C may be applied to the General Education requirements and elective classes in programs leading to the undergraduate degree in teacher preparation. Transfer grades of C- and D may not be used in the major/endorsement area courses or in the professional courses in teacher preparation programs.

Human Science Majors:

For Human Science majors, up to 9 hours of grades below C (C-, D+, D, D-) from other academic institutions can only be applied to general education requirements and elective classes.

Grades Earned Outside UN System

The college will accept no more than 9 credit hours of grades less than a C from any program outside the University of Nebraska system. Grades below a C can only be applied to general education requirements and elective classes.

Up to 9 hours of transfer credit with grades below C may be applied to the General Education requirements and elective classes in programs leading to the undergraduate degree in teacher preparation. Transfer grades of C- and D may not be used in the major/endorsement area courses or in the professional courses in teacher preparation programs.

For Human Science majors, up to 9 hours of grades below C (C-, D+, D, D-) from other academic institutions can only be applied to general education requirements and elective classes.

Transfer courses are evaluated by the University and the College to determine UNL and College course equivalencies. The College determines which courses will be accepted and how they will apply toward degree requirements. Sixty-six (66) is the maximum number of hours that will be accepted on transfer from a two-year college. Ninety-five (95) is the maximum number of hours that will be accepted on transfer from accredited four-year colleges and universities. Courses taken 10 years before admission or readmission to the College will be evaluated by the major department to determine if it is appropriate to accept those courses for transfer and application to degree requirements. Specific courses will be reviewed in keeping with the guidelines specified by each department.

Grades Earned Within UN System

JIM--Grades of D-, D, D+, and C- satisfy requirements in all programs in the College unless specified otherwise under the “Degree Programs and Requirements in Education (Teacher Preparation)” on page 253, “Courses of Instruction in Education” on page 260, or “Areas of Study in Human Sciences” on page 268 of this bulletin. Students who receive a grade of D-, D, D+, C-, however, are encouraged to retake the course.

Pass/No Pass Limits

Education Majors

A student enrolled at the University may, in certain instances, take a grading option of Pass/No Pass (P/N) for a specific course. A grade of pass represents satisfactory completion of a course with a grade of C or better. Credits earned under the pass grade option count toward graduation, but no grade points are tabulated in the cumulative grade point average. Likewise, a grade of no pass is not tabulated in the grade point average. The following rules apply to students who are enrolled in teacher preparation programs who choose the Pass/No Pass option:

1. Only one course in each subject endorsement; two courses in a field endorsement.

2. For students in certification programs, pre-professional and professional education classes may not be taken Pass/No Pass unless a class already has a Pass/No Pass designation

3. Any course in the general education requirements unless otherwise stipulated by the department of the course.

4. Total P/N credits may not exceed 12 credit hours. This limit does not include courses offered on a Pass/No Pass only basis.

Human Science Majors

The Pass/No Pass (P/N) option is designed for students who want to study elective areas or topics when they may have minimum preparation. If used for this purpose, the option can enrich the student’s academic experience without lowering the student’s grade point average. Free electives may be taken P/N. Students can earn no more than 12 hours of pass credit excluding courses offered on Pass/No Pass only basis.

Not all classes in Human Science majors can be taken under the Pass/No Pass option. All courses, specified by course and number, must be taken for a grade. Should a student have earned a P in one of the courses prior to starting the option, the P will be reviewed by the appropriate department.

GPA Requirements

Grade Requirements in Education Programs

Requirements for completion of an undergraduate degree in a teacher preparation program include a minimum cumulative grade point average (GPA) of 2.5. Students seeking certification must also have a 2.5 GPA in their education courses with no grade lower than a C. Students are also required to have a 2.5 GPA in their subject endorsement area(s) with no grade lower than C in either area.

Grade Requirements in Human Sciences

A minimum 2.0 cumulative GPA is required to graduate. Students in family and consumer sciences education must have a minimum 2.5 GPA.

Transfer Credit Rules

Maximum Number of Hours for Transfer

Transfer courses are evaluated by the University and the College to determine UNL and College course equivalencies. The College determines which courses will be accepted and how they will apply toward degree requirements. Sixty-six (66) is the maximum number of hours that will be accepted on transfer from a two-year college. Ninety-five (95) is the maximum number of hours that will be accepted on transfer from accredited four-year colleges and universities.

Courses taken 10 years before admission or readmission to the College will be evaluated by the major department to determine if it is appropriate to accept those courses for transfer and application to degree requirements. Specific courses will be reviewed in keeping with the guidelines specified by each department.

Transfer Credit from Technical, Non-Accredited and Foreign Institutions

Students who desire to transfer from these institutions must have each course evaluated by the appropriate departmental representative. All rules stated above in reference to grades and maximum credit hours apply. For additional information and guidance in this process contact the Dean’s Office.

Transfer Agreements with UNO and UNK

Transfer agreements between the three institutions within the University System allow for a smooth transition for students interested in taking courses from UNO, UNK, and/or UNL. Although restrictions noted above on grades and maximum transfer hours still apply, there are some exceptions. For purposes of residency, courses from UNO and UNK fulfill these requirements. Students planning to major in a program in the college should read the specific requirements noted with individual programs. Questions about academic transfer should be addressed to the Dean’s Office.

Transfer Agreements with Community Colleges

Articulation agreements and “Transfer with Ease Programs” with Nebraska community colleges indicate how courses and programs will transfer to UNL and the College of Education and Human Sciences. The same guidelines noted above on the acceptance of courses, grades, and hours also apply to these institutions. Students interested in transferring from a community college should consult with their school or the Student Services Center to determine which courses will transfer to fulfill specific College of Education and Human Sciences requirements.

Courses from accredited two-year institutions will generally not be substituted for 400-level human sciences classes in the College. The 300-level courses will be considered on an individual basis by the respective departments in the College of Education and Human Sciences.

Courses taken prior to course articulation agreements will be accepted contingent upon departmental validation of the credit.

Course Level Requirements (Hour Requirement 300+)

Residency

A minimum total of 125 credit hours of course work in teacher preparation programs is required for a bachelors degree in education and human sciences, of which 30 of the last 36 hours of credit needed for a degree must be registered for and completed in residence at a University of Nebraska system institution. This means that the last year of work must generally be spent at UNL. Half of the credit needed to graduate can be earned by means of correspondence courses; however, such credit does not count toward residence and thus cannot be among the last 30 credit hours earned. Independent Study and summer reading courses sponsored by the UNL Extended Education do not apply to residency.

Residency Requirement and Study Abroad Courses

Credit earned during study abroad may be used toward degree requirements if students participate in prior approved programs and register through UNL (see “Study Abroad and Exchange Programs” on page 20).

Extended Education and Independent Study Rules

Independent Study and summer reading courses sponsored by the UNL Extended Education do not apply to residency.

Other College Degree Requirements

Grade Appeals

Any student enrolled in a course in the College of Education and Human Sciences who wishes to appeal alleged unfair and prejudicial treatment by a faculty member shall present his/her appeal in writing to the Dean’s Office no later than 30 days after notice of the student’s final course grade has been mailed from campus.

Students may use and are encouraged to use the following sequential procedures to appeal the grade. The problem may be solved at any of the levels of the appeal procedure.

1. Contact the instructor. Frequently the problems can be solved at this point.

2. Submit a request to the chair of the department.

3. Take the case to the departmental Grading Appeals Committee. The Committee is contacted by the department chair.

4. Take the case to the College Appeals, Retention and Certification Committee by contacting the Dean’s Office.

The complaint will be forwarded to a committee consisting of faculty and student representatives. After a hearing, the Committee will make a written recommendation regarding the appeal. The Committee’s recommendation is binding on the appealing student and faculty member.

Senior Check and Degree Application

During student teaching, all students must apply for and have completed a senior check.

It is the student’s responsibility to notify Graduation Services, 109 Canfield Administration Building, early in the semester the student plans to graduate. Failure to meet the published deadline will delay graduation one full term.

Program Evaluation and Assessment

College wide assessment and department assessment committees, comprised of faculty and students, assist the college/departments in evaluating the effectiveness of programs. Students participate in college-wide surveys, exit interviews and portfolio development. Student involvement in assessment will in no way affect a student’s GPA or graduation. In addition, graduates may be asked to participate in post graduation surveys which seek information about professional preparation and employment.

Students in education teaching endorsement programs are required to do any or all of the following, prior to graduation:

pass a test that measures subject area knowledge;
have their teaching performance judged to be satisfactory by professional evaluators;
complete the appropriate Praxis II tests for their respective endorsement areas and grade levels.

OTHER (CONTENT BOX HEADING):

Felony and Misdemeanor Convictions

The Nebraska Department of Education policy requires that a person with any felony conviction or a misdemeanor conviction involving abuse, neglect, or sexual misconduct shall not be allowed to participate in pre-student teaching laboratory and classroom experiences or student teach without approval of the Board of Education. To comply with this policy, the College of Education and Human Sciences will require each student to affirm under oath that he/she does not have any convictions in the above-named areas prior to each field experience. If a student does have any felony or any misdemeanor convictions, he/she is required to meet with the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experiences as soon as possible.

To ensure that each individual complies with this policy, all students who are pursuing a teaching certificate will be required to periodically complete a “Personal and Professional Fitness” form (PPF) as well as submit to two formal reviews of their criminal history, which is conducted by an independent third party. The first review will be completed during the first semester of the individual’s freshman year or upon the individual’s transfer into the College of Education and Human Sciences. At that time, each student will complete the PPF form and will also be expected to submit a request for the review of their criminal history. The PPF form will again be completed and submitted as a part of the application process for the Teacher Education Program. The final review, including the submission of the PPF form and the completion of a second criminal history check, will take place as part of the application process to student teach. Each student is responsible for the cost of the two criminal history reviews.

Professional and Ethical Behavior

Teaching is a profession that requires its potential candidates to be individuals of integrity. Prospective teachers must be able to demonstrate that they are individuals of strong moral character who can make mature decisions for themselves and for their students. Teachers are responsible for the education, safety and well-being for anyone in their charge. Therefore, the College of Education and Human Sciences is interested in training future teachers who show a high degree of moral character and the ability to act responsibly. These individuals must be able to serve as representatives of our College and the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.

With this in mind, it is the responsibility of the student to inform the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experiences of any convictions handed down by any court or any plea of guilty made by the individual. At that time, should the College, through its reasonable judgment, determine that one’s individual behavior represents a lack of integrity, questionable moral/ethical character, or otherwise indicates a potential of risk to young persons and others in the educational community, the College of Education and Human Sciences reserves the right to deny entry to or dismiss anyone from any program which leads to certification. More specifically, these kinds of behavior shall be adequate foundation to deny any candidate or potential candidate from participation in any practicum, pre-practicum, student teaching or similar field experience, since the interests and safety of the children, and young people present in the classroom, schools and other venues where these practicum experiences take place are paramount.

Problematic behaviors, which the College of Education and Human Sciences reasonably determines renders the candidate a risk to the educational community or demonstrates a likelihood of illegal activity, may be established by any credible means, including the facts surrounding a record of arrests and/or convictions.

Similarly, behaviors which result in a finding by a court or other governmental body that the individual is:

a mentally ill and dangerous person;
mentally incompetent to stand trial;
acquitted of criminal charges because of insanity;
an incapacitated person;
a person in need of a guardian or conservator, or;
a person unable to manage his or her property due to mental illness, mental deficiency, or chronic use of drugs or chronic intoxication are the kind of behaviors which are likely to disqualify a candidate from participation in practicum experiences and other College of Education and Human Sciences programs.

DEGREES & MAJORS (Content Box Heading):

Degrees and Endorsements In Education (Teacher Preparation)

The College of Education and Human Sciences offers an undergraduate bachelor of science in education and human sciences degree. The College offers undergraduate programs leading to a bachelor of science in education and human sciences in more than 40 different teaching endorsements and in undergraduate programs leading to careers in fields, such as administrative resource management and technical education.

Some students in other colleges choose to seek certification, completing a degree in their home college while meeting all requirements for teacher certification in the College of Education and Human Sciences.

Early field placement in public and private schools is a nationally recognized hallmark of the teacher education program in the College of Education and Human Sciences. These placements permit students to gain classroom experience early in their University studies, allowing them an opportunity to know both the satisfactions and the pressures of the classroom atmosphere long before they approach the end of their undergraduate work.

Secondary education endorsements (or majors) are divided into fields or single subjects. Students graduating from the College of Education and Human Sciences or working toward certification must complete one field endorsement or two subject endorsements and must take a methods course and student teach in each endorsement. A few supplemental endorsements are available that may enhance employment possibilities. Endorsements that require two subjects are noted with an (*). Students may contact the College Student Services Center, 105 Henzlik Hall, for additional information or an explanation of the requirements

For undergraduate endorsements, see the individual endorsements listed on the major search box on the main page of the bulletin.

Undergraduate Teaching Endorsements

– Agricultural Education. (see College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources

– Art. (Grades K-12)

– *Art. (Grades K-6)

– *Biology. (Grades 7-12)

– Business Education/Cooperative Education. (Grades 7-12)

– *Chemistry. (Grades 7-12)

– Early Care and Education. (Birth-Age 5)

– Early Childhood Education—Inclusive. (Birth-Grade 3)

– *Earth Science. (Grades 7-12)

– Economics and History. (Grades 7-12)

– Elementary Education. (Grades K-6):

– Dual endorsement programs in Elementary Education

– Elementary Education–Early Childhood Education. (Elementary Education Grades K-6, Early Childhood Education Birth-Grade 3).

– Elementary Education and Mild/Moderate Disabilities. (Grades K-6)

– Elementary Education and Deaf or Hard of Hearing Education (pre-professional concentration). (Grades K-6)

– English. (Grades 7-12)

– Family and Consumer Sciences. (Grades 7-12)

– French. (Grades 7-12) Under review. Please see adviser.

– Geography and History. (Grades 7-12)

– German. (Grades 7-12) Under review. Please see adviser.

– *History and a Non-Social Science Discipline. (Grades 7-12)

– Industrial Tech?

– Journalism and Mass Communications and English. (Grades 7-12)

– Language Arts. (Grades 7-12)

– Latin. Under review. Please see adviser.

– Marketing Education and Cooperative Education. (Grades 7-12)

– Mathematics. (Grades 7-12)

– Middle Grades Education. (Grades 4-9)

– Mild/Moderate Disabilities. (Grades 7-12)

– Mild/Moderate Disabilities (Grades 7-12) and Deaf or Hard of Hearing (pre-professional

– Mild/Moderate Disabilities: (Grades 7-12)

– Music. For a description of the programs for teacher preparation in music, see the requirements for the bachelor of music education degree in the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts section within this catalog.

– Natural Science. (Grades 7-12)

– Physical Science. (Grades 7-12)

– *Physics. (Grades 7-12)

– Political Science and History. (Grades 7-12)

– *Reading and Writing. (Grades 7-12)

– Russian. (Grades 7-12) Under review. Please see adviser.

– Social Science. (Grades 7-12) 62-63 hours

– Spanish. (Grades 7-12) 30-46 hours:

– Speech and English. (Grades 7-12)

– Speech-Language Pathologist. (Grades P-12)

– Theatre and English. (Grades 7-12)

Supplemental Undergraduate Endorsements

To pursue a supplemental endorsement, students must either hold a valid teaching certificate or be admitted to a teacher education program. Also, supplements endorsements require the completion of either a field or a subject endorsement.

Coaching. (Grades 7-12) 15 hours: ATHT 235 3 hrs; ATHC 279 and 494 3 hrs each; 6 hrs selected from ATHC 311, 312, 317, 318.

Cooperative Education–Diversified Occupations. (9 hours): TEAC 424 or 815 3 hrs; TEAC 425 or 825 3 hrs; SPED 434/834 3 hrs. NOTE: Endorsement in business, marketing, or industrial technology required.

English as a 2nd Language–Undergraduate. (Grades K-12) 21 hrs: TEAC 213 and 438 3 hrs each; TEAC 441 or 411 or 411A or 411B 3 hrs; TEAC 413A, 413B, 413D, 497E 3 hrs each.

English as a 2nd Language–Graduate. (Grades K-12) 19 hrs: TEAC 438/838 or 813K 3 hrs, 841 or 811 or 811A or 811B 3 hrs, 813A, 813B, 813D 3 hrs each, 897E 1 hr; TEAC 813J or COMM 950 or 950B 3 hrs.

High Ability Education. (Grades K-12): Please contact John Bernthal at 472-5496. This program is offered jointly with the University of Nebraska at Kearney. For additional program information, please contact Dr. Joan Lewis at UNK at (308) 865-8613.

Information Technology–Undergraduate. (Grades K-12) 17 hours: TEAC 323, 451L, 444 3 hrs each; TEAC 397L 1 hr; CSCE 101, 150 3 hrs each; CSCE 101L 1 hr.

Severe/Multiple Disabilities–Autism. (Grades P-12) 23 hours: Teaching Certificate in Special Education – Mild/Moderate Disabilities or equivalent; SPED 480/880, 809, 881, 882, 897P 3 hrs each, 810, 896P, 980, 981 2 hrs each.

Vocational Special Needs. (Grades 7-12) 15 hours: TEAC 434 3 hrs; SPED 436 3 hrs each; 6 hrs from SPED 201, 400.

Non-Endorsement Programs

Non-teaching degree programs in administrative resource management, technical education and audiology are available.

Audiology Option

This option is intended for undergraduate students who wish to major in the area of Communication Disorders with an emphasis in audiology and who ultimately expect to enter graduate school and obtain a masters degree in audiology. It is assumed that these students will NOT wish to be certified to be in the classroom.

It is highly recommended that students pursue the bachelor of science in education: Non-Teaching Endorsement Program (BSEd). The following curriculum is based upon the requirements for that degree.

In addition to the education general requirements, students must complete the following:

– SLPA 101, 150, 250, 251, 271 (3 hrs ea), 397A (1 hr), 455, 456 (4 hrs ea), 421, 472 (3 hrs ea);

– PSYC 463, 465 (3 hrs ea)

– One speech disorders course (SLPA 464 recommended) (3 hrs)

– One language disorders course (SLPA 461 recommended) (3 hrs)

NOTE: Students in audiology need the following specific courses that also fulfill general education requirements: BIOS 101/101L, 213/213L; MATH 102, 104 or 106; PHYS 141; PSYC 181.

DEGREES IN HUMAN SCIENCES -Child, Youth and Family Studies

The College offers programs leading to a bachelor of science in education and human sciences in the following areas:

Inclusive Early Childhood Education:
Birth to Grade 3
Child Development/Early Childhood Education*
Family and Consumer Sciences Education*
Child, Youth and Family Studies and Journalism and Mass Communications*
Family Science*

*Available at UNO.

DEGREES IN HUMAN SCIENCES -Nutritional Science and Dietetics

The College offers programs leading to a bachelor of science in education and human sciences in the following areas:

Athletic Training
Culinary Science (Culinology®)
Dietetics
Dietetics/Journalism and Mass Communications
Nutrition, Exercise and Health Science
Nutrition Science
Hospitality, Restaurant and Tourism Management

DEGREES IN HUMAN SCIENCES -Textiles, Clothing and Design

The College offers programs leading to a bachelor of science in education and human sciences in the following areas:

Merchandising*
Textile and Apparel Design
Textile Science**
Textiles, Clothing and Design/Journalism and Mass Communications

* Minor in marketing from College of Business Administration

** Minor in chemistry

These undergraduate programs provide students with an educational background for positions in a variety of government, business, community service, health care, and educational employment settings.

Dual Degrees from College of Education and Human Sciences and Other UNL College (Requires Dual Matriculation)

Students in the College of Education and Human Sciences may earn a bachelor of science degree from the College of Education and Human Sciences and a bachelor of science degree from another UNL college. Students must complete the degree requirements for both colleges and a minimum of 30 credit hours beyond their primary college.

Dual Options Within and Among Departments of the College of Education and Human Sciences

A student in the College of Education and Human Sciences may complete two or more areas of study within the College. Completion of the areas of study will be listed on the transcript. Students must complete the degree requirements for each area of study.

ADD--STUDENT CLASSIFICATION FOR STUDENTS PURSUING TEACHER EDUCATION (CONTENT BOX HEADING):

Pre-Education

All newly admitted students who are pursuing a teacher preparation program, except those in non-teaching majors, are classified as pre-education until admitted to a Teacher Education Program.

Admission to a Teacher Education Program (TEP)

Admission to the College of Education and Human Sciences does not guarantee admission to a teacher education program. Admission to the advanced phases of teacher education is selective and, in some endorsements, highly competitive. Selection to a TEP is based upon the following criteria:

1. Elementary education students must earn a minimum of 30 credit hours of college credit; secondary education students must earn a minimum of 42 credit hours of college credit.

2. Completion and submission of the Teacher Education Program Approval Form.

3. Completion of TEAC 331 or 430 or 431 or 434 or 437 or 496 (3 hrs) or approved transfer course, and EDPS 250 or 251 with a 2.5 cumulative average in the two classes, and no grade lower than C.

4. Documentation of proficiency in reading, writing, and mathematics through successful completion of a basic skills examination that meets the Nebraska Department of Education competency requirement.

5. Completion of one course in communication studies selected from COMM 109, 205, 209, 210, or 286, or approved substitute.

6. Faculty recommendations.

7. Completion of a personal and professional fitness self-disclosure form as well as the completion of a formal criminal history review. (See Felony and Misdemeanor Convictions above.)

8. Specific programs may have particular learning outcomes that students must address as part of the application process.

Post-baccalaureate Students Seeking Initial Teaching Certification

Students who have received a bachelors degree or higher and desire to obtain an initial teaching certificate may do so by pursuing a non-degree post-baccalaureate initial certification program with or without a masters degree. They must apply to the Graduate College for admission to the University of Nebraska–Lincoln and apply to a Teacher Education Program (TEP) for admission to the initial teaching certification program. Students are also required to apply for admission to a degree program if they desire to pursue a masters degree with their certification program. All students seeking initial certification must meet with the post baccalaureate assistant academic adviser. Those seeking a masters degree will also meet with a faculty adviser. Post-baccalaureate students interested in completing a teacher education program should refer to this bulletin as to policies and regulations for program completion. For specific guidelines, see the Student Services Center.

Admission to Student Teaching

All students who are candidates for an appropriately endorsed Nebraska Teacher’s Certificate are required to student teach. Students who plan to student teach in the fall semester must complete the student teaching application form and submit it by the preceding March 1 to the Director of Field Experiences in 104 Henzlik Hall; students planning to student teach in the spring semester must apply by the preceding October 1. The basic program for student teaching provides for a full-day experience on a semester basis. Students enrolled in an elementary education dual major will complete requirements for student teaching in both majors. Admission to student teaching requires the following:

1. Matriculation in a teacher education program in the College of Education and Human Sciences, the Graduate College, or dual matriculation in the College of Education and Human Sciences and another college.

2. Admission to a teacher education program.

3. Senior standing (89 hours or more) with a minimum cumulative GPA of 2.5.

4. Minimum average of 2.5 in each endorsement area with no grade below C.

5. A minimum grade point average of 2.5 in pre-professional and professional education courses and no grade below C in pre-professional education courses and no grade below a C+ in professional education courses.

6. Completion of a criminal history check that will be conducted by an independent party (fee required).

Student Teaching Registration Requirements

Undergraduate students are required to take 12 credit hours of student teaching or student teaching related course work during a semester-long student teaching experience. Those individuals who are completing two field endorsements will student teach for 20 weeks and will register for a total of 14 credit hours. Graduate students completing a semester-long student teaching experience will register for 6 graduate hours for either a 16 or 20 week experience.

All pre-professional education, professional education, and subject area endorsement course work must be completed prior to student teaching. Students will not be allowed to student teach with anything more than 6 credit hours of general education requirements remaining for their degree or in their program. No additional course work can be taken during the student teaching semester.

Student Teaching Placement

The Office of Field Experiences is responsible for the placement of student teachers. Several factors are considered in determining the district and school to which an individual is assigned. The availability of a cooperating teacher and supervisor who meet the requirements established by the Nebraska Department of Education and the University of Nebraska–Lincoln are among those factors. Opportunities to student teach out-of-state are limited and those placements are becoming increasingly difficult. All requests to student teach outside of the immediate Lincoln area must be individually reviewed and approved by the Director of Field Experiences.

Removal from Student Teaching

Students participating in practicum or student teaching assignments may be removed from their assigned schools if their conduct suggests a lack of professional commitment and presents a negative influence on the well-being or learning of the students in the schools. Specific guidelines that all student teachers are to follow can be found in The Student Teaching Experience: A Handbook for the University of Nebraska–Lincoln. If such a problem occurs, the student in question will be removed by the Director of Field Experiences at the request of the cooperating teacher, building principal, and the College supervisor.

In such cases, a written report stating the problem and efforts to correct the situation will be forwarded to the Director of Field Experiences in the College Student Services Center.

Any student removed from a practicum or student teaching assignment may appeal that decision by submitting a written request to the College Appeals Committee within 30 days of the removal. The Appeals Committee will schedule a meeting, request pertinent information from the Director of Field Experiences, and notify the student several days in advance of the scheduled appeal meeting. Students are advised of their right to seek legal advice and may personally attend the Appeals Committee meeting.

The Committee’s decision will be forwarded in writing to the student, to the Director of Field Experiences, and to the Dean of the College.

Praxis II

All students completing a program leading to a teaching certificate with an endorsement in elementary grades (Grades K-6) will be required to take the EECIA-00011 version of Praxis II before graduation. Test completion will be documented through official test score results.

Students will not be allowed to graduate unless this test is completed.

Application for a Nebraska Teaching Certificate

To actively engage in the teaching profession, a candidate must fulfill both the College degree requirements and the professional certification requirements of the State of Nebraska. Undergraduate students apply for the teaching certificate online at www.nde.state.ne.us/tcert and apply for the baccalaureate degree in 109 Canfield Administration Building. Post-baccalaureate students completing teacher certification also apply online.

To be eligible for a recommendation for certification, a candidate must meet the following requirements:

1. Earn one or more degrees from the College of Education and Human Sciences or another accredited institution approved by the College of Education and Human Sciences with a minimum 2.5 grade point average.

2. Complete the teacher education general education requirements listed for elementary, middle grades or secondary education.

3. Complete professional education requirements according to established standards.

4. Complete endorsement(s) according to established standards.

5. Successfully complete a required period of student teaching.

6. Complete application for the degree and certificate.

Graduation Without Certification

In rare cases, permission may be granted for a student to graduate without a recommendation for certification. This provision is for the student who does not qualify for or is removed from student teaching. However, there are times when because of illness or other extreme situations, a student will decide not to complete all professional requirements. In this situation, the student should contact his or her adviser, then complete a formal request to the College’s Certification Officer to be allowed to graduate without completing all certification requirements. If permission is granted, the student is expected to complete all professional requirements except student teaching. This includes a passing grade in all methods courses. If a student fails to complete at least one half of the student teaching assignment, the individual will be required to complete a culminating project not to exceed 6 credit hours.

Any student who graduates without a recommendation for certification will not be recommended for teacher certification in any state. In addition, the student will not be eligible for graduation with honors. If, at some future time, the student wishes to complete certification requirements, (s)he must first appeal for readmission to a teacher education program. At least one semester must pass after graduation before the appeal can be made. If the appeal is granted, the student will be treated as a readmitted student and will complete all requirements in effect at the time of reentry, including passing grades in all methods courses.

GRADUATE STUDENT INFORMATION (Content Box Heading):

EDUCATION

Majors in education leading to the indicated graduate degrees are:

Education (Doctoral)

Administration, Curriculum, and Instruction–EdD, PhD
Community and Human Resources–EdD, PhD
Psychological and Cultural Studies–PhD
Education (Masters and Specialists)
Curriculum and Instruction–MA, MEd, MST, EdS
Educational Administration–MA, MEd
Educational Psychology–MA, EdS
Health and Human Performance–MEd, MPE, EdS
Special Education–MA, MEd
Special Education and Communication Disorders–EdS
Speech-Language Pathology and Audiology–MS, EdS

In addition to the above degrees, work leading to a Certificate of Specialization in Administration and Supervision is offered in the Department of Educational Administration. Courses of study provide for specialization in administration and supervision of the central school office, secondary and elementary schools, curriculum, instruction, community college, media centers, special education, and the area of speech pathology and audiology.

For information on graduate work in education, consult the Graduate Bulletin and the Web site, tc.unl.edu/grad.

Seniors in this University who have obtained in advance the approval of the Dean of Graduate Studies may receive up to 12 hours credit for graduate courses taken in addition to the courses necessary to complete their undergraduate work, provided that such credits are earned within the calendar year prior to receipt of the bachelors degree. (For procedures, inquire at the Office of Graduate Studies, 301 Canfield Administration Building.) Course work taken prior to receipt of the bachelors may not always be accepted for transfer to other institutions as graduate work.

Seniors at UNL needing not more than 9 hours of undergraduate credit to complete the bachelors degree and wishing to register for graduate credit may be granted admission to Graduate Studies on a provisional basis subject to receiving their baccalaureate within one calendar year. They must file applications to Graduate Studies and, if admitted, their graduate registrations may count as residence in the Graduate College.

Endorsements for Graduate Students

Students graduating from the College of Education and Human Sciences or working towards certification must complete one field endorsement or two subject endorsements. Those that require a second endorsement are noted with an (*) asterisk.

Assessment Leadership. (Grades P-12) 18 hours: TEAC 890, 893 3 hrs each; 991, 993 6 hrs each.

Behaviorally Disordered. (Grades P-6) 40 hours: SPED 800 (prereq), 802, 803, 804, 841, 896, 907B, 908, 942 3 hrs each, 897B 6 hrs, 897Z 1 hr; EDPS 850 3 hrs; EDUC 800 or SLPA 854 3 hrs.

Behaviorally Disordered. (Grades P-12) 40 hours: SPED 800 (prereq), 802, 803, 804, 841, 896, 907B, 908, 942 3 hrs each, 897B 6 hrs, 497Z 1 hr. Supporting courses 6 hrs: EDPS 850 or EDPS 851 or EDPS 869. Guided elective 3 hrs.

Counselor, School Guidance. (Grades K-6) 47 hours: (Candidates must be admitted into a masters degree program in educational psychology or, in the case of an already existing graduate degree, must be reviewed and meet the existing admission requirements. The candidate must have a valid teaching or special services certificate and two years teaching experience.) EDPS 850, 853, 859, 869 or 985, 965A, 984, 800, 866, 868, 870, 964, 974, 975 3 hrs each, 997A, 997B 4 hrs each. NOTE: To add a 7-12 endorsement to a K-6 endorsement, a student must add EDPS 851 and an additional 997B at the 7-12 grade level.

Counselor, School Guidance. (Grades 7-12) 47 hours: (Candidates must be admitted into a masters degree program in educational psychology or, in the case of an already existing graduate degree, must be reviewed and meet the existing admission requirements. The candidate must have a valid teaching or special services certificate and two years of teaching experience.) EDPS 851, 853, 859, 869 or 985, 965A, 984, 800, 866, 868, 870, 964, 974, 975 3 hrs each, 997A, 997B 4 hrs. NOTE: To add a K-6 endorsement to a 7-12 endorsement, a student must add EDPS 850 and an additional 997B at the K-6 grade level.

Deaf or Hard of Hearing/Subject. (Grades P-12) 30-45 hours: Candidates must hold an initial certificate in Elementary Education, Middle Grades, or Special Education-Mild/Moderate Disabilities. Students without a Special Education certificate are required to take a four-course series in Special Education. Proficiency requirements: Demonstrated proficiency in American Sign Language; successful completion of SLPA 202 or minimum score on Sign Communication Proficiency Interview or EIPA or other approved measure. Prerequisites: SPED 400/800, 302/802, 304/803, 313/804 3 hrs each; SLPA 251 3 hrs (15 hours). SPED 472/872, 873, 874, 875, 897D, 960 3 hrs each; and either SPED 896D 3 hrs or 896D 2 hrs and 896E 1 hr; SLPA 850, 884, 956 3 hrs each (30 hours).

Early Childhood Education. (Grade P-3) 30-31 hours: Prerequisites: Must hold a valid elementary education teaching endorsement or permission. Consult the College of Education and Human Sciences for advising. CYAF 961 or SPED 960 3 hrs; CYAF 897A, 972 3 hrs each; CYAF 874 or 876 3 hrs; CYAF 877 or ALEC 802 or 807 3 hrs; CYAF 973 or PSYC 889 3 hrs; CYAF 865 or 896 3 hrs; CYAF 970 or 971 or SPED 860 3 hrs; CYAF 974 or EDPS 850 or TEAC 817 3 hrs. Select one course from the following: SPED 804, 860, 862, 863, or 960 3 hrs; or SLPA 862A and 862J 2 hrs ea.

Early Childhood Special Education. (Birth thru grade 3) minimum 27 graduate hours: Prerequisites: Teaching Certificate Endorsement in Elementary Education (K-6) or Early Childhood Education (P-3) or Unified Early Childhood (Birth thru grade 3); SPED 800, 802, 804, 815 12 hrs. Required completion of (or equivalent): CYAF 970, SPED 890 (or SLPA 251), SPED 860, 861, 862, 863, 882, 960 and 897Q 3 hrs each.

Information Technology (graduate). (Grades K-12) 19 hours: TEAC 851L, 860, 882A, 882B, 882D, 882J 3 hrs each; TEAC 894L 1 hr.

Library Media Specialist. (Grades K-12): This program is offered jointly with the University of Nebraska at Omaha. Please contact Dr. Becky Pasco at UNO at (402) 554-2119 for advising.

Pre-School Disabilities. (Birth thru K) minimum 30 hours: Prerequisites: Teaching Certificate Endorsement for Special Education or Speech Pathology; SPED 800, 802, 804 9 hrs. Required completion of (or equivalent): SPED 860, 861, 862, 863, 882, 960, 890 or (SLPA 251) 3 hrs each and SPED 897Q 6 hrs and CYAF 970 3 hrs. NOTE: There is a masters degree program available that includes an initial teaching certificate with this endorsement focus for students with undergraduate degrees outside education. Contact Special Education and Communication Disorders at 472-2141.

Reading Specialist. (Grades P-12) 30 hours: Candidates must hold a valid teaching credential and have at least one year teaching experience. TEAC 802, 811, 838, 839, 841, TEAC/SPED 886, 886B 3 hrs each; TEAC 893 (Professional Development for Literacy Coaches version only) 3 hrs; select 6-8 hrs from the following: ENGL 957B 6 hrs, or TEAC 817, 854, 890, 990, 921, 950, 951, 952, 953 3 hrs; or EDPS 989 3 hrs; or SPED 805 3 hrs paralleled with 805A 1 hr or TEAC/SPED 806 3 hrs paralleled with 806A 1 hr; SPED 815 3 hrs paralleled with 815A 1 hr.

Visual Impairment. (Grades P-12) 33 hours: Prerequisites: Admittance into VI program, hold or earn concurrently subject or field endorsement. If your endorsement is not in special education, the following core classes must be completed: SPED 800 and 803 3 hrs each. Requirements: SPED 846, 847, 849, 851, 852, 853, 882 3 hrs each; 852A 1 hr; 852B 2 hrs; 897V 3 hrs; guided electives in special education 6 hrs selected with adviser; braille proficiency exam.

Special Services Endorsements

School Psychologist. (Grades P-12) 76-85 hours: Candidate must hold a masters degree in educational or clinical psychology, education, or a related field. This is an educational specialist degree program. EDPS 859 or equivalent, 870 or equivalent, 868 or equivalent, 850 or 851, 854, 860, 863, 867, 869, 949, 952, 954 3 hrs each; 950, 951 4 hrs each; 996A 6 hrs; 958A or 959 7 hrs; 957A, 958B 8 hrs each; EDUC 800 or equivalent and 900B 3 hrs each; SPED 800, 802 or equivalent 3 hrs each.

School Transition Specialist. (Grades 7-12) 18 hours: SPED 800 or 834, 807, 808, 835 or 836, 837 or 896, 908 3 hrs each.

Administrative and Supervisory Standard Certificates

Standard Certificate Requirements

The completion of a masters degree or 36 hours of a specialist program and the fulfillment of the State Department of Education Guidelines for Certification are required to obtain the Standard Administrative and Supervisory Certificate. A minimum of 9 hours must be taken at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln. All individuals seeking certification for an administrative certificate must hold or qualify for a Standard Teaching Certificate. The following endorsements on the certificate are available through the College of Education and Human Sciences. Candidates must have on file a program approved by the Department of Educational Administration.

Assessment Leadership. Refer to Graduate Level Teaching Endorsements for list of courses.

Curriculum Supervisor. (Grades P-12) 36 hours: EDAD 811, 830, 851, 903, 948; TEAC 800, 801, 888 3 hrs; Select one course from EDAD 833, 837, or 852 3 hrs; Select two courses from TEAC 846A, 846B, 848, 944, 944A, 944B, 944D, 944E 3 hrs each (6 total); Select one course from TEAC 830, 831, 832, 834, 840, 840A, 840B, 840D, 861, 902 3 hrs. NOTE: Students must be admitted to both educational administration and curriculum and instruction and meet exit requirements for both departments.

Principal, Elementary. (Grades P-8) 36 hours: a) EDAD 811, 830, 833, 837, 851, 852, 903, 981 3 hrs each; b) TEAC 801 or 848 or 944 3 hrs, and TEAC 800 or 946 or 948 3 hrs; c) approved College of Education and Human Sciences course other than educational administration or curriculum and instruction 3 hrs; d) approved elective 3 hrs. Must complete satisfactorily a Professional Portfolio. Must either hold teaching endorsement valid for elementary school grades or earn additional 9 hrs pertaining to elementary school level. NOTE: Applicant must have met Nebraska Department of Education requirements for basic skills, human relations training, special education, and two years of teaching experience.

Principal, Middle Grades. (Grades 4-9) 36 hours: a) EDAD 811, 830, 833, 837, 851, 852, 903, 981 3 hrs each; b) TEAC 801 or 848 or 944 3 hrs, and TEAC 800 or 946 or 948 3 hrs; c) approved College of Education and Human Sciences course other than educational administration or curriculum and instruction 3 hrs; d) approved elective 3 hrs. Must complete satisfactorily a Professional Portfolio. Must either hold teaching endorsement valid for middle school grades or earn additional 9 hrs pertaining to middle school level. NOTE: Applicant must have met Nebraska Department of Education requirements for basic skills, human relations training, special education, and two years of teaching experience.

Principal, Secondary. (Grades 7-12) 36 hours: a) EDAD 811, 830, 833, 837, 851, 852, 903, 981 3 hrs each; b) TEAC 801 or 848 or 944 3 hrs, and TEAC 800 or 946 or 948 3 hrs; c) approved College of Education and Human Sciences course other than educational administration or curriculum and instruction 3 hrs; d) approved elective 3 hrs. Must complete satisfactorily a Professional Portfolio. Must either hold teaching endorsement valid for secondary school grades or earn additional 9 hrs pertaining to secondary school level. NOTE: Applicant must have met Nebraska Department of Education requirements for basic skills, human relations training, special education, and two years of teaching experience.

Supervisor of Special Education Programs. (Grades P-12) 36 hours: EDAD 800 6 hrs, 811, 981 3 hrs each, EDAD approved electives 6 hrs; EDAD/SPED 857, 858 3 hrs each; 12 hrs approved graduate courses in special education, 6 of which are outside of person’s endorsement area, taken within past 6 years. NOTE: Special education endorsement required and 2 years of successful teaching experience.

Administrative and Supervisory Professional Certificates

The completion of the specialist program and the fulfillment of the State Department of Education Guidelines for Certification are required to obtain the Professional Administrative and Supervisory Certificate. All individuals seeking certification for an administrative certificate must hold or qualify for a Standard Teaching Certificate. The following endorsements on this certificate are available through the College of Education and Human Sciences. Advisement for all specialist programs is through the Department of Educational Administration.

Superintendent. (Grades P-12): 66 hours: Prereq: Must have a valid regular teaching certificate or an administrative and supervisory certificate (principal, curriculum supervisor) and at least two years of teaching experience. a) Educational Administration 42 hrs: EDAD 801, 811, 830, 833, 835, 837, 851, 852, 901, 903, 904, 905, 981, 998 3 hrs each; b) Teaching Learning and Teacher Education 6 hrs: either TEAC 801 or 848 or 944, and either Teach 800 or 946 or 948; c) supporting area other than Educational Administration or Teaching Learning and Teacher Education 3 hrs; d) approved electives 15 hrs.

Courses of Instruction in Education

Prerequisites. In addition to the specific prerequisites of each course, the general prerequisite for all courses in the 400 series consists of not fewer than 12 hours of undergraduate credit in education, including 3 hours of educational psychology and 3 hours of educational methods.

Workshop Seminars in Education

490/890, 493/893, 990 or 993. Workshop Seminar (1-12 cr) Opportunity to learn and to put into practice the principles and techniques of developing instructional aids such as courses of study, resource units, handbooks, and motion picture guides.

Graduate Studies in Human Sciences

Study beyond the undergraduate level may be required for those seeking technical or professional positions. The College offers opportunities to those who want to earn advanced degrees in the Graduate College.

Graduate education that develops professional competence of students combined with a strong sense of social responsibility continues to be the aim of the graduate faculty.

Graduate study leading to the masters degree is offered in the departments of child, youth and family studies; nutrition and health science; and textiles, clothing and design.

For the doctor of philosophy degree, courses of study in human sciences leading to the doctoral degree are offered through the College of Education and Human Sciences. Specific programs are designed to meet the needs and interests of individual students as directed by the supervisory committee.

For students interested primarily in a career in nutrition research, the interdepartmental area of nutrition provides work leading to the degrees of master of science and doctor of philosophy. For further information on these advanced degree programs see the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

Acceptance of Senior Credits

Seniors who have advanced approval of the Dean of Graduate Studies may receive up to 12 hours credit for graduate courses taken in addition to the courses necessary to complete their undergraduate course work, provided that such credits are earned within the calendar year prior to receipt of the baccalaureate.

Seniors needing not more than 9 hours of undergraduate credit to complete the bachelors degree, and wishing to register for graduate credit, may be granted provisional admission to the Graduate College subject to receiving their baccalaureate within one calendar year.

MINORS & AREAS OF SPECIALIZATIONS OFFERED (Content Box Heading):

African American Studies Minor (For Students in Teacher Preparation)

Students in teacher preparation may obtain a minor in African American Studies by satisfactorily completing a minimum of 18 credit hours of work as prescribed by the adviser for the African American Studies minor in the College of Arts and Sciences. Students must file a C-D-M-A (College-Degree-Major-Adviser) form with the College Student Services Center prior to filing for graduation.

Coaching Minor

Students in the College of Education and Human Sciences who are not seeking teaching certification may obtain a coaching minor by satisfactorily completing the coaching supplemental endorsement. Students must file C-D-M-A (College-Degree-Major-Adviser) form with the College Student Services Center prior to filing for graduation.

Education Minor (For Non-Teacher Education Students)

18 hours: TEAC 331 or equivalent and 330 3 hrs ea; EDPS 250 or 251 and 362 or 457 3 hrs ea; SPED 201 3 hrs; CYAF 380 or approved elective from CYAF, EDPS, NUTR, SPED, or TEAC 3 hrs.

Area of Specialization in Education

Multicultural Education. It is possible to obtain multicultural education specialization along with a teaching endorsement. Basic requirements are as follows:

TEAC 330, 433, 434, 436, and approved elective; 12 hrs selected from ANTH 212, 242, 351, 482; ENGL 220, 244B, 245B, 245D, 245J, 445; HIST 357; POLS 238; SOCI 217, 218, 481; COMM 211 or 380. An approved field/practicum experience outside of normal class assignments (3 cr); student teaching in a multicultural setting; and demonstrated language proficiency through course work or testing in one of the following languages: Spanish, Vietnamese, Sioux (Lakota/Dakota), Portuguese, Chinese, Japanese, German, Czech, Russian or French.

HUMAN SCIENCES -International Studies Minor

The College of Education and Human Sciences offers a minor in international studies to students in the human sciences.

Human Sciences International Minor

18 Hour International Studies Minor

HUMS 465 International Perspectives of Human Resources and Family Sciences (3 cr)

TXCD 123 Clothing and Human Behavior or NUTR 253 Cultural Aspects of Food and Nutrition or CYAF 495 Special Topics in Family and Cultural Diversity (Diversity) (3 cr)

Maximum of 9 credits from one department or program—Applicable courses from College of Arts and Sciences International Studies Thematic Specialization List (1. Power and Production; 2. International Relations; 3. Cultural Encounters) (See page 187.)

Minimum of 3 hours of preapproved International or Cultural Experience (HUMS 490)

Minimum of 6 credits at or above the 300 level

12 Hour International Studies Minor

HUMS 465 International Perspectives of Human Resources and Family Sciences (3 cr)

TXCD 123 Clothing and Human Behavior or NUTR 253 Cultural Aspects of Food and Nutrition or CYAF 495 Special Topics in Family and Cultural Diversity (Diversity) (3 cr)

Applicable courses from College of Arts and Sciences International Studies Thematic Specialization List (1. Power and Production; 2. International Relations; 3. Cultural Encounters) (See page 187.)

Minimum of 9 credits at or above the 300 level

HUMAN SCIENCES - Hospitality Management Minor

The hospitality management minor is for students in CASNR and CEHS Human Sciences (Child, Youth and Family; Nutrition and Health Science; Textile, Clothing and Design) Departments.

Required 9 hours:

HRTM 171 Intro to Hospitality, Restaurant & Tourism Management (3 hrs)

HRTM 285 Intro to Lodging (3 hrs)

HRTM 289 Intro to the Event Industry (3 hrs)

Select 9 hours from:

HRTM 280 Intro to Tourism (3 hrs)

HRTM 373 Catering (3 hrs)

HRTM 374 Guest Services Management (3 hrs)

HRTM 474 Food & Beverage Management (3 hrs)

HRTM 478 Tourism Resources & Development (3 hrs)

HRTM 479 Hospitality Industry Perspectives (3 hrs)

HRTM 485 Advanced Lodging Operations (3 hrs)

HRTM 489 Convention & Meeting Planning (3 hrs)

NUTR 471 Vines, Wine & You (3 hrs)

HUMAN SCIENCES - Minors in Other Colleges

An undergraduate student with a major in human sciences who wants a minor in another college should consult with their College of Education and Human Sciences adviser and prepare the list of approved courses desired for the minor.

Arts and Sciences. Prepare the list of courses required for either Plan A or Plan B in the chosen minor as indicated in the College of Arts and Sciences section of this bulletin. Plan A indicates a single minor; Plan B indicates two minors with fewer hours in each subject than the number required for a single minor.

Complete a Change of Major/Adviser (CDMA) form in the Student Services Center, 105 Henzlik.

General Agriculture. Students in human sciences may obtain a minor in general agriculture by satisfactorily completing a minimum of 18 credit hours of work in courses offered by the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources (CASNR).

More specific details about general areas and courses are given in the CASNR section of this bulletin. The specific minor program must be prepared in consultation with the CASNR Dean’s office, room 103 Agriculture Hall.

HUMS 465 International Perspectives of Human Resources and Family Sciences (3 cr)

TXCD 123 Clothing and Human Behavior or NUTR 253 Cultural Aspects of Food and Nutrition or CYAF 495 Special Topics in Family and Cultural Diversity (Diversity) (3 cr)

Maximum of 9 credits from one department or program—Applicable courses from College of Arts and Sciences International Studies Thematic Specialization List (1. Power and Production; 2. International Relations; 3. Cultural Encounters) (See page 187.)

Minimum of 3 hours of preapproved International or Cultural Experience (HUMS 490)

Minimum of 6 credits at or above the 300 level

College of Engineering

David H. Allen, Ph.D., P.E., Dean and Professor of Engineering Mechanics

Namas Chandra, Ph.D., Associate Dean for Research and Graduate Programs and Professor of Engineering Mechanics

Raymond K. Moore, Ph.D., P.E., Associate Dean for Undergraduate Education and Professor of Civil Engineering

Lance C. Pérez, Ph.D., Associate Dean and Associate Professor of Electrical Engineering

John S. Thorpe, M.S., Associate Dean for Undergraduate Programs (Omaha Campus)

About the College

Role and Mission

The College of Engineering enthusiastically embraces its unique role as the singular intellectual and cultural resource for engineering instruction, research, and outreach within the state. It provides the people of Nebraska with comprehensive engineering academic programs to fulfill their highest aspirations and ambitions.

The missions of the College of Engineering at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln are:

to deliver relevant and challenging educational programs to attract an outstanding diverse student body, prepare graduates for rewarding careers in their chosen professions, and encourage graduates to extend their level of knowledge through lifelong learning;
to conduct leading edge research advances engineering science, and stimulate the intellectual development and creativity of both students and faculty; and,
to extend exemplary engineering service and transfer knowledge that contributes to the well-being and betterment of society.

Administrative Structure

The College of Engineering is located on three campuses (Lincoln city campus, Lincoln East Campus, and Omaha), and has two Dean’s Offices, 114 Othmer Hall in Lincoln and 101 Peter Kiewit Institute in Omaha. The College is subdivided into units, each under the leadership of a chairperson, department head, or director.

ADMISSION

College Admission

College Entrance Requirements

Students must have high school credit for (one unit is equal to one high school year):

1. 4 units of mathematics: 2 of algebra, 1 of geometry, 1 of precalculus and trigonometry.

2. 4 units of English.

3. 3 units of natural science that must include 1 unit of physics and 1 unit of chemistry (chemistry requirement waived for students in construction management).

4. 2 units of a single foreign language.

5. 3 units of social studies.

6. Students having a composite ACT score of 28 or greater (or equivalent SAT score) will be admitted to the College of Engineering even if they lack any one of the following: trigonometry, chemistry, or physics.

7. Students having an ACT score of 19 or less in English (or equivalent SAT score) must take ENGL 150 or ENGL 151.

A total of 16 units is required for admission.

Students must have an ACT (enhanced) score of 24 or greater (or equivalent SAT). Students who lack entrance requirements may be admitted based on ACT scores, high school rank and credits, or may be admitted to Pre-Engineering status in the Division of General Studies. Pre-engineering students are advised within the College of Engineering.

Students who lack entrance units may complete precollege training by Independent Study through the UNL Extended Education, in Summer Sessions courses, or as a part of their first or second semester course loads while in the Division of General Studies or other Colleges at UNL.

Students should consult their adviser, their department chair, or the Office of the Dean if they have questions on current policies.

Other Admission Requirements

Students who transfer from other colleges or universities must meet the freshman entrance requirements and have a minimum cumulative grade point average of 2.5 for Nebraska residents. Nonresidents must have a minimum cumulative grade point average of 3.0 unless they are transferring from an accredited engineering program, in which case a 2.5 grade point average is acceptable. Students who do not meet this requirement must enroll in another college at the University and achieve a minimum 2.5 cumulative grade point average in the first 12 hours or more of course work taken at UNL. They may then be considered for admission to the College of Engineering.

The College of Engineering accepts courses for transfer for which a C grade or above was received. Grades of D from the University of Nebraska at Kearney, Lincoln, or Omaha may be transferred to fulfill requirements, however, students are strongly encouraged to repeat those courses. All transfer students must adopt the curricular requirements of the undergraduate bulletin current at the time of transfer–not that in use when they entered UNL.

ADVISING

Academic Advising

Advisers assigned to students are located in the departments.

Student Responsibility

Application for the Diploma

Students must file an application of candidacy for the diploma at the Office of Registration and Records.

Failure to meet these stipulations may postpone graduation.

ACADEMIC PROGRAMS & POLICIES

Honors Program

Honor Societies

These recognize students who excel in scholarship and give promise of being leaders in professional areas. They are branches of national societies and are generally open upon invitation to juniors and seniors: Alpha Epsilon (agricultural engineering), Alpha Pi Mu (industrial engineering), Chi Epsilon (civil engineering, both campuses), Eta Kappa Nu (electrical engineering), Pi Tau Sigma (mechanical engineering), Sigma Lambda Chi (construction management), Sigma Xi (scientific, all colleges), Tau Alpha Pi (engineering technology, Omaha campus), and Tau Beta Pi (all engineering).

Student Recognition

Graduation with Distinction

Students with outstanding scholastic records may obtain the special honor of graduation With Distinction, With High Distinction, or With Highest Distinction upon the recommendation of the faculty of the College. Check with your major department for specific requirements of each degree.

Student Standing/Classification

After being admitted, students wishing to pursue degree programs in the College of Engineering will be classified as described below.

1. Pre-Engineering and Pre-Construction Management Students. New students are accepted on a provisional basis to establish their academic credentials and to firm up their career objectives. These students may take freshman- and sophomore-level courses in the College of Engineering.
Readmitted students will be initially classified as pre-engineering, and pre-construction management students when their accumulative GPA for a total of at least 12 credit hours and most recent semester or term GPA at the University of Nebraska is at least 2.5. Students may be reclassified to restricted status if their accumulative GPA falls below 2.4.

2. Regular Engineering Students. Students who have completed 43 credit hours applicable to their engineering degree may apply for formal admission to that degree program. Those exceeding 61 credit hours must receive formal admission to an engineering degree program if they are to continue to take engineering courses taught in the College of Engineering and/or be identified with the College. Transfer students must have at least 12 credit hours of course work from the University of Nebraska on record before an application will be considered.
Students may apply to an engineering degree program during the first four weeks of the fall or spring semester, which must include a complete record of course work. Students may select a first and second choice of a degree program on a single application and may submit no more than two applications and only in successive semesters. Applications are judged on a competitive academic performance basis. The student should contact the department of his/her choice to determine if there are specific requirements. Admission of non-Nebraska residents may be limited to ten percent of the total.
Regular engineering students may be re-classified to a restricted status if their accumulative GPA falls below 2.4. Students may not graduate with a degree in engineering while in the restricted category.

3. Regular Construction Management Students. Pre-construction management students must apply and be admitted to the construction management degree program after completing 30 credit hours of required course work. Students failing to be admitted to the construction management degree program prior to earning 65 credit hours may be dropped as construction management degree candidates.
Regular construction management students who fail to maintain a minimum cumulative GPA of 2.4 may be reclassified as restricted students.

4. Restricted Students. These students are ones who are in the Division of General Studies or other colleges, or those who have failed to maintain the academic standards or general policies of the College of Engineering. Restricted students are substantially limited in the choice of courses that may be taken in the College. Restricted students may:

Retake D and F grades in College of Engineering courses on a space available basis with permission.
Repeat a maximum of three courses in the College any one of which may be taken only twice.
Enroll in CNST 112 and CNST 131.
Enroll in ENGM 220 and ENGM 324.
Enroll in AGEN 112, BSEN 112, CIVE 112, IMSE 050, MECH 130 on a space available basis. Students admitted to the College of Engineering have priority in these two courses.
Not enroll in ELEC 121, or ELEC 122 without approval from the respective departments.
Enroll in ENGR 010.

General College Policies

These policies are applicable to all students in the College of Engineering:

1. Student priority for entrance into classes for which demand exceeds available class space will be based on accumulative GPA. This priority will be applied at the end of early registration (when applicable).

2. Students may repeat a maximum of three engineering courses. Students may take any one engineering course a maximum of two times.

3. At least 30 of the last 36 credit hours needed for a degree must be registered for and completed at UNL or UNO while identified with the College of Engineering. This means that, practically speaking, the last year of a student’s work must be spent in residence. Credit earned during study abroad may be used toward degree requirements if students participate in prior approved programs and register through UNL (see “Study Abroad and Exchange Programs”).

4. Pass/No Pass courses: Students in the College of Engineering must take ENGR 010, 020 and 400 with the grading option Pass/No Pass. In addition, students may take up to 12 credit hours of courses in the humanities and social sciences on a Pass/No Pass basis. Students in the College of Engineering may not take any other required courses or technical elective courses with the grading option of Pass/No Pass.

5. Credits for “English for Foreign Students who are Non-native Speakers” at UNL and “English as a Second Language” at UNO are not applicable to degree programs in the College of Engineering.

6. Six hours of English composition may be substituted for the written communications requirement in all degree programs.

7. Students who enroll at UNL, UNO, or UNK under the academic year (Fall, Spring, Summer) of this bulletin must fulfill the requirements stated in this UNL bulletin or in any other UNL bulletin which is published while they are enrolled in the College, provided that the bulletin is no more than 10 years old at the time of graduation. A student must, however, meet the graduation requirements from one bulletin only. A student may not choose a portion from one bulletin and the remainder from another bulletin.

Undergraduate Seminars. All freshmen students are required to attend ENGR 010, Freshman Engineering Seminar, a zero credit course. This seminar provides students with a variety of information useful throughout their attendance in the UNL College of Engineering. Sophomore engineering students are required to attend ENGR 020, Sophomore Engineering Seminar, a zero credit course. The Sophomore Engineering Seminar provides information on career planning, interviewing, resumé preparation and coop/internship opportunities.

Design Requirement. All engineering majors require a minimum of 48 credit hours of engineering topics (engineering topics include subjects in the engineering sciences or engineering design). Engineering design is the process of devising a system, component or process to meet desired needs. Engineering design work may be done by individuals; however, team efforts are encouraged where appropriate. Engineering majors are provided an integrated engineering design experience throughout the curriculum. In addition, all engineering programs include a meaningful major design experience that builds upon the fundamental concepts of mathematics, basic sciences, humanities, social sciences, engineering topics, and communication skills.

BULLETIN TO USE

COLLEGE DEGREE REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Grade Appeals

In the event of a dispute involving any college policies or grades, the student should appeal to his/her instructor, adviser, and department chair (in that order). If a satisfactory solution is not achieved, the student may appeal his/her case through the College Academic Appeals Committee on his/her campus.

DEGREES & MAJORS

Engineering

To meet the need for innovative engineers, the College’s programs offer broad education in the physical sciences, social sciences, mathematics, information sciences, and humanities. This education is complemented by study of engineering methods of modeling, analysis, synthesis, and design in students’ areas of specialization. In addition to preparing students for careers in engineering, the College’s bachelors degree programs provide excellent preparation for graduate study in those fields.

Construction Management

This profession is allied with architecture, engineering, and business administration. Construction managers coordinate people, machines, and materials to produce (within the constraints of budget and time) buildings, highways, bridges, dams, and other structures essential to modern society. The College’s construction management program provides a solid technical background, develops business knowledge, and considers ethical issues of the profession.

Undergraduate Programs on the Lincoln Campus

Engineering. The College offers bachelor of science degree programs in each of the following engineering fields: agricultural engineering, architectural engineering, biological systems engineering, chemical engineering, civil engineering, computer engineering, construction engineering, electrical engineering, electronics engineering, industrial engineering, and mechanical engineering. Over 85 percent of all the engineering degrees granted in the United States during the last five years were granted in these fields. Students with interests in specialty fields such as aerospace, environmental, or biomedical engineering should seek advice in the Office of the Dean on how to incorporate such emphases into the above degree programs.

Construction Management. The College offers the bachelor of science degree program in construction management, a program accredited by The American Council for Construction Education.

Double Majors. Students can major in two departments in the college by consulting their advisers (one from each department) and completing all the requirements for the departmental majors.

Undergraduate Programs on the Omaha Campus

Construction Management. The College offers the bachelor of science degree program in construction management, a program accredited by The American Council for Construction Education.

Engineering. The College offers bachelor of science degree programs in architectural engineering, civil engineering, computer engineering, construction engineering, and electronics engineering on the Omaha campus. First- and second-year course work is also offered on the Omaha campus in most other engineering fields through the College’s pre-engineering program.

Fire Protection Technology. An associate degree in fire protection technology is offered through the UNL Extended Education and Outreach. The College of Engineering grants an ASET degree.

GRADUATE STUDENT INFORMATION

Courses supporting several engineering graduate programs are offered both on and off campus. For details, see the University of Nebraska–Lincoln Graduate Studies Bulletin and contact the appropriate department or the Office of the Dean of the College of Engineering.

Seniors in this University who have obtained prior approval of the Dean of Graduate Studies may receive up to 12 hours credit for graduate courses taken in addition to their required undergraduate work. However, these credits must be earned within the calendar year prior to receipt of the bachelors degree. For procedures, inquire at the UNL Graduate Studies Office. Graduate credits earned prior to receipt of the bachelors degree may not always be accepted for transfer to other institutions as graduate work.

MINORS & AREAS OF SPECIALIZATIONS OFFERED

Approved Minors for College of Engineering Students

Policies:

1. A minor will not reduce or alter the existing course or degree requirements for students electing to pursue a minor.

2. A student’s minor program(s) must be organized and approved by an adviser prior to the submission of the senior check to the department chair or head.

3. The minor(s) must be approved by the adviser, the department chair or head, the Dean and the cognizant program offering the minor(s).

4. The College of Engineering will follow the “A/B” format of the Arts and Sciences College in which a student pursuing a single minor must complete the “A” requirements. A student pursuing a double (or greater) minor must fulfill either the “A” or “B” requirements for both minors depending on which plan is offered by the cognizant department.

5. Minors on the Lincoln or Omaha campuses may be added to the following list on approval of the College of Engineering Curriculum Committee and faculty.

Approved Minors

Agricultural Economics: See “Agricultural Economics Minor”

Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communication: See “Leadership and Communication Minor”

Agriculture and Natural Resources: See “International Agriculture and Natural Resources Minor”

Agronomy: See “Agronomy Minor”

Animal Science: See “Animal Science Minor”

Art History: See “Art History Minor”

Aviation (Omaha campus): Contact Aviation Institute at UNO for more details at 402/554-3424.

Biochemistry: See “Requirements for the Minor in Biochemistry”

Biological Sciences: See “Requirements for the Minor in Biological Sciences”

Biomedical Engineering Minor:

Required Core Courses 24

BIOS 101 & BIOS 101L or BIOS 102 4

BIOS 213 & BIOS 213L 4

PHYS 212 4

BSEN 317 3

Electives 9

(6 hrs in courses outside your major)

Tracks:

Tissue-Engineering

CHME 473 3

Biomechanics

MECH 436 3

IMSE 415 3

IMSE 416 3

Medical Imaging

BSEN 311 3

And Biomedical

BSEN 414 3

Signal Processing

ELEC 304 3

Business Minor for Jeffrey S. Raikes School of Computer Science and Management: Plan A only.

The minor detailed below is applicable only to students participating in the Jeffrey S. Raikes School of Computer Science and Management. All courses must be taken for a letter grade.

Required Foundation Courses 16-17

MATH 106, MATH 107 or MATH 208 4-5

STAT 218 or STAT 380 or IMSE 321 3

RAIK 181H 3

RAIK 182H 3

RAIK 281H 3

Required Business Core Courses 12

MRKT 341 3

RAIK 282H 3

RAIK 381H 3

RAIK 382H 3

Total hours for the RAIK/BSAD minor 28-29

Communication Studies: See “Requirements for the Minor in Communication Studies”

NOTE: Engineering students may not use internship credit to satisfy this minor.

Construction Management: Plan A only.

All courses must be taken for a letter grade.

Required Courses 27

BLAW 372 Business Law I 3

CNST 112 Construction Communications 3

CNST 241 Construction Equipment & Methods I 3

CNST 305 Physical Environmental Systems I 3

CNST 378 Construction Estimating I 3

CNST 379 Construction Estimating II 3

CNST 480 Productivity & Human Factors 3

CNST 485 Construction Project Scheduling & Control 3

MNGT 360 Managing Behavior in Organizations 3

Economics: See “Requirements for the Minor in Economics”

Engineering Mechanics: Plan A–12 credit hours beyond the regular undergraduate engineering mechanics sequence (ENGM 223, 325, 373 or ENGM 250, 350). These may be chosen from 300- and 400-level courses offered by engineering mechanics, excluding those courses required in the student’s curriculum by the major department.

English: See “Requirements for the Minor in English”

Ethnic Studies: See “Requirements for the Minor in Ethnic Studies”

European Studies: See “Requirements for the Minor in European Studies”

General Business: Plan A only.

All courses must be taken for a letter grade.

Required Foundation Courses 21-26

ACCT 201 & ACCT 202 or ACCT 306 4-6

ECON 211 & ACCT 212 or ACCT 210 6

IMSE 321 or STAT 380 or ECON 215 or STAT 218 or ELEC 305 3

MATH 106 5

CSCE 150A or CSCE 150E or CSCE 155 or CNST 112 & CNST 131 3-6

Required Business Core Courses 12

FINA 361 or IMSE 206 3

MRKT 341 3

MNGT 350/MIST 350 or MNGT 320 or MNGT 331 or MNGT 360 3

300/400-level business course 3

Geography: See “Requirements for the Major in Geography”

Geology: See “Requirements for the Minor in Geology”

History: See “Requirements for the Minor in History”

International Agriculture and Natural Resources: See “International Agriculture and Natural Resources Minor”

International Studies: See “International Studies”

Japanese: See “Requirements for the Minor in Japanese”

Mathematics and Statistics: Plan A only–12 credit hours beyond the calculus sequence (MATH 106-MATH 107-MATH 208, or MATH 106H-MATH 208H) and differential equations (MATH 221 or MATH 221H). These courses may be chosen from the 300- or 400-level course offered by mathematics and statistics except MATH 350, MATH 450 and MATH 460.

Meteorology-Climatology: See “Requirements for the Minor in Meteorology–Climatology”

Modern Languages: Only for engineering students.

Czech: There is no Plan A minor. Plan B–6 hours at the 300 level.

French, German and Russian: Plan A–12 hours at the 203 level and above, including 6 hours at the 300 level. Plan B–9 hours at the 203 level and above, including 3 hours at the 300 level.

Japanese: Plan A–12 hours at the 203 level and above, including 6 hours at the 300 level. Plan B–6 hours at the 203 level and above, including 204.

Spanish: Plan A–12 hours numbered at 303 or above. Plan B–6 hours from 303 or above.

Music: See “Requirements for the Minor in Music (Plan A) (19 cr)”

Philosophy: See “Requirements for the Minor in Philosophy”

Physics: See “Requirements for the Minor in Physics”

Political Science: See “Requirements for the Minor in Political Science”

Psychology: See “Requirements for the Minor in Psychology”

Sociology: See “Requirements for the Minor in Sociology”

Water Science: See “Water Science Minor”

Women’s and Gender Studies: See “Requirements for the Minor in Women’s and Gender Studies”

Minor in International Engineering

This minor is designed to encourage and give recognition to undergraduate students who enhance their engineering education with courses and experiences consistent with the global nature of engineering and the economy. This minor has four components:

1. Twelve (12) credit hours of courses in international engineering and related courses.
The courses must be chosen from the list of courses maintained by the Associate Dean of Academic Affairs and the College Office of International Programs. The course list includes all sections of ENGR 490 and MODL 98 and the list of courses included in Appendix 1. In addition,

a. A minimum of 3 credit hours must be in ENGR 490 courses.

b. A minimum of 6 credit hours must be in 300-level courses or above.

c. A maximum of 6 credit hours may be taken Pass/No Pass.

2. Two (2) semesters with a minimum of 6 credit hours of college-level foreign language.
The actual number of credit hours taken will depend on the specific courses taken by the student.

3. Participation in a study abroad experience in a program approved by the Associate Dean of Academic Affairs and the College Office of International Programs.

4. A minimum of 9 credit hours of the course work listed for this minor cannot count toward the undergraduate engineering degree or the master of architectural engineering degree.

OTHER

Professional Licensure

The College encourages professional licensure. The majority of the College’s engineering seniors take the Fundamentals of Engineering (FE) examination prior to graduation. This examination is administered by the Nebraska Board of Engineers and Architects, a state agency, and the first step in the process of becoming a licensed professional engineer. To become a licensed professional engineer, one must pass the FE exam, have four years of experience, and pass a professional practice examination. Students may take the FE exam in the last semester of their baccalaureate program.

Accreditation

All programs are accredited by the Accreditation Board for Engineering and Technology (ABET). The agricultural engineering, biological systems engineering, chemical engineering, civil engineering (Lincoln and Omaha campuses), computer engineering (Lincoln and Omaha campus), electrical engineering, electronics engineering, industrial engineering, and mechanical engineering programs are accredited by the Engineering Accreditation Commission of the Accreditation Board for Engineering and Technology.

The master of architectural engineering is accredited by the Engineering Accreditation Commission of the Accreditation Board for Engineering and Technology.

The construction management program is accredited by the American Council for Construction Education.

The undergraduate degree program in construction engineering is accredited.

Scholarships and Financial Aid

Each year the College awards scholarships to freshmen and upperclassmen worth more than $750,000. Scholarship awards are made possible through generous gifts of alumni and friends, local and national organizations, and through funding by the Nebraska Legislature. Contact the Office of the Dean or the Office of Scholarships and Financial Aid for information regarding these awards and for other financial assistance.

Application for UNL freshmen scholarships automatically makes you eligible for College of Engineering scholarships as well as other university awards such as the Regents and David scholarships. You must submit the UNL Application form (due January 15, prior to the beginning of the next academic year) to be eligible.

A significant number of entering students have academic records that qualify them for university-wide scholarship awards. Each year about 25 percent of the freshman Regent Scholarship recipients are engineering students.

A large number of students are able to find part-time employment in fields related to their interests.

Student Organizations in the College

Technical Societies

The technical student societies help develop a greater personal and professional interest and understanding in engineering, computer science and construction management. Student branches of the major national technical and scientific societies are sponsored by the academic programs and departments.

Lincoln Campus. American Institute of Chemical Engineers; The Society for Engineering in Agricultural, Food, and Biological Systems; American Society of Civil Engineers; American Society of Mechanical Engineers; Associated General Contractors; Association for Computer Machinery; Institute of Electrical and Electronic Engineers; Institute of Industrial Engineers; American Society for Metals; Student Advisory Board; Institute of Transportation Engineers; National Society of Black Engineers; Society of American Military Engineers; Society of Women Engineers; and Society of Automotive Engineers.

Omaha Campus. American Society of Civil Engineers; American Society of Heating, Refrigeration and Air-conditioning Engineers; Associated General Contractors; Institute of Electrical and Electronic Engineers; Instrumentation Society of America; Architectural Engineering Institute, Acoustical Society of America; Minorities in Engineering; Society of Women Engineers; Engineering Student Advisory Board; and Architectural Engineering Student Leadership and Advisory Committee.

Lifelong Learning

The education of professionals in construction management, engineering, and engineering technology is a continuing process. The groundwork in both technical and nontechnical studies is laid while in college, but education continues after graduation. For a professional, education continues in the technical and in the human and social concerns areas, and may expect to take a leadership role in the community, have a broad awareness of human and social accomplishments, needs, values, and a willingness to take the responsibility for meeting these needs. For these reasons, an integrated program of course work in the humanities and social sciences is a part of the educational requirements.

###

College of Journalism & Mass Communications

College of Journalism & Mass Communications

About the College

Gary Kebbel, M.A., M.S.W., M.A., Dean and Professor of Journalism, 472-3041

Charlyne Berens, Ph.D., Associate Dean and Professor of Journalism, 472-3041

Mission/Objectives/Goals

The primary mission of the College of Journalism and Mass Communications is to graduate highly competitive young professionals who have acquired communication and critical thinking skills appropriate to the practice of journalism and strategic communications: writing, editing, oral presentation and design in print, broadcast and interactive media. Because a viable career in the media professions requires graduates to understand the changes in society that make differences in people’s lives, journalism and mass communications education includes a fusion with the liberal arts and sciences at UNL.

The college’s mission dictates a high priority role for excellent undergraduate teaching in advertising, broadcasting and news-editorial. An MA in journalism and mass communications complements this emphasis by building on a well established and nationally recognized undergraduate curriculum.

Administrative Structure

The college includes two sequences—advertising and journalism—in which students may major in advertising, broadcasting, or news-editorial.

Undergraduate Majors

Advertising

Broadcasting

News-editorial

Faculty

Quality undergraduate teaching is a source of pride in the College of Journalism and Mass Communications. Most classes are small, and faculty members are known for the individual attention they give to their students. Faculty have a wealth of experience in the communications professions: as advertising and public relations managers, writers and designers for advertising and public relations agencies, newspapers and broadcasting outlets; as writers, producers and on-air talent for radio and television; and as reporters, editors and photographers at newspapers and magazines.

ADMISSION

College Admission

The entrance requirements for the College of Journalism and Mass Communications are the same as the admission requirements for the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.

These include:

English (4 units)
Mathematics (4 units)
Social studies (3 units)
Natural sciences (3 units), and
Foreign language (2 units).

One unit equals one year of high school credit. Students with one deficiency, two deficiencies but not in the same category, or two deficiencies in foreign language who receive a Deferred Admission or Admission by Review, may be considered for admission to the college. Students who are admitted through the Admission by Review process with core course deficiencies will have certain conditions attached to their enrollment at UNL. These conditions are explained under Admission to the University, Removal of Deficiencies. High school deficiencies must be removed during the first 30 credit hours of enrollment at UNL (60 hours for foreign language) or the first calendar year, whichever takes longer.

Admission Deficiency Information

The college’s policy regarding acceptance of credit for courses taken to remove admission deficiencies is that those credit hours will count toward ACE and elective credit (Group L of the non-major requirements) only.

Admission GPA

Any student transferring into the college must have at least a 2.0 GPA. A student with 12 or more hours of college credit must have at least a 2.0 GPA to be admitted or readmitted to the College of Journalism and Mass Communications.

Readmission

A student who left the University not in good standing (below a 2.0 grade point average), may be readmitted in the Division of General Studies. Such a student would be eligible to reenter the College of Journalism and Mass Communications upon attaining a 2.0 cumulative GPA. This student would follow the bulletin in effect at the time of the transfer from General Studies to the college.

Other Admission Requirements

Students from Other Colleges

College of Journalism and Mass Communications courses will be restricted to College of Journalism and Mass Communications majors except where stipulated differently. Students from colleges and departments with a written agreement with the College of Journalism and Mass Communications will be exempt from this policy. Permission may be granted by the dean of the College of Journalism and Mass Communications in special circumstances following the directives provided by the faculty in these matters.

ESL Students

Applicants who speak English as a second language must present a TOEFL score of 600 or higher. Additionally, broadcasting majors must present a score of at least 45 on the Test of Spoken English.

ADVISING

Academic Advising

Upon enrollment in the college, each student is assigned to a faculty adviser. The student is expected to consult with his or her adviser each semester before registering for the next semester’s courses.

Although the faculty advisers seek to assist students in the selection of courses leading toward graduation, the final decision regarding which courses are taken is ultimately the student’s. Therefore, students are responsible for identifying and enrolling in those courses that will lead to completion of all published degree requirements.

In addition, each first-year student and each senior should see the college’s advising coordinator, 105 Andersen Hall, to make sure all college and university requirements are completed.

ACADEMIC PROGRAMS & POLICIES

Course Exclusions & Restrictions

Course Exclusions

Courses from the following areas will not count toward the bachelor of journalism degree.

athletic coaching (ATHC)
athletic training (ATHT)
health education (NUTR), first aid or emergency healthcare
agricultural leadership, education and communication (ALEC) (except ALEC 102, ALEC 207, and ALEC 417)
vocational and adult education courses, business education courses student assistantships, teaching assistantships, proctoring, or grading internships of a journalistic nature taken through any university unit or department
any independent study course, clinical course, experiential course or practicum outside the College of Journalism and Mass Communications undertaken without the prior written approval of the student’s adviser
driver training education
industrial arts (including courses concerned primarily with manual skills, tools, machines, or industrial processes and design)
orientation courses, such as UNL’s ALEC 397E and ALEC 397K (neither course is applicable to the courses numbered above 299 requirement); ASCI 107; BIOC 101; BIOS 150, 160; EDPS 150; FDST 107; HRFS 183; NRES 101, NUTR 150; PSYC 100, PSYC 150; TEAC 210; VBMS 101
math courses below 100 and MATH 100A
course on word processing and graphics
EDPS 327 (except EDPS 189H, EDPS 250, EDPS 251, EDPS 362, EDPS 457, and EDPS 459)
BSAD 150 or CSCE 137 or AGRI 271

Course Restrictions

Credit toward the degree may be earned in only one course, including honors sections, from each group of courses listed below:

BIOS 312 or AGRO 360

BIOS 313 or BIOS 314

CHEM 105, CHEM 109, CHEM 111, CHEM 113, CHEM 195

CHEM 116 or CHEM 221

CHEM 251 and more than 1 cr of CHEM 263

CHEM 471 or CHEM 481

CSCE 252D or CSCE 150E

CSCE 252D or ENGM 112

CSCE 252D or ELEC 121

CSCE 340 or CSCE 480

ECON 210, or ECON 211 and ECON 212

ECON 215, CRIM 300, EDPS 459 or STAT 218

FREN 201 and FREN 202, or FREN 210

GEOL 100 or GEOL 101 or GEOL 101H

GEOL 103 or GEOL 105

GERM 201 and GERM 202, or GERM 210

LATN 102 or LATN 201

MATH 101 and/or MATH 102 or MATH 103

MATH 104 or MATH 106

MATH 200 or MATH 300

MATH 201 or MATH 301

MATH 340 or ENGM 480

PHYS 141 or PHYS 151

PHYS 151 or MSYM 109

SOCI 205 or CRIM 251

SOCI 209 or CRIM 355

SOCI 311 or CRIM 337

SOCI 474 or CRIM 413

SPAN 201 and SPAN 202, or SPAN 210

Credit Rules

Credit by Examination

Through study or experience that parallels a University of Nebraska-Lincoln course, a regularly enrolled university student may feel prepared to pass an examination on the course content for course credit. To apply for credit, a student should:

1. Pick up a credit-by-examination form at the Information Window, Office of Registration and Records, 107 Canfield Administration Building;

2. Secure the approval signature of the dean of the college;

3. Have the Credentials Office verify that he or she is currently enrolled;

4. Secure the Bursar’s Receipt for Payment of the examination fee; and

5. Present the completed form to the instructor designated by the dean’s office.

The instructor will then give the examination and report the results to the Office of Registration and Records through the dean of the college. A student is not permitted to receive credit by examination in a course that is a prerequisite for one in which he or she already has received credit.

The College of Journalism and Mass Communications also gives credit for the subject and general examinations of the College Level Examination Program (CLEP) administered by the College Entrance Examination Board. Inquire in 107 Canfield Administration Building for the current policy regarding CLEP examinations.

Grade Appeals

The following is a synopsis of the College of Journalism and Mass Communications grade appeals policy. The policy is designed to provide students with protection through orderly procedures against prejudiced or capricious academic evaluation. A student with a concern about a grade should take the following steps:

1. Talk with the instructor involved. Many problems are resolved at this level.

2. Talk with an assistant or associate dean in 147 Andersen Hall.

3. If the foregoing steps have not resulted in a solution, arrange to take the problem to the sequence grading appeals committee. This step involves presenting the problem in writing.

4. If an appeal from the sequence committee is necessary, arrange to take the appeal to the College Grading Appeals Committee.

Student Recognition

Honors and Awards

Outstanding students are honored each spring during an honors convocation. The college recognizes students whose cumulative grade point averages place them in the top 10 percent of their respective classes, students who hold scholarships and students who have earned special awards.

In addition, the college distributes a semester dean’s list. To be included on the semester dean’s list, a student must have earned at least a 3.7 semester GPA on 12 or more graded hours.

Kappa Tau Alpha. The Will Owen Jones Chapter of Kappa Tau Alpha, the national journalism honorary, recognizes outstanding undergraduate and graduate students. Membership is limited to those in the top 10 percent of the junior and senior classes in the College of Journalism and Mass Communications who have completed the junior level professional courses. Each year the society honors a student achieving the highest four-year grade point average in the college and presents an award to the Distinguished Journalist of the Year.

Alpha Delta Sigma. As the only national honorary society for advertising students, ADS recognizes outstanding academic achievement. Since ADS was initiated in 1976, students nominated by their faculty advisers have been elected by division leaders into this exclusive scholastic group. An ADS chapter was founded at UNL in 1993. To be eligible for nomination, students must be enrolled in the local American Advertising Federation chapter (Ad Club).

Alpha Epsilon Rho. Alpha Epsilon Rho recognizes superior scholarship in the field of broadcasting. The University of Nebraska chapter was chartered in 1946. Membership is by invitation upon completion of 9 hours in broadcasting with a cumulative grade of 3.25 in broadcasting and 3.0 cumulative or above. For more information, contact the college office in 147 Andersen Hall.

Degrees With Distinction

In recognition of academic excellence, the college recommends the bachelors degree with distinction, with high distinction and with highest distinction. To be recommended, candidates must fulfill the specific criteria as described below, in addition to meeting all the general criteria and procedures applicable to all distinction classifications. The thesis and results of the examination over the thesis in each instance must be acceptable to the advisory committee.

Highest Distinction. Candidates for the bachelors degree may be recommended for degrees with highest distinction on the basis of the following criteria: scholastic standing within the top 5 percent of the graduating class of the college in the preceding 12-month period and the advisory committee’s recommendation based upon a thesis or comparable creative effort and an oral examination over that thesis or creative effort.

High Distinction. Candidates for the bachelors degree may be recommended for degrees with high distinction by fulfilling one of two sets of criteria: 1) by achieving scholastic standing within the top 5 percent of the graduating class of the college in the preceding 12-month period; or 2) by achieving scholastic standing within the top 10 percent of the graduating class of the college in the preceding 12-month period and by recommendation of the advisory committee based on a thesis or comparable creative effort and an oral examination over that thesis or creative effort.

Distinction. Candidates for the bachelors degree may be recommended for degrees with distinction by achieving one of two sets of criteria: 1) by achieving scholastic standing within the top 10 percent of the graduating class of the college in the preceding 12-month period; or 2) by achieving scholastic standing within the top 15 percent of the graduating class (never below a 3.7 GPA) of the college for the preceding 12-month period and by recommendation of the college’s advisory committee based upon a thesis or comparable creative effort and an oral examination over that thesis or creative effort.

The following criteria apply to all categories: Ordinarily, only students who have taken their last 48 hours of course work in residence will be considered for degrees with distinction. In considering individual cases, the advisory committee will review both grades and the program of courses. Students who choose one of the thesis options described above should make arrangements before their senior year by consulting with their academic advisers. These students must register for ADVT 499H or JOUR 499H for one hour of credit in the semester they plan to complete the thesis proposal and register for an additional two hours of credit in the semester they plan to complete the thesis. At least two members of the student’s honors thesis committee must make a recommendation to the advisory committee on the thesis work.

During the semester before the student intends to graduate, she or he should visit the dean’s office in Andersen Hall to obtain the schedule of deadline dates for submission of reports of examining committees. The forms for making the reports are also available in the dean’s office.

Scholarships

Each year the college awards more than 100 scholarships worth more than $178,000. Most scholarships go to upperclassmen, although a limited number are awarded to freshmen.

College scholarship information is available on-line at the college’s Web site, www.unl.edu/journalism/students/undergrad/scholarships.shtml. The forms must be completed and returned to the dean’s office by March 1. Awards are made in April.

Entering freshmen must apply through the university’s Admissions Office in the Van Brunt Visitor Center, 313 N. 13th Street. Additional applications and letters of explanation may be sent to the college at the following address:

College of Journalism and Mass Communications

University of Nebraska–Lincoln

Scholarship Committee

147 Andersen Hall

PO Box 880443

Lincoln, NE 68588-0443

Senior Check/Degree Audit

It is no longer necessary to request a “senior check.” Graduation Services, 109 Canfield Administration Building, automatically mails a letter and degree audit to each senior to identify any unfulfilled requirements in the student’s academic program.

With each term’s registration, students should determine how course selections apply to requirements by obtaining a degree audit, available at the MyRED link on http://www.unl.edu.

Students should print their degree audits and take them to the meetings with their advisers. Because the Web-based degree audit system loads overnight, one can examine a new audit no sooner than one day after registering for classes.

Application for Degree

Each student who expects to receive a diploma must file an application for candidacy for the diploma and pay a $25 fee to Graduation Services, 109 Canfield Administration Building. Announcements about deadline dates are published and posted on bulletin boards around campus.

Students are responsible for informing Graduation Services of their graduation plans, including their addresses, the manner in which they are completing their requirements, such as by correspondence, by clearance of incompletes, by enrollment at another institution, by taking special examinations, etc., and of any later revision of such plans. Failure to follow this procedure may cause postponement of graduation until a later semester.

The first semester during which the transcript indicates a student is a journalism major establishes the semester in which he or she is considered to have entered the college.

Student Standing/Classification

Sophomore Standing. For admission to sophomore standing a student must have completed a minimum of 27 semester hours of credit and attained a total grade point average of at least C.

Junior Standing. A student has junior standing after meeting the requirements for sophomore standing and completing 53 semester hours of credit.

Senior Standing. A student has senior standing after meeting the requirements for junior standing and completing 89 semester hours of credit.

Waivers/Substitutions

The college will allow no waivers for graduation requirements. If students think they have met the intent of a particular requirement in some other fashion, they may submit a substitution request form.

The form requires students to justify the request and secure recommendations from their advisers. Students must submit completed requests, with appropriate recommendations, to the dean’s office no later than two working days prior to the next regularly scheduled meeting of the College Executive Committee. Decisions to grant or deny requests will be made by that committee or a designated subcommittee; appeals will go to the full faculty.

Students must remember that it is their responsibility to know and follow the graduation requirements of the college. A substitution request should come only after all other avenues of advising and course work have been exhausted.

The faculty will consider only substitutions. Under no circumstances will requirements be waived. A substitution shall be defined as:

1. The replacement of a required course by a course of very similar content.

2. Credit by examination when offered.

3. The replacement of a required course with significant professional experience. This will be allowed only in rare instances. The experience will substitute only for course content, not for credit hours. Additional credit hours may be needed to maintain minimum credit hour requirements for graduation.

ACE REQUIREMENTS

All students must fulfill the Achievement Centered Education (ACE) requirements. Information about the ACE program may be viewed at ace.unl.edu.

BULLETIN TO USE

Students who left the university in good standing may be readmitted in the College of Journalism and Mass Communications, and they may choose the bulletin under which they wish to graduate according to the following guidelines:

1. Students must fulfill the requirements stated in the Undergraduate Bulletin for the year they enter the College of Journalism and Mass Communications or in any subsequent bulletin published while they are enrolled in the college.

2. A student must, however, meet the requirements from one bulletin only rather than choosing a portion from one bulletin and the remainder from another.

3. No returning student may use a bulletin that is 10 years old or older. In addition, any student seeking graduation credit for a College of Journalism and Mass Communications course taken more than 10 years prior to graduation must demonstrate mastery of the material currently included in that course at the proficiency level satisfactory to the college’s advisory committee and one or more faculty members qualified to teach the course in question. Students unable to demonstrate satisfactory mastery of the course material will be required to repeat the original course or a corresponding contemporary course designated by the college’s advisory committee, if the original course is no longer offered.

COLLEGE DEGREE REQUIREMENTS

College General Education Requirements

To graduate with a bachelor of journalism degree, students must complete requirements from the following areas:

the University ACE requirements
the requirements for a major offered by the college
the non-major requirements that are specific to the college

College Non-Major Requirements

The College non-major requirements (NMR) are designed to further the purposes of liberal education by encouraging study in several different areas. Courses satisfying these requirements may impart specialized knowledge or broadly connect the subject matter to other areas of knowledge.

Students may use ACE courses (except for ACE 3 courses) to satisfy the College non-major requirements. Independent study courses and internships cannot be used to satisfy requirements A-G.

The College of Journalism and Mass Communications requires all students to complete the following specific course requirements. Many of these may also count toward ACE outcomes:

A. Six hours from ACE outcome 1. At least three hours must be from ENGL 101, ENGL 150, ENGL 151 or ENGL 254.

B. Ten hours from natural, physical and mathematical sciences: Choose from two different departments, including at least one course from the natural or physical sciences. Select from: biochemistry, biological sciences, chemistry, computer science and engineering, geosciences, mathematics, physics and astronomy, and statistics.

C. Complete a lab for a natural or physical science course above. Lab courses may be selected from biochemistry, biological sciences, chemistry, geosciences, physics and astronomy, geography, and anthropology*.

* See degree audit for approved geography and anthropology lab courses.

D. Six hours from economics (ECON). See ACE 6 and ACE 8 for overlapping options.

E. Three hours from political science (POLS).

F. Nine hours from history (HIST). See ACE 5 and ACE 9 for overlapping options.

G. Nine hours from humanities department(s) other than history. Select from classics, English (film or literature, not writing), modern languages and literatures, philosophy, and religious studies.

H. LIBR 110, 1 credit hour–waived for transfer students with 27 or more hours.

I. Candidates for the bachelor of journalism degree must abide by the Accrediting Council on Education in Journalism and Mass Communication accrediting guidelines, which require 65 semester hours taken in subjects listed as traditional liberal arts and sciences by the University. See the degree audit for a list of the areas currently considered liberal arts.

J. Languages—Classical and Modern: 0-6 hours
Fulfilled by the completion of 6 credit hours at the 200 level or above in a single foreign language in one of the following departments: classics and religious studies, modern languages and literatures, or anthropology. Instruction is currently available in Biblical Hebrew, Chinese, Czech, French, German, Greek, Japanese, Latin, Omaha, Russian, and Spanish. A student who has completed the fourth-year level of one foreign language in high school is exempt from the languages requirement.

Options for completion of language requirement:

1. Regular four-semester sequence: 101, 102, 201, and 202 (5, 5, 3, 3 hours for a total of 16)

2. Three-semester sequence: 101, 102, and 210 (5, 5, 6 hours for a total of 16)

3. 101, 102 fall and spring semesters; 201, 202 summer sessions (5, 5, 3, 3 hours for a total of 16). This and the option below constitute the only possibilities to finish the complete requirement in one year.

4. (For Spanish) 101, 102 at UNL; 201, 202 at Monterrey Summer Institute (6 hours). (5, 5, 6 hours for a total of 16.) One six-week summer session (1st summer session). See modern languages non-majors adviser for information and application.

Students who have taken three years or fewer of a foreign language in high school should contact the Department of Modern Languages and Literatures for recommended placement.

A student who achieves a specified scaled score in the College Level Examination Program (CLEP) subject exam in French, German and Spanish, levels 1 and 2, may be exempted from the language requirement and may also receive credit for the fourth semester course in the language. Students wishing to exercise this option must receive permission from the dean of the College of Journalism and Mass Communications.

A transfer student with 11 or 12 semester hours of accepted credit in a single foreign language has two choices: a) to complete 201 and 202 in the same language; or b) to enroll in 202 with permission of the chair of the Department of Modern Languages and Literatures.

A student from a foreign country who has demonstrated acceptable proficiency in his or her native language (other than English) is exempted from the foreign language requirement without credit toward the degree. United States citizens who present acceptable evidence that their second language is English are exempted from the language requirement without credit toward the degree. All such students should see the dean of the College of Journalism and Mass Communications for this exemption.

NOTE: Language courses numbered 201, 202 or 210 apply to the Group J Foreign Language requirement and to Group I. Language courses numbered in the 100s apply only to Group L.

K. Students also must choose courses that will produce three 12-hour concentrations or one 24-hour concentration and one 12-hour concentration. A concentration is defined as 12 ours from the same department with no more than 6 100-level hours. A specified minor may take the place of one 12-hour concentration. A major of 24 or more hours may take the place of a 24-hour concentration. At least one of these options must be from one of the liberal arts departments, and all of these options must be from outside the College of Journalism and Mass Communications.
The College recognizes cross-listed courses as equivalent for the purposes of degree requirements. However, a course taken under one department that is cross-listed cannot be applied in all the majors and minors affected by all the cross-listings of the course until at least 36 hours of course work have been recorded in the concentration requirement. Once 36 discrete hours are applied to Group K, courses may count in more than one concentration. Hybrid concentrations in fine arts and business are shown in the separate major pages.

L. The Accrediting Council on Education in Journalism and Mass Communication additionally requires that students complete at least 80 semester hours in courses outside the College of Journalism and Mass Communications.
Students graduating with 125 hours can take no more than 45 hours in the College of Journalism and Mass Communications.
Students needing 130 hours to graduate can take no more than 50 hours in College of Journalism and Mass Communication courses. Students wanting to take more than 45 or 50 hours in the college should note that any hours over the 45- or 50-hour limit will be in addition to the hours required to graduate.

M. At least 30 of the 125 (or 130) semester hours of credit must be in courses numbered above 299. NOTE: ALEC 397E and ALEC 397K do not count toward these 30 hours.

Minimum Hours Required for Graduation

A minimum of 125 semester hours of credit is required for graduation from the College of Journalism and Mass Communications.

Students who enter the college with fewer than two units of a single foreign language from high school are required to take 130 semester hours as a minimum for the bachelor of journalism degree.

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

The college will accept no more than 15 semester hours of grades less than a C from any program outside the University of Nebraska system. No grades less than a C will count toward a major, a minor, or concentration.

Pass/No Pass Limits

The college will accept up to 24 hours of Pass/No Pass courses toward a bachelor of journalism degree, subject to the following limits.

All courses in the College of Journalism and Mass Communications must be taken for grade only. No journalism course may be taken Pass/No Pass. This applies to both majors and non-majors.

The Pass/No Pass (P/N) option is designed to be used by students seeking to expand their intellectual horizons by taking courses in areas where they may have minimum preparation without adversely affecting a student’s grade point average.

1. Neither a P (pass) nor an N (no pass) contributes to a student’s GPA.

2. P (pass) is interpreted to mean a grade of C or better. A student who earns a C- or lower will receive a grade of N.

3. P/N is not available to students on academic probation unless the course is offered only that way.

4. For undergraduates, the 24-hour college limit shall apply. This limit does not include courses offered on a Pass/No Pass only basis or AP credit. This limit does apply to transfer courses from UNO, UNK, UNMC, and other institutions.

5. P/N hours can count toward fulfillment of group requirements, including concentrations, up to the 24 credit hour maximum. No journalism major may take a journalism course Pass/No Pass.

6. Students may change from graded to P/N only until half way through the course. Additionally, after the half-way date, a student registered for P/N cannot change to graded unless the P/N registration is in conflict with a professor, department, college, or university policy governing P/N. Changing from graded to P/N or from P/N to graded can be completed on MyRED or by filing a drop/add form with the Office of Registration and Records, 107 Canfield Administration Building, and needs no instructor’s approval.

Transfer Credit Rules

The goal of the following policy is to ensure that students from other campuses meet the same standards required of students who take all their courses at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln’s College of Journalism and Mass Communications.

The college will accept up to 6 hours in journalism and mass communications courses taken at institutions that do not have an accredited journalism and mass communications program. Students must take the remainder of the required hours in journalism courses on campus at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln. In advertising, these courses must include 460 and 489 and in broadcasting, 370 and 372 or 360 and 362. In news-editorial, the courses must include 302 and one selected from the following: JOUR 303, JOUR 404, or a 400-level writing course. Students from ACEJMC-accredited programs may request equivalency reviews of the required courses at those schools. Degree candidates must accumulate 80 credit hours of non-journalism classes, 65 of those in disciplines listed as liberal arts.

Credit for courses taken at foreign universities and colleges will be transferred only after evaluation by the appropriate professor in the major. This evaluation may include examination of the student over subject matter studied at the foreign institution.

Normally, credit is not given for pre-university work. In some instances, it may be possible to receive credit through satisfactory examination.

Residency

At least 30 of the last 36 hours of credit needed for the degree must be registered for and completed while the student is enrolled in the University of Nebraska–Lincoln. This means the last year of the student’s work must be spent in residence. To encourage participation in international study, the college accepts all study-abroad hours as hours in residence.

DEGREES & MAJORS

Bachelor of Journalism Degree Requirements

A minimum of 125 semester hours of credit is required for graduation from the College of Journalism and Mass Communications. A student who enters with fewer than two years of the same high school foreign language must complete 130 hours.

A maximum of 12 hours of military science (MLSC), naval science (NAVS), and aerospace studies (AERO) may be counted toward the degree.

A maximum of 4 hours of practice courses in varsity sports and recreational activity courses (ATHP, COMB, FITN, INDV, ODED and RACS) or Basic Military Science, which is credit for active military duty, not ROTC course work.

A maximum of 15 hours of applied study, defined as courses including “performance, practice or skills” in their titles or course descriptions. This limitation on fine arts, communication studies and other areas outside the College of Journalism and Mass Communications does not apply to students completing designated majors or minors in those areas. This means that a student who has declared a designated major or minor or concentration in any of these areas has no performance limit applied to the degree audit.

Majors

The major is 35 hours in advertising, 35 hours in broadcasting and 35 hours in news-editorial.

Students must choose at least one of three undergraduate majors—advertising, broadcasting, or news-editorial. Each of these majors requires professional courses for students. Additionally, all students must take the core courses–JOUR 101, JOUR 142, JOUR 486, and JOUR 487.

Students may complete two majors in the College of Journalism and Mass Communications by completing all requirements for each major; however, the second major in the college will not take the place of a 24-hour concentration.

Intercollege Studies

A student in the College of Journalism and Mass Communications pursuing a bachelor of journalism degree may also complete a second major in the College of Arts and Sciences as part of a four-year program. In addition to ACE and College of Journalism and Mass Communications requirements, students will be expected to meet all College of Arts and Sciences distribution requirements and major requirements. Because students choosing this option will not be earning a degree from Arts and Sciences, they will not be eligible for Arts and Sciences-based scholarships and aid, but they will be eligible for consideration for Phi Beta Kappa.

A student who prefers to receive the second degree would file for dual matriculation. Such a student would complete an additional 30 hours as part of earning the second degree.

JGEN courses, which are open to students from any college, do not count in any College of Journalism and Mass Communications major. Non-College of Journalism and Mass Communications students must have permission to enroll in any ADVT, BRDC, or JOUR courses. Permission generally is reserved for students whose colleges have agreements with the College of Journalism and Mass Communications.

GRADUATE STUDENT INFORMATION

Graduate Courses

Seniors in the University who have obtained in advance the approval of the dean for Graduate Studies may receive up to 12 credit hours for graduate courses taken in addition to the courses necessary to complete their undergraduate work, provided that such credits are earned within the calendar year prior to receipt of the baccalaureate. For procedures, inquire at the Office of Graduate Studies.

Course work taken prior to receipt of the baccalaureate may not always be accepted for transfer to other institutions as graduate work.

The Graduate Program

A graduate program, leading to the master of arts degree, was established in 1975. It is designed to prepare the student to translate more effectively to mass audiences the complexities of a rapidly changing society. Emphasis may be placed on advertising, broadcasting or news-editorial journalism. Students entering the program must have the equivalent of an undergraduate major in an accredited program in journalism and mass communications or extensive professional experience. Students also can earn a masters degree in journalism in an interdisciplinary program that includes advertising, marketing and communication studies. Persons seeking more information about graduate study in the College of Journalism and Mass Communications should consult the graduate bulletin or call or write the Gilbert M. and Martha H. Hitchcock Center for Graduate Study and Professional Journalism, 127 Andersen Hall, (402) 472-3042, or visit the college’s Web site.

Hitchcock Center for Graduate Study and Professional Journalism Development

The Hitchcock Center, with a $250,000 endowment from the Gilbert M. and Martha H. Hitchcock Foundation, helps finance the graduate program in the College of Journalism and Mass Communications and further develops the skills of Nebraska’s professional journalists. It accomplishes the latter goal by giving direct support to the state’s professional journalists through research projects and statewide workshops aimed at improving skills in newswriting, advertising and broadcasting. The center also funds a $5,000 graduate fellowship and a distinguished faculty chair. Gilbert M. Hitchcock was a United States senator from Nebraska and founder of the Omaha World-Herald.

Division of General Studies

DESCRIPTION

A Program of the Office of Undergraduate Studies

Chief Adviser: Jennifer Nelson

The Division of General Studies provides an academic home for UNL students who come to the campus uncertain about the field of study they wish to pursue. The Division of General Studies does not award degrees. While students are choosing their major, General Studies advisers assist students with course selection and degree planning. Advisers also help students identify UNL majors that match their interests.

Students who choose to begin their academic careers in General Studies have a variety of career interests and need time to make a decision regarding which college and major are most appropriate for them. Others have narrowed their choices to two or three options but want to explore these choices in greater depth before they make a firm commitment. Still other students have no idea what they want to major in or what career opportunities are available to them.

A fourth category is the student who has chosen a field of study (e.g., engineering or architecture) but needs preparatory work in order to meet the admission requirements of that program. All of these students will find the assistance they need by enrolling as General Studies students.

General Studies advisers cooperate with all eight undergraduate degree-granting colleges on campus as well as the UNO- and UNMC-based programs by providing general academic assistance to students wanting to explore different majors before making a decision about a particular college. One of the strengths of General Studies is its unique position with regard to academic advising. Professional advisers in the Division are qualified to advise students interested in any of the eight UNL undergraduate colleges. By working closely with all of the colleges and with other programs on campus, the adviser can help students design a general academic plan for one or more semesters that will allow them to progress toward a degree, while exploring the variety of opportunities offered by the University.

Since General Studies does not offer a degree program, most students are encouraged to transfer to one of the eight undergraduate colleges by the end of their freshman year. Some will transfer before that time while others may remain in General Studies longer if they have not met all of the admission requirements for their chosen college, such as a specific grade point average (GPA). Once they have chosen a college, it is in the best interest of students to transfer out of General Studies into that college without delay as it is important for them to make connections with faculty and staff in their academic program.

ADMISSION

Program Admission

Students who have met the overall University admission requirements established by the Board of Regents are eligible for admission to General Studies. The University admission requirements are outlined in detail on the Admissions site at http://admissions.unl.edu/.

Some UNL colleges have admission requirements in addition to the overall University admission requirements, and General Studies students will be advised accordingly as they choose the majors they would like to pursue in their chosen colleges.

Students desiring to transfer from other institutions and enroll in General Studies at UNL must have a cumulative grade point average of C (2.0 GPA on a 4.0 scale) or above. Students who do not meet this requirement may appeal their admission status to the Director of Admissions.

Admission Deficiencies/Removal of Deficiencies

General Studies students who enter the University with one or more course deficiencies (according to the 1997 Admissions Standards) must remove all deficiencies (except those in modern language) within their first 30 credit hours or their first twelve months of continuous enrollment, whichever takes longer. Deficiencies in modern language must be removed within the first 60 credit hours or the first twenty-four months of continuous enrollment, whichever takes longer. Students who enter the University with a math deficiency must take a math course their first semester in attendance and continue taking math until they have successfully removed the deficiency.

General Studies students who lack one or more of the high school units required for admission to any of the eight undergraduate colleges will be advised of the procedure for removing the deficiency by their General Studies adviser. Most UNL colleges expect these deficiencies to be removed by the end of the first year at the University.

ADVISING

Academic Advising

General Studies does not assign students an academic adviser. Students may see any adviser in the Division. The office has daily walk-in hours (no appointment is necessary). Students should consult with their advisers frequently to discuss their academic program, career interests, course selections, specific college admission and graduation requirements, University procedures and policies and other matters of concern to them.

Since the General Studies advisers work closely with advisers in the eight undergraduate colleges on campus, a student will be able to take courses that meet several college requirements while deciding on a major. This opportunity allows the student to explore possible areas of interest before declaring a major.

Once a student has selected a major or college, the General Studies adviser will review the admission requirements with the student and outline the steps necessary to matriculate in the newly-selected major and college.

Student Responsibility

General Studies students should meet with their academic adviser at least two times each semester. We encourage students to seek advisement whenever they have questions related to their academic major and or interests.

ACE REQUIREMENTS

All University of Nebraska students are required to complete general education courses. Students new to UNL must complete the Achievement-Centered Education requirements (ACE). See the ace.unl.edu Web site for details.

During their first year at UNL, students should also enroll in exploratory courses to help them identify majors of interest. Please refer to the Division of General Studies Web site (http://www.unl.edu/dgs) for an up-to-date list of exploratory courses (listed by major) .

Students should keep in mind that, in general, 100-level courses are for freshmen, 200-level courses for sophomores, 300-level courses for juniors, and 400-level courses for seniors.

ACADEMIC PROGRAMS & POLICIES

Academic Load

General Studies students may enroll in a maximum of 18 credits in the fall and spring semesters. Students should refer to the Summer Schedule of Classes to determine the number of credits they may enroll in for each of the summer sessions.

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

General Studies students should always seek assistance from their adviser in determining whether they should take a course on the Pass/No Pass option.

Student Recognition

Dean’s List/Degrees with Distinction/Scholarships

Students who complete at least 12 graded semester hours with a 3.60 GPA are eligible for the General Studies Honor Roll.

Transfer Credit Rules

General Studies does not offer a degree. Thus General Studies advisers do not make transfer evaluation decisions. Students transferring into General Studies from outside the University of Nebraska system will need to present a transcript for admission. Courses on the transcript may be viewed as meeting the overall University requirements for admission, but the determination of which of these courses will meet graduation requirements in a specific college cannot be made until the student declares a specific major within one of the eight undergraduate degree-granting colleges. The General Studies adviser can provide a preliminary assessment of which specific courses may be accepted by each of the colleges. This assessment is done in cooperation with the colleges and is subject to their approval upon admission to their program.

###

University Libraries

Dean of Libraries: Joan Giesecke

Associate Dean: Nancy Busch

Associate Dean: Elaine Westbrooks

The Libraries

The University Libraries, comprised of Love Library and six branch libraries, is the single comprehensive research library in Nebraska. The Libraries Encore search interface offers access to a vast array of resources including electronic books, full-text journal articles, and online archival material. Libraries services include in-person, telephone, and online reference and research assistance, specialized subject area research assistance, and interlibrary loan and document delivery services.

For further information, please consult the Libraries’ main page:

Main Libraries page: http://iris.unl.edu/
What’s New: http://www.unl.edu/libr/news/
Encore: http://encore.unl.edu/iii/encore/home?lang=eng
Librarian Subject Specialties: http://www.unl.edu/libr/liaison/subjsubj.shtml

Courses of Instruction

LIBR 110. Introduction to Library Research (1 cr) A seven-week independent learning course.

The course provides the skills necessary for doing college-level research:

Identifying various information types and when to use them
Developing strong search strategies
Recognizing and avoiding plagiarism
Evaluating online and print information
Utilizing the resources of a large academic library

Course of Instruction

Students are recommended to take Library 110 in their first or second year
Designed to support the research activities done for other UNL courses

Grading

Course is Pass/No Pass
P (Pass) is interpreted to mean a grade of C or better.
A student who earns a C- or lower will receive a grade of N.

Grading Appeals

A student who feels s/he has been unfairly graded may take the following sequential steps:

1. Talk with the course instructor.

2. Talk with the instructor’s department chair.

Reserve Officer Training Corps (ROTC)

Reserve Officer Training Corps (ROTC)

Information about the Reserve Officer Training Corps (ROTC) program is available on the UNL Army, Navy, Marines and Air Force ROTC Web sites.

Military Science/Army ROTC

Chair: MAJ John Blankenhorn

110 Pershing Military & Naval Science Building

www.unl.edu/armyrotc

Naval Science/Navy ROTC

Chair: CAPT Jeffrey Whiting

103 Pershing Military and Naval Science Building

http://www.unl.edu/nrotc/

Aerospace Studies/Air Force ROTC

Chair: Lt Colonel Stephen Gibson

209 Pershing Military and Naval Science Building

http://www.unl.edu/afrotc/

For the policy regarding elective credit in Military Science, Naval Science, or Aerospace Studies, students majoring in the College of Arts and Sciences and College of Architecture should contact their academic adviser.

Military Science/Army ROTC

Military science is a United States Army ROTC program offered at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln through a cooperative effort contractually agreed to by the United States Army and the University.

Objectives

Prepare, graduate and commission students with leadership potential to serve as commissioned officers in the Regular Army, United States Army Reserve and National Guard components
Develop leadership skills, managerial skills and a basic understanding of associated professional knowledge with a strong sense of personal integrity, honor and individual responsibility

Benefits

Academic credits earned may apply toward the student’s degree depending on the discipline
Students earn a commission as Second Lieutenant in the United States Army concurrent with an academic degree in a discipline of choice
Receive leadership training designed to qualify graduates for civilian careers in executive and management positions upon completion of their military commitment
Uniforms, textbooks and equipment are provided to the student

Curriculum

Military science is an elective program, not an academic major.

Four-year program:

The Army ROTC four-year program consists of two parts, Basic Course and Advanced Course.

Basic Course: One basic level military science course (MLSC 101, MLSC 102, MLSC 201, and MLSC 202) is taken each semester in conjunction with one lab session per week during the freshman and sophomore years. Students may participate in the Army ROTC basic level courses without incurring any military obligation.
Advanced Course: One advanced level military science course (MLSC 301, MLSC 302, MLSC 401, and MLSC 402) is taken each semester along with one lab session per week during the junior and senior years. Military science advanced courses may only be taken by students who are contracting to earn a commission and have completed Basic Course (or equivalency).

Two-year program:

The Army ROTC two-year program accommodates upperclass students already enrolled at or transferring to UNL who have not taken the Basic Course. To participate in this program, the student shall have successfully completed the Leader’s Training Course (LTC), Army Basic Combat Training, or alternate approved training during the summer before entering the advanced course.

Commissioning Requirements

Upon graduation from Army ROTC, you will have the opportunity to be commissioned into the Active Army, Army Reserve, or Army National Guard as a Second Lieutenant if you have met the following requirements:

Satisfactory completion of:

The Basic Course (via class attendance and/or placement credit)
The Advanced Course
Leader Development and Assessment Course
A course in Military History (HIST 303 or HIST 304)

The cadet must:

Maintain at least a 2.0 cumulative grade point average (GPA).
Pass a Department of Defense medical examination within 24 months of the date of commissioning.
Pass the Army Physical Fitness Test within 30 days of the date of commissioning.
Not have exceeded the 32nd birthday (27th for scholarship students) by December 30 of the year of commissioning.

For information on financial assistance, Army ROTC scholarships, Army ROTC courses and general information about the UNL Army ROTC program, visit www.unl.edu/armyrotc.

Naval Science/Navy ROTC

The Naval Reserve Officer Training Corps (NROTC) is a competitive program designed for the purpose of educating men and women for service as commissioned officers in the United States Navy and Marine Corps. Students accepted into the program receive training and experience in the one quality that will always be in great demand: Leadership. Upon commissioning, University of Nebraska NROTC graduates serve in such diverse fields as aviation, surface warfare, submarine warfare, nursing, and as United States Marines.

Benefits

Most NROTC Midshipmen receive a scholarship covering full tuition and fees, a stipend for books, and a monthly stipend to help cover living expenses.
There is also a non-scholarship program for students who did not initially qualify for a scholarship but are interested in a career in the United States Navy or United States Marine Corps.
All NROTC students receive their full uniform.

Curriculum

Four-Year Scholarship Program

Four-Year NROTC scholarships are awarded annually based on a competitive selection process in which consideration is given to factors such as high school record, college board scores, extracurricular activities, and leadership qualities. The primary applicant to this program is a high school senior, but college freshman may also qualify.

Two-Year Scholarship Program

Two-Year NROTC scholarships are awarded to current students that are approaching their junior year. Consideration is given to factors such as performance in college and leadership potential. Recipients of this scholarship attend a six-week naval indoctrination program in Rhode Island the summer before their junior year.

College Program

A non-scholarship program designed for students that did not qualify or are not interested in an NROTC Scholarship. Students in the College Program are fully integrated in the NROTC program and qualify for the same careers in the Navy and Marine Corps upon graduation. There is also opportunity for College Program students to compete for NROTC scholarships after one or more semesters of exemplary performance.

For information on financial assistance, Navy and Marine Corps ROTC Scholarships, and general information about the UNL Naval ROTC program, visit http://www.unl.edu/nrotc/

Naval Science Open Curriculum

Any University of Nebraska–Lincoln student may take naval science academic courses for college credit. However, enrollment in leadership laboratories is restricted to students who are formally enrolled in the NROTC program. Texts and equipment for naval science courses are provided free. No active duty obligation is incurred.

Integrated Studies Minor in Naval Science

It is possible to minor in naval science under the integrated studies program of the College of Arts and Sciences. All interested students enrolled in that college are eligible.

An integrated minor requires a minimum of 25 credit hours, including 10 in one department. The choice in the naval science minor is made from the list of courses that follows. Approval of the course of study must be obtained from the student’s arts and sciences adviser and endorsed by a representative of the dean of the College of Arts and Sciences.

This integrated minor is available also to College of Agriculture and College of Education and Human Sciences students with the approval of their advisers.

NOTE: Although students may take additional naval science courses beyond the 12-credit-hour maximum, credit in these will not count toward a degree in the College of Arts and Sciences. Students majoring in the College of Arts and Sciences may only count up to 12 credit hours in naval science courses toward their degree. Courses cross listed between naval science and other departments of the College of Arts and Sciences are not included in this restriction.

Students enrolled in the NROTC program must take 17 credits in naval science subjects to earn a commission and should schedule HIST 304 and ALEC 302 at the time of asking their College of Arts and Sciences adviser for approval of their program.

Aerospace Studies/Air Force ROTC

Students who are considering seeking a commission in the Armed Forces should be aware that Department of Defense regulations impose standards of personal and sexual conduct on Armed Forces personnel, as reflected in the Uniform Code of Military Justice, which may not be consistent with University Equal Opportunity standards. For information on these policies contact any one of the commanders of UNL’s ROTC programs or Student Legal Services.

The Department of Aerospace Studies is a United States Air Force ROTC program offered at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln through a cooperative effort contractually agreed to by the Air Force and the University.

Eligibility and Enrollment

Aerospace Studies classes are open to all full-time students at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln, as well as students at Nebraska Wesleyan University, Doane College (Crete), and Concordia University (Seward), who have “visiting student” arrangements with the University of Nebraska for Air Force ROTC. Students register for Aerospace Studies the same way they sign up for any other course on campus. In addition to academic class, students are registered for the corresponding leadership lab.

To contract with the Air Force at the start of the junior year or upon receipt of a scholarship, you must be a United States citizen and meet age and other requirements.

Programs

You can participate in Air Force ROTC by enrolling in either the Four-Year or Three-Year program.

Scholarships/Benefits

High school and college students compete for Air Force ROTC college scholarships. The scholarships provide full tuition, fees, and textbook allowance. Students on scholarship also receive a monthly tax-free allowance during the school year that ranges from $300-$500.

Curriculum

Any University of Nebraska–Lincoln, Doane College, Nebraska Wesleyan, and Concordia University student may take Aerospace Studies academic courses for college credit. Textbooks are free and provided by the Aerospace Department. No active duty obligation is incurred. Leadership laboratories are open only to students eligible for, and enrolled in, the Air Force ROTC program.

Credit Hours

Credit hours earned by students enrolled in Aerospace Studies may be used to fulfill elective credit hour requirements for graduation for any college in the University.

Military Obligation

No military obligation results from enrolling in the freshman or sophomore courses in Aerospace Studies. A military obligation occurs only when a student enters the junior year of the program or accepts an Air Force ROTC scholarship. Students who complete Air Force ROTC are commissioned Second Lieutenants and will go on active duty in the United States Air Force after graduation from the University. The active duty service commitment varies from 4-10 years. (Pilots, navigators, and air battle managers incur a longer active duty commitment.)

Delay for Graduate Education. An Air Force ROTC student is commissioned upon graduation from the University. If students are qualified for and interested in working toward advanced degrees, deferment from active duty may be possible until graduate degrees have been completed.

Field Training Program

Each student who successfully receives a competitive allocation to enter the junior year professional officer course (POC) program must attend one field training encampment. This training is held at Maxwell AFB, AL, during the summer between their sophomore and junior year. Field training emphasizes development of leadership abilities and informs students of the many challenging career opportunities available in the Air Force. Students receive travel allowances and pay for field training. All accommodations, clothing, and food are furnished. Successful completion of field training is required to enter the POC.